This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 18
A 1,000 lǐ journey alone
Yúnchǎng, halt!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúnchǎng
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Yúnchǎng, why are you in such a rush?
In the past, I submitted myself to you, Chancellor.
Now that I know my master is at Héběi,
how could I not think of going back?
I constantly tried to tell you but was never met.
Hence, I wrote a letter bidding farewell.
I left my riches and hung my seal to repay you, sir.
I really hope you, sire, did not forget our promises.
If I were to win the trust of the world...
How could I go back on my words?
I fear you might lack some tools,
so here are some gifts for your journey!
Chancellor's has been generous, so I do not lack in gold.
Please give this gold to the soldiers instead.
Such a meager gift is poor
compensation for thy peerless service!
Such service is not worth mentioning.
Yúnchǎng, you are a righteous man within the realm.
It is my misfortune that I can't keep you.
Please accept this silk cloak as a token of my sincerity!
Chancellor!
Many thanks, sire, for this cloak!
Xǔ Chǔ
Styled: Zhòngkāng
Such an arrogant man!
Why can't we seize him?
Yúnchǎng is but one man on one horse, while we are of many!
Why wouldn't he be suspicious?
I have spoken. We will not pursue.
How Yúnchǎng fades away...
General Guān!
Who are you? Please tell me your name.
I am from Xiāngyáng. My name is Liào Huà, styled Yuánjiǎn!
Through these troubled times I've roamed as a drifter
I had to rob people to survive.
Just now, my companion Dù Yuǎn
went down the mountain to patrol.
Liào Huà
Styled: Yuánjiǎn
We mistakenly kidnapped
your ladies up the mountain.
Only later I learned from my followers they're the Imperial Uncle's wives!
I also found out the general was to escort them here,
so I brought them down the mountain.
Yet Dù Yuǎn had ill thoughts, wanting to harm them.
I had no choice but to kill him.
Now, I come down to
beg forgiveness from you!
Where are the two ladies?
General, please look!
You must be scared.
Lady Mí
Had it not been for General Liao, we would have been shamed by Dù Yuǎn.
Lady Gān
Thank you, sir!
I have long heard of your esteemed name, sir!
I am fortunate to meet you today!
If you are willing to, I
would serve you with my life.
You have proven yourself a righteous man.
I am lucky to meet you today.
I will repay you for sure in the future.
But if I must seek my lord across a thousand lǐ,
roaming without end,
I wish to escort the two ladies' carriage alone.
If you say such, then I, Liào Huà, must bid farewell.
If I can be of service in the future, I am yours to command!
Who is approaching?
I am the master of the mansion ahead.
Please come and have some rest.
If so, please allow me to discuss this with everyone.
I am escorting my two sisters-in-laws
over a thousand lǐ. It is a heavy responsibility and a long trip,
so please, sire, forgive me for not drinking anything.
A true hero!
I have a son named Hú Bān,
He now serves under the
Administrator of Xíngyáng, Wáng Zhí.
If you pass through Xíngyáng,
I have a letter to send to my little son.
May I trouble you with this matter?
I will accept this, sir!
May I ask, good sir, where are we at?
Not too far is the choke-point to three provinces, Dōnglǐng-Pass.
Many thanks, sire!
Dōnglǐng
Pass
General, your destination?
Kǒng Xiù
I've bid farewell to the Chancellor and
am going to Héběi to find my brother.
Oh yes, Yuán Shào of Héběi is the
Chancellor's nemesis.
For you to pass, you must have
the Chancellor's document.
I left in a hurry and was unable to get them.
Without the documents,
you must stop and settle within the pass.
Wait for me to send for the Chancellor, and then I can let you pass.
If I wait until you send for the Chancellor, would that not delay my journey?
You have no choice.
If I can't see the Chancellor's documents for a day, then you must wait for a day.
If I can't see it for a year,
general, then you can only wait for a year.
You refuse to give passage to me?
If you want to pass,
you'll have to leave the old and young as a gauge.
You dare try to pass?
Die!
Stop running!
I had no choice but to kill Kǒng Xiù! The rest of you are innocent.
I ask of you as witnesses to pass this to Chancellor Cáo.
Tell him Kǒng Xiù wanted to harm me, so I killed him.
Luòyáng
Who goes?
Guān Yǔ. I would walk through this road.
Do you have Chancellor Cáo's documents?
It is an emergency, I couldn't get them!
I, on the Chancellor's orders, am guarding this place,
especially to investigate spies.
If you don't have the documents, then you must be a deserter!
I live by the honour of my word.
I am escorting the Imperial Uncle's two wives and followers only about ten or so.
Please reconsider, administrator, and allow us passage.
If not, blades may be drawn.
Blades may be drawn? So what!
Kǒng Xiù of Dōnglǐng Pass tried to stop me
without cause and is now dead by my blade.
Traitor! The audacity!
Who wants to capture him together?
I want to!
Hán Fú
I had no choice but to fight, I apologize for the horror.
Please rise, brother-in-law.
Thank you, my ladies.
Sìshuǐ
Pass
General Guān!
Biàn Xǐ
General Guān, after you!
Your reputation exceeds you
who wouldn't be awed?
Now you're returning to the
Imperial Uncle! Your loyalty is clear!
General Biàn, you exaggerate!
Of course not. Of course not!
Since the general was fortunate
enough to arrive, I am overjoyed!
I left Xǔdū to find my elder brother,
and there were many dangers along the way.
Who would knew I would meet the pass guards Kǒng Xiù, Hán Fú, and Mèng Tǎn,
who caused trouble without sympathy in my quest to find my brother.
They wanted a fight, so I had no choice but to kill them.
You were justified!
If I see the Chancellor, I'll be sure to exonerate you in front of him.
General Biàn, you are generous and just. I thank you.
You praise me too highly!
Note: Emperor Míng of Hàn, 28 CE to 75 CE
General, this place, since Emperor Míng's reign, was called the Fragrant Flame Garden.
During Dǒng Zhuó's rule, it was abandoned, but the Chancellor had it rebuilt.
You must be tired from escorting the two ladies.
This place is exactly where you can find peace and quiet.
General, please?
Please.
I have already prepared a banquet for you.
Also, this gentleman has been waiting for you.
General Guān, how long has it
been since you have left Púdōng?
Almost twenty years.
General, perhaps you remember me?
General Guān, please!
Come in please!
Please.
General, cheers?
Cheers.
Cheers?
The two ladies are still waiting in the carriage—
Indeed, indeed, let's first serve the two ladies!
Bring tea for the Imperial Uncle's wives.
Yes!
General, cheers?
Cheers.
What you, sir, have said just now, is that
I, having left for many years, can no longer recognize you.
Indeed! Indeed!
General, my old home was directly across the river from yours.
I wish to dine with the general alone, Why are you here blabbering!?
It's okay, it's okay.
When old neighbors happen to meet, how could we not reminisce?
Cheers.
General Guān, the banquet has been prepared for you.
General Guān, please come!
Please?
After you?
After you.
General Guān!
General Biàn, did you invite me out of kindness...
... or out of malice?!
H-How could there be malice...?
Get him, now!
General Guān!
I thought you a decent man, yet you dare to do this!
General! General! Mercy!
If not for you, sir, we would have been dead.
This is no place here to take shelter.
You should pack up and search elsewhere.
Take care, sire.
We will meet again.
General, take good care.
Xíngyáng
Sir, you have escorted your carriage all the way here.
Wáng Zhí
Now that there's a place to rest in,
what harm is there in one cup of wine?
Ah, you might not know, administrator,
but considering the two ladies presence, I need to mind myself.
Please forgive me, Administrator.
General, I've long heard of your integrity.
If that is really so, then I won't be forceful.
If I am being inconvenient, then
I wouldn't dare trouble you with such an ask.
General, do as you wish. I will take my leave.
Administrator, please!
Come! Administrator Wáng has brought food and wine.
Let the two ladies eat first.
Yes, sir!
Tonight, get a thousand soldiers
and surround the inn.
Have every person light a torch and burn it down at the third watch.
Burn everyone on sight.
I'll bring troops to support you.
Once successful, I'll petition the Chancellor
to have you rewarded handsomely.
I shall obey your orders!
Hú Bān
Hurry! There, there!
Hurry! Hurry up!
I've long heard of Guān Yúnchǎng's fame,
but never knew what he looked like.
I must have a look at him.
Truly a man of divinity!
Who is outside?
The subordinate to the administrator of Xíngyáng, Hú Bān.
Are you not the son of Lord Hú Huá?
Indeed.
Along the road, your father received me with kindness!
Here is his family letter.
You've arrived at a perfect time!
Thank you, General.
To harm a high-hearted man, would shame my name for generations...
General, please forgive me!
How come?
Wáng Zhí wants to harm you in order to avenge his relative, Adminstrator Hán!
He's ordered me to surround the inn on all sides, bury you in wood and grass,
and set fire at the third watch!
Such vileness... Must be answered with blades drawn!
General! General, Wáng Zhí has made preparations!
He has laid an ambush!
Though the general is a match for a thousand men, the carriage you escort may come to harm.
Better to quickly stow the baggage. I’ll go open the gates.
Let the general leave the city.
Indeed.
General, don't delay!
Servants!
Here!
Stow the carriage!
Please help the ladies escape!
Yes!
Go!
Hurry, hurry!
General Guān!
I promise to repay you in the future!
General, you need not say more!
Please leave now, and take care!
I don't deserve such grace!
Please general, you have to be quick
I must go back to light the fire!
General, please leave now!
Mount your horse!
Take good care!
Yes!
General, look!
Hú Bān is a kind man.
If Wáng Zhí knew of Hú Bān's actions,
having us leave the city first, and then lighting the fire, he will surely try to harm him.
Let's go, General!
It must be Wáng Zhí coming to kill us!
You escort the carriage away first.
Let me deal with this!
Traitor, don't you dare leave!
You fool!
We had no quarrel!
Why would you burn us?!
Breaching passes, killing my kin,
and you dare say there is no quarrel?!
If you honor my requests, I will let you live.
Your subordinate, Hú Bān, is my friend's son.
He is a virtuous man!
Allow Hú Bān to accompany me, and this matter is settled.
If not, then it will only take a single blow to take your life.
I did want him to leave with you!
Then that's good. Let Hú Bān come out!
Let Hú Bān out to his quisling master!
For Hú Bān's betrayal, I've seen to his death!
Go ahead, take his head with you!
Wáng Zhí
Your life ends here!
Second Uncle!
Border of
Huá Province
General Guān, Liú Xuándé is currently with Yuán Shào,
and Yuán Shào is the Chancellor's rival.
How could the Chancellor let you go there?
Back then, the Chancellor and I made a promise
If I got news of my elder brother,
I would join him without hesitation.
What you have said is what I shall believe.
Liú Yán
There is a checkpoint at the Yellow River, but it's guarded by Xiàhóu Dūn's subordinate, Qín Qí.
Without the Chancellor's documents,
I'm afraid they won't allow you to ferry.
Perhaps sir could some prepare the boats for me?
I'm not trying to stop you, but even having
the ships, I fear the Chancellor may punish me.
I wouldn't dare oppose him.
I happened to save you from danger once.
Now I ask to ferry the river, yet you refuse. Why is that?
Sir may not know this, but General Xiàhóu is among the most favoured by the Chancellor.
If he knew of this, I will be convicted.
So I cannot pass?
I cannot be of assistance.
My utmost apologies, Yúnchǎng.
If your predicament is such, I can only go alone.
Go!
General, take good care along the way!
Who approaches?
Precinct Marquis of Hànshòu, Guān Yǔ!
What's your destination?
I wish to borrow your boats to search for my elder brother in Héběi.
Héběi is in Yuán Shào’s lands.
Qín Qí
Where are the Chancellor's documents?
I am no longer under his rule.
Why would I need it?
Under General Xiàhóu's orders, I am guarding this pass!
Without Chancellor's orders, you shall not pass!
Are you aware of the fates of those who try to stop me?
Yes I have!
If you do know, why do you insist to stop me?
All those killed are but meager rabble!
Do you dare to challenge me?
Can you compare with Yán Liáng or Wén Chǒu?
Loose!
Spare us! Have mercy!
The one who tried to stop me, is dead!
The rest of you don't need to panic!
Prepare a boat for me to cross the river!
Yes!