This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Romance of the Three Kingdoms
Gǔngǔn chángjiāng dōng shì shuǐ
On and on the Great River rolls, racing east.
Lànghuā táo jǐn yīngxióng
Of proud and gallant heroes its white-waves leave no trace.
Shìfēi chéngbài zhuǎn tóu kōng
As right and wrong, glory and fall,
fade at once into unreal.
Qīngshān yījiù zài
Yet ever the green hills stay—
Jǐ dù xīyáng hóng
— to blaze in the west-waning day.
Bái fà yú qiáo jiāng zhǔ shàng
Fishers and woodsmen comb on the river isles—
Guàn kàn qiūyuè chūnfēng
White-crowned, looking on
the autumn moons and spring breezes.
Yī hú zhuó jiǔ xǐ xiāngféng
With a jar of wine, they merrily gather.
Gǔjīn duōshǎo shì
The countless tales of present and past —
Jiē fù xiào tán zhōng
— all in their jests.
Yī hú zhuó jiǔ xǐ xiāngféng
With a jar of wine, they merrily gather.
Gǔjīn duōshǎo shì
The countless tales of present and past—
Jiē fù xiào tán zhōng
— all in their jests.
Act 2
The Battle of Red Cliffs
Episode 23
Leap over Tán-Creek
After unifying the northern realms —
— Cao Cao ordered to build "Bronze Sparrow Terrace" on the bank of the Zhang-River —
Note: "Bronze Sparrow Terrace" (铜雀台) was a real terrace located in Yè-city, Hebei.
— to commemorate his great achievement.
He garrisoned his troops around Xǔchāng and fiefed them land to cultivate, to build up their strength-
— and prepare for his expedition southwards: First to conquer the Jing-Province, then take lands of Wú.
Liu Bei turned to Liu Biao in Jing-Province
after his defeat at Runan.
When Cao Cao warring in the north,
Xǔchāng was weakly defended.
Liu Bei proposed an attack on Xǔchāng several times —
— but his proposals were never accepted by Liu Biao.
In the spring of the 12th year of Jian'an period*—
*207 AD
—Liu Biao's surrendered generals, Zhang Wu and Chen Sun, rebelled at Jiangxia.
Liu Bei led Guan Yu, Zhang Fei, and Zhao Yun
on a punitive expedition—
— and crushed the rebellion of Chen Sun and Zhang Wu.
My lord!
Zǐlóng, you truly are a valiant warrior!
Zhào Yún
Styled: Zǐlóng
Good horse!
Lord Xuande.
You've done a marvelous job.
The rebellion at Jiangxia has been crushed—
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
— and the people can live in peace.
I must say that all the credit should go to you!
Liú Biǎo
Styled: Jǐngshēng
I've prepared a banquet in your honor
to celebrate the triumph.
I serve under your command.
It is my duty to repay your kindness with gratitude.
My brother—
after you.
After you, brother Jǐngshēng.
It's a good horse.
A great horse.
Cài Mào
Styled: Déguī
This was Zhang Wu's horse.
A good horse indeed!
Brother, since you like this horse this much,
then I'd like to offer it to you!
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Oh! My brother, that will do!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
Note: The choreography depicts the characters "迎皇叔" or "Welcome, Uncle."
Yī Jí
Styled: Jībó
Good.
Please.
My brother, please.
With your great talent
Jing-Province can be safe now.
Though the rebellion of Jiangxia has been crushed —
— the nine commanderies and forty-two counties of Jing aren't free from outside disturbances.
Attacks and harassments by
the Nanyue are still troubling.
And the strong forces of Zhāng Lǔ and Sūn Quán
have only added to my worries.
You don't need to worry,
my three warrior-generals will be enough.
Zhang Fei can guard the southern border along Nanyue.
Guan Yu can defend the city of Guzi
to be a deterrent force to Zhang Lu.
And Zhao Yun can patrol the Three Rivers
to watch out for Sun Quan.
Note: The Three Rivers aka. Sānjiāng
So brother, are you still worried?
Well in that case, Jing-Province will be safe!
That Liu Bei harbors ill will.
He had to come to Jing-Province after his defeat by Cao Cao.
He had nowhere else to seek refuge.
Today he came back in triumph, and tried his best to win the favor of my brother-in-law.
Now, he managed to appoint three of
his warrior-generals to important posts.
So, the defense of Jing-Province —
Lady Cài
— has fallen into the hands of Liu Bei and has subordinates?
Liu Bei's generals are at three key strategic positions, while he himself stays here.
As I see it, the longer this goes, the more disastrous it will be for us.
I've often heard from your brother-in-law —
that Liu Bei is a man of profound ambition and a great shrewdness, like a closed book.
That's why you must prevent my brother-in-law —
— from handing over Jing-Province to Liu Bei.
Attendant!
I have to go.
Please look for a chance to persuade my brother-in-law.
Yes, I know.
Attendant!
Why am I lying here?
You got drunk at the banquet and was brought back in.
Indeed, I was in high spirits.
I guess I did drink a little too much.
I find you've indeed become muddle-headed.
Otherwise, why would you entrust the defense of Jing-Province to outsiders so easily?
What do you mean?
I hear you've assigned the defense of Jing-Province to the three generals under Liu Bei's command.
His men are all valiant and fierce. I like them!
How can you trust other people?
I hear that since his arrival in Jing-Province, Liu Bei has been getting along with the officials and officers.
You can't be caught off guard by this kind of person.
Besides, he's assigned his generals to important places.
While he himself remains in the city!
If anything should go wrong one day, how would you deal with all this?
Liu Bei is a kind and righteous person
Let us not suspect him without evidence.
After Liu Bei's defeat at Runan, none of the lords dared to shelter him.
Nobody had kindness like you.
I think it'd be for the best to send Liu Bei out of Jing-Province.
My lord!
Good horse!
Truly a good horse!
My lord!
This horse must not be ridden.
Why not?
Lord, this horse has "tear tracks" under its eyes
Its name is 'Dilu'. It will harm its rider.
Zhang Wu died because of this horse.
My lord should never ride it.
My lord—
"Dilu" is a good horse indeed.
However, good horses should be used for close combat on the battlefield.
Liu Xuande is a veteran warrior of countless battles.
As the saying goes:
A treasured horse matches only a gallant warrior.
It will be proper to offer back the horse
to its master, Liu Xuande.
My brother.
What have you come here for, my brother?
I've been sitting all day doing nothing,
so I've come here to practice riding to pass the time.
If you find days dragging on—
— you could lead your troops to Xinye County in Xiāngyáng, and station them there for the moment.
It's a prosperous place with ample provisions to support a battalion.
Besides, staying still for too long would only be a waste of your martial talents.
Good idea.
I'm grateful for that great steed you gave me the other day—
— but you are a soldier, fighting on the battlefield. You need a great steed.
I shouldn't have taken the horse away from you.
So I give it back to you now.
In that case, I can't but take the horse back.
Many thanks, my brother.
Excuse me, Lord Xuande.
May I know your name, sir?
I am Yī Jí,
an apparitor of Jing-Province.
Is there anything you'd like to tell me?
General, this horse must not be ridden.
Please tell me the reason.
You gave it to Lord Liu Biao, didn't you?
Well, he has returned it to me.
That is because Kuǎi Yuè told Lord Liu Biao  —
that this horse is named "Dilu" and it will harm its rider.
That's why Lord Liu Biao returned the horse
back to you. How can you ride it again?
Thank you for your kindness, I did not know that.
However, everyone has his destiny. How can a horse change it?
Well said.
You're known as a kindhearted and righteous man.
If you don't mind,
I'd like to pay a visit to you at Xinye some day.
Thank you, you're flattering me.
You're welcome at my place any time.
You are so kind.
Goodbye.
A few days ago, Lady Gān dreamed that she had swallowed the stars of the Big Dipper.
Note: The turtle-shells and sticks on Sun Qian's table are part of historical Chinese divination.
Lord, this is a good omen!
Sūn Qián
Styled: Gōngyòu
The baby to be born
must be a man of great expectation.
Is this a good omen?
For certain!
You are about to get an honorable son!
My congratulations!
Go and find out if the baby is a boy or a girl.
It's a boy! Congratulations!
Things turned out as expected!
My congratulations.
Congratulations, my elder brother!
My elder brother, give a name to my nephew!
Right, think of a name with good omen.
That's right! Let's think of a name... think of a name...
Well, since my lady dreamed of swallowing the Big Dipper —
we may give him the name Ēdǒu!
*(or  Ādǒu. "Dǒu" means the Big Dipper)
Good!
Congratulations, my elder brother! You now have a son, and the Hàn Dynasty has a successor!
Go and have a look at my nephew!
Let's go! Quick!
Lord Xuande, congratulations!
Many thanks, sir!
It's kind of you to come to me in person.
Excuse me for not coming to meet you earlier.
Lord Liu Biao sent me
to invite you to Jing-Province for a talk.
All right.
My brother, I see you are getting light-headed.
We'd better stop drinking.
You are better than me.
I have no one to talk to about my worries.
What a shame.
Don't worry.
If there is anything the matter, you can just tell me.
Cao Cao is in the capital of Xǔ with his soldiers back from his northern conquests.
The Yuán clan of Hebei have all been eliminated —
— Cao Cao must have already begun planning to taking over the Jing-Province.
Back then, I didn't heed your advice and attack Cao Cao while he was away.
I lost a good opportunity. Now how much I regret!
My brother, there is no need to worry.
Right now, the Empire is still in disarray.
War breaks out everyday.
There will be other opportunities.
Brother, why are you so sad?
I have been trying to tell you my worries.
But I have never had a chance.
You don't have to worry.
If I am of any help to you —
— By hook or by crook, I will do anything for you.
I am worried about my two sons.
My former wife gave birth to my first son, Liú Qí.
He is virtuous, but too weak and timid to manage the state affairs.
My second wife gave birth to my younger son, Liú Cóng.
He's a bright boy, I like him very much.
If I set aside the elder and make the younger my successor.
I'd be going against the way of things.
If I name the elder as my successor,
what can I do with the Cài Family?
The military power in Jing-Province is in their hands —
— and they are sure to cause trouble in the future.
That's why I'm wavering and can't make the decision, my brother.
This is a matter of your family.
It needs to be considered carefully.
My interference would be improper.
We're just like brothers.
I hope you'll speak without reservations.
Choosing the successor is of extreme importance. One should never act impetuously.
Since the ancient times, removing the elder and choosing the younger—
—has been the source of disaster. Endless trouble will follow.
If you're worried about the Cai-clan's power,
you could reduce it a bit at a time.
You can't make the younger the successor only because you dote on him.
The days and months are slipping by, and I'm becoming old.
But my great deeds are still to be accomplished...
I hear that while you were in Xǔchāng —
—you and Cao Cao talked about heroes over green plums and wine.
You proposed many famous men of our present time —
—but Cao Cao just said that: 'There are only two heroes of these lands, you and himself.'
With all his power and influence，
Cao Cao didn't place himself before you.
Why do you have to worry about great deeds?
My only hurdle is that I don't have any armies or land.
To tell you the truth—
— if I had a real solid base, the lesser men of the world are indeed not worth worrying over!
Please, my brother.
Tonight at midnight,
I will send men to surround Liu Bei's guest-house.
We'll kill him first and then tell my brother-in-law.
Be sure not to leak this out.
Rest assured, my sister.
Sir!
Sir, sir, sir!
Why are you in such a panic?
Lord Xuande—you're still kept in the dark!
Cai Mao has sent troops to kill you tonight! Please return to Xīnyě immediately!
Liu Biao knows nothing about it.
The Cais plans to act first and report later.
There is no time for hesitation!
Sir, this...
How can I go without saying goodbye to Brother Jingsheng?
If you do that, you will be killed by Cai's men for certain!
All right. I will repay your kindness in the future.
-Be quick!
Go! Search it!
Hurry!
There's nobody inside!
Who leaked our plans?
Liu Bei must have gotten away!
After him!
Roger!
"Too long, far too long. I have been stuck—
—gazing at the old mountains and rivers day by day.
A dragon can never be kept in a pond—
—he should ride on the thunder to heaven and beyond."
I will kill this ingrate!
I have been with Xuande quite some time.
I've never seen him write poems.
Could it be a plot by someone else to drive a wedge between us?
Brother-in-law, a person's heart is unpredictable.
Letting Liu Bei go is like releasing a tiger into wilderness.
We should go to Xinye and catch Liu Bei at once
to avoid future trouble.
Don't be reckless. There's no hurry.
We must not lose the opportunity.
Today, you release a tiger into wilderness!
Tomorrow, it will be too late to regret.
My lord.
A letter from Lord Liu Biao.
My elder brother.
My lord.
My three brothers, Mr Sun.
Lord Liu Biao has sent me a letter —
— asking me to preside over the Harvest Festival in Xiāngyáng on his behalf.
What do you say to it?
Well...
Why can't he himself preside over the festival?
Jingsheng is not in good health recently.
His two sons are too young.
He is afraid of a violation of etiquette if they preside.
That's why I am asked to preside on his behalf.
The other day, you returned in a hurry from Jing-Province, disturbed.
I think something must have gone wrong in Jing-Province.
You shouldn't go to this festival without preparation.
When Brother Jingsheng and I had a drink, I made an indiscreet remark
But Brother Jingsheng didn't blame me.
Only Lady Cai and Cai Mao tried to murder me.
Thanks to Yi Ji's timely warning,
I was able to escape to Xīnyě before dawn.
Today's invitation to the festival...
I do not know how it will turn out.
You suspect that you made an indiscreet remark, but Lord Liu Biao didn't blame you.
We can't easily trust words of outsiders
Xiāngyáng is not far away from here.
If you don't go, Lord Liu Biao will genuinely become suspicious.
Yunchang has a good point.
Elder brother, one can't be too careful.
There are no 'good' banquets.
*Alludes to the Hongmen Banquet
It's better not to go.
My two elder brothers both have a point.
If you don't go, Lord Liu Biao would be suspicious.
If you go, Cai Mao might intend to murder you.
My lord, I think you should go.
I will lead three hundred soldiers to escort you and make sure nothing happens to you.
This is the best way.
Pass on my orders:
Nothing is to be told to anyone.
Those who disobey will be put to death.
Yes, sir!
General.
General. Seeing your actions,
I feel something is going to happen.
Liu Bei is a 'mighty raptor' of our time.
Note: A "Mighty Raptor" or "Xiāoxióng"(枭雄) is a term used for fierce, ambitious and formidable "great men" of history.
He'll be a source of trouble if he stays here long.
We're going to kill him today.
No!
Today, the officials from the nine commanderies and forty-two counties are all at the banquet.
Such an act may make lose their favor.
I have secret orders from my lord.
Well, in that case, we will do as he says.
The east, north and south gates of Xiāngyáng city
are guarded by my brothers.
Only the west gate is left open,
because the Tán-Creek blocks the passage.
Even with tens of thousands of troops,
one could not get across that.
If Liu Bei's officers follow and protect him, it would be hard to attack.
I've already placed five hundred men in ambush inside the city.
You can tell Wén Pìn and Wang Wei —
— to arrange another table in the outer hall
and treat the officers.
First, separate Liu Bei from his officers.
Then you can strike.
Good idea!
My lord!
Lord Liu.
Lord Liu, excuse me for not coming to meet you earlier.
General Cai, you are so kind.
Excuse me for being late.
No, you're just in time.
General Zhao, this way please.
Lord Liu, this way please.
Uncle, my father is feeling unwell and could not come.
Liú Cóng
The officials from the counties are all present. Please preside at the ceremonies on his behalf.
Please, uncle.
I normally wouldn't dare undertake such a heavy task.
But since it's my brother's order—
—I dare not refuse.
Sirs, please.
Please.
Lord Liu, please.
My lord.
Everybody, please.
Lord Liu, please.
Please.
General Zhao.
The banquet is ready in the side chamber
and your presence is expected.
Thank you two generals, but you don't need to mind me.
I can't drink alcohol.
Wén Pìn
Styled:Zhòng Yè)
Lord Liu.
The officers would like to drink with General Zhao.
What would you say to it?
Zilong. Yes, it's ok to listen to them.
Take a seat at the banquet.
Please.
My two young lords, please.
Please, uncle.
General Zhao, please
Uncle, please.
Two young lords, please.
General Zhao, have some more wine.
Thanks. You too, please.
General Zhao, have some more drinks please.
General Zhao, have some more.
General Cai, everything is ready.
Good.
When the drum is beat, you will all strike.
Don't let Liu Bei get away.
Yes, sir!
Come, come!
Good, good!
Uncle, please.
Come on, General Zhao!
Uncle—please!
My two young lords, please.
General Zhao, have another cup.
May I show you the restroom, Lord Xuande?
A toast to General Zhao!
Have another cup!
Can you even have another? Haha!
Ah, okay.
Uncle, please do as you please.
Another toast to General Zhao!
Good, General Zhao, good!
General Zhao, please finish this cup.
Good, good, good, good! Hahaha...
Cai Mao has planned to murder you.
Soldiers have laid an ambush in the city.
The east, north and south gates of the city are heavily guarded.
Only the west gate is left open.
You should leave here immediately.
Then farewell.
Fine.
Come on, General Zhao, drink! Drink!
Go!
Stop! Stop!
Report to General Cai
Liu Bei rode out of the west gate!
Yes, sir!
Quick! Be sure to capture Liu Bei! Go!
General Zhao, have another glass!
Hurry up, chase him!
Dilu, hurry up!
Liu Bei, stop!
Liu Bei, stop! Don't let Liu Bei escape!
Dilu, Dilu, why do you harm your master?
Hurry! Get into the water!
Catch Liu Bei!
Yes, sir!
Catch him!
Dilu!
General Cai, look!
Liu Bei!
Your life ends here!
Dilu, Dilu, you indeed harmed your master!
Heaven is helping him.
Lord Liu, why are you running away from the party?
Cai Mao!
We have no grudge against each other!
Why do you wish for my death!?
I ... I have no such intention!
D–don't be misled by others!
Cai Mao!
My lord is an invited guest!
Why are you chasing him with troops?
Where is my lord?
He's left the banquet. I don't know where he's gone.
I've been looking for him.
But there's no sight of him.
I'll go on looking for him.
If I can't find him,
I will come back for you.
Let's go!
General, you must be Liu Xuande. Am I right?
Country lad, how do you know my name?
I didn't know you.
But my teacher often talks with his visitors.
They say Liu Xuande is a hero of the age, and he would pass here recently!
I find you look like the person they talk about, that's why I asked you.
Who's your teacher?
My master is Sīmǎ Huī.
His style name is Décāo. He's from Yǐngchuān.
His Daoist title is Master Shuǐjìng.*
*Water Mirror
Among his many friends —
— there are Páng Dégōng
and Páng Tǒng  from Xiangyang.
And who are these two Pángs?
They're uncle and nephew.
Páng Dégōng, style name Shanming,
is ten years older than my master.
Páng Tǒng, style name Shìyuán,
he is five yours younger than my master.
My master is very fond of Páng Tǒng
and calls him his younger brother.
Where's your master now?
In the cottage in the woods right ahead.
Just come with me, General Liu.
All right.
Nice place!
The melody is so beautiful.
We may as well listen to it.
Master!
Sīmǎ Huī
Styled: Décāo)
A high note suddenly rang out.
It suggests that a hero must be listening.
This is my master, Master Shuijing.
Sire, today you're fortunate to have a narrow escape.
Please, come in and have a cup of tea.
If sir would please.
The blade's light and sword's shadow fade,
Àndànliao dāoguāngjiànyǐng
Far away is the drum and horn's serenade;
yuǎn qùliao gǔjiǎo zhēng míng
Before my eyes appear, one by one,
Yǎnqián fēiyángzhe yīgè gè
Such vibrant visages.
xiān huó de miànróng
The old paths are buried now—
yānmòliao huáng chén gǔdào
—by a fire burning through every town.
huāngwúliao fēnghuǒ biānchéng
But time, you cannot take away that string—
Suìyuè a nǐ dài bù zǒu, nà yī chuàn chuàn
—of still familiar names.
shúxī di xìngmíng
What man will determine victory or death?
Xīngwáng shéi rén dìng a
Prosperity and decline have no cause, indeed!
shèngshuāi qǐ wú píng a
A single breeze scatters the clouds—
yī yè fēngyún sàn nà
—and the world as we knew it vansih with them.
biànhuànliao shíkōng
Meetings and partings happen for their reasons—
Jù sàn jiē shì yuán a
—but these comings and going still rouse our feelings!
líhé zǒng guān qíng a
We carry the weight of our pasts—
dāndāng shēngqián shì a
—and account little for the opinions left behind.
hé jì shēnhòu píng
The Long River turns to tears—
Chángjiāng yǒuyì huà zuò lèi
—its waters rise in a song;
Chángjiāng yǒuqíng qǐ gēshēng
In the skies of history there yet shines a few stars—
lìshǐ di tiānkōng shǎnshuò jǐ kē xīng
—as in the world of man dwells a spirit of heroism, ever galloping forward.
rénjiān yī gǔ yīngxióng qì zài chíchěng zònghéng