This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 12
White Gate Tower (Part 1)
Cáo Cāo's large army experienced
more than one month of tedious battles.
They eventually conquered
Shòuchūn and routed Yuán Shù.
At this time, Zhāng Xiù and Liú Biǎo
took advantage of Cáo Cāo's absence
from Xǔdū (Xǔchāng) to attack the Central Plains.
Cáo Cāo was forced to lead
his army to defend Xǔdū.
On the 3rd year of the Jiàn'ān era, three more
invasions against Zhāng Xi commenced.
Note: 198-199 AD
Cáo Cāo's army is here!
Run away! Run away!
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Send someone, to inform
all the villagers, far or near,
that I was ordered by the Emperor
to send an army against a rebellion!
However, it coincides with the
harvest season, Lieutenant.
We have to go through the wheat,
but whoever tramples them...
must be beheaded.
Yes!
With strict orders, the people can safely
harvest wheat; no need to be anxious.
Yes!
Halt!
My orders are utmostly important,
so you ought to be careful and obey it as well.
Yes!
Where is the Provost Marshal?
The
Provost Marshal
Here.
My horse trampled the wheat;
how shall I be punished?
Chancellor, how can I punish you?
If I broke the law knowingly, but was absolved,
how could the masses trust us?
Guō Jiā
Styled: Fèngxiào
Chancellor! Chancellor!
Everyone stop!
Do not oppose my orders.
Sir, during the Spring and Autumn period,
those laws were not applied to the venerated.
Sir, you lead a grand army.
How could you harm yourself?
Chancellor! Chancellor!
Since the Spring and Autumn's laws
does not apply to those of esteem,
I will not execute myself for now.
Chancellor!
However, military orders are like mountains,
so although I shall be spared,
Note: This idiom means that military orders cannot be violated, just like how mountains cannot be moved.
I shall substitute my head with my hair.
Chancellor.
Where are we?
20 lǐ ahead is Wǎnchéng.
Where is Yùshuǐ-River?
When we reach the grand mound on the right.
Yùshuǐ-River is below it.
Like a solitary leaf in the wind, I wither.
Born under an unlucky star,
my life has been bitter;
escaping from the chaos, I encountered you.
I am most grateful for
your kindness when we met;
your love brings but temporary happiness.
The beacon signals an auspicious occasion.
Dian Wei
With tears in my eyes for your life,
Cao Ang
Wáng Hòu
wine conceals the scars of warfare.
Dim, so dim is the lamplight;
deep, so deep is this tent.
The soft pouring of wine;
the soft words spoken.
An instant of elation;
an instant of comfort.
Who will understand the meaning of my verse;
who will empathize with the person in this song?
General Dian Wei,
I have come to attend your memorial!
I have lost my beloved
son and nephew...
but I do not mourn so heavily
for them as for General Diǎn Wéi!
But until today,
I haven't even found my general's remains!
Chancellor.
Why not hold a memorial herenow?
A memorial...
for the warriors who fell in battle at Shòuchūn.
A memorial for the supplies overseer, Wáng Hòu.
Correct... we should... we should...
but... but where is Wáng Hòu's head?
Chancellor!
Cáo Cāo subdued Zhāng Xiù once again,
Although he triumphed, his heart
and emotions were but very heavy.
What shall his next step be?
Yuán Shào intended to exploit my invasion against Zhāng Xiù to scout and map Xǔdū (Xǔchāng).
Now he saw me return and used a
deft excuse to conceal his intentions.
That man is indeed hateful.
Yuán Shào is too sordid,
he needs to be fought.
I only regret I am unable to do so.
Gentlemen, do you have any ideas? Do share.
Chancellor.
Fèngxiào, please tell.
As I see it,
(Yuán) Shào has ten disadvantages;
you have ten advantages.
Yuán Shào may have the larger army,
but it is nothing to be fearful of.
I have ten advantages;
Shào has ten disadvantages?
Fèngxiào, elaborate.
Shào is liturgical and doctrinaire,
You are generous and grounded.
In conduct, you win.
Shào is obstinate,
You are flexible.
In popularity, you win.
Ever since the reigns of
Emperors Huán and Líng passed,
the state is injudicious,
Shào even more so.
You strive for efficiency.
In politics, you win.
Shào seems populist but is envious inside.
He gives into nepotism.
You seem critical but are clear-cut inside.
You appoint those of merit.
In magnanimity, you win.
Shào makes plans but can't commit,
you are cunning and decisive.
In strategy, you win.
Shào collects those for fame,
you treat people as they are.
In virtue, you win.
Shào cares for the close but ignores the far.
You worry for all despite distance.
In benevolence, you win.
Shào is flustered by deception
you may be misled but maintain your quo.
In perception, you win.
Shào's sense of right is muddled,
your standards upstanding.
In competency, you win.
Shào loves to make empty threats but lacks tactical ability.
Your armies are less, but can defeat the many
In warfare, you win.
With these ten advantages,
how hard would it be to defeat Yuǎn Shào?
If that is the case,
I shall send an army to attack Yuán Shào.
Having said that,
Chancellor, before you attack Yuán Shào,
we need to settle a major threat
within your heart first.
Major threat?
What major threat in my heart?
Lǚ Bù of Xú-Province.
He is the major threat within your heart.
Chancellor, you can first take on him,
wiping the threats in the southeast,
then plan against Yuán Shào.
If Lǚ Bù, three times a wanton traitor, were left alive, he will become a hazard.
Conquer Lǚ Bù, wipe out this major threat!
Lǚ Bù told me to detain Hán Yìn
and send him to Xǔdū for you to deal with.
Chén Dēng
Styled: Yuánlóng
Lǚ Bù is brave and candid,
but he also acts like a rabid wolf.
He only sees in the short-term, acting with reckless abandon.
My lord, you should plan against him first.
Chén Dēng,
you are the envoy for Lǚ Bù.
Why would you, in front of me, slander your lord?
Eh... my lord.
My ancestral home was in Xú-Province.
I initially assisted Táo Qiān, then Liú Bèi.
But after a drunk Zhāng Fēi bungled matters
and beat up Lǚ Bù's father-in-law,
Lǚ Bù retaliated and seized Xú-Province.
Because my father was still in service to him,
I couldn't abandon him;
I had to bend myself to serve under him.
I had but no choice, that is all.
Forgive me for my inconsiderate assumption.
I hope you will accept it.
I know Lǚ Bù has the wild ambitions of a rabid wolf.
It will be hard to feed him for long.
Sire, what plans do you suggest?
Chancellor, if you decide to act,
I shall serve as your spy.
Good. I shall bestow you the title of
Administrator of Guǎnglíng.
Thank you, Chancellor!
Wait.
I shall entrust the matters of Xú-Province to you.
Can you do it?
Chancellor, rest assured.
General.
Ah, you returned.
Yes.
How is Xǔdū faring?
Lord Cáo presented me 2,000 shí for my father
and appointed me as the
Administrator of Guǎnglíng.
You didn't vouch for me to be
the Potentate of Xú-Province,
but got yourself all the benefits?
Your father advised me to ally with Cáo Cāo,
call off the marriage between Yuán Shù,
and send Hán Yìn for execution.
I expected to be promoted
by now but I got nothing!
Yet you and your father both got noble titles!
You two have betrayed me!
Why are you laughing?
Because of your ignorance to the real meaning!
After I met Lord Cáo, I petitioned for you
to be the Potentate of Xú-Province.
I said, "Supporting Lǚ Bù
would be like raising a tiger."
"You ought to fully feed him
with meat, lest he starts eating men".
Lord Cáo said, "No. I must raise him,"
"not as a tiger, but rather a hawk."
"If the foxes and rabbits aren't rested,"
"you mustn't fully feed the eagle then."
If the eagle is famished, then he is of my use.
"If full, he will surely then fly away."
I then asked Lord Cáo,
"Then who are the foxes and rabbits?"
The reply was,
"Yuán Shù of Huáinán, Sūn Cè of Jiāngdōng,"
"Yuán Shào of Jìzhōu, Liú Biǎo of Jīngxiāng,"
"Liú Zhāng of Yìzhōu, and Zhāng Lǔ of Hànzhōng."
"They are the foxes and rabbits."
Chén Gōng
Styled: Gōngtái
General, no need to be humble!
You've done many great deeds for the empire.
You ought to be ranked among
the Three Excellencies!
Note: The Excellencies are the highest
officials in the Imperial Court
Yuánlóng, you're flattering me.
Gōngtái?
What are you here for?
General, if he has something to say,
let us excuse ourselves.
General, let us take our leave now. Farewell.
Farewell!
Gōngtái, what exactly is wrong?
The father-son duo often flatter
and sweet-talk you, General.
I fear unspeakable motives in their heart.
General, you ought to be on guard.
Or is it that you are slandering
good men for no reason?
Isn't that why you waited?
If you ignore my loyal words,
we will will suffer disaster!
Spare me!
Behead him!
Sire, spare me, please!
Spare me!
Who is this?
Exalted sire, Chancellor Cáo sent me
to deliver Liú of Yù-Province a message!
Liú Bèi replied and sent me back! I just want to go back!
I really don't know what the contents are!
Exalted sires, spare me!
I'm begging you, spare me!
Sires, spare me!
Sires...
Spare me, please!
As my lord has instructed,
The plan against Lǚ Bù continues without hesitation,
but with so few soldiers,
I wouldn't dare take him lightly.
But if Chancellor were to strike,
I could lead the vanguard.
My armies prepared.
I await further orders, sire.
That bastard has the nerve to...!?
Gōngtái, get me-!
Exalted sire, spare me!
Exalted sire, mercy!
Mercy, please!
Xiǎopèi
Liú Bèi! You joined forces with
Cáo Cāo to harm my master!
You better come out and surrender!
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Our city is too small. How can we guard it?
We must think of a plan.
Sūn Qián,
Styled: Gōngyòu
We could ally with Cáo Cāo.
I'll send a message right now.
Good.
Report! Lǚ Bù's general, Zhāng Liáo,
is attacking the Western gate!
Fire!
Halt.
Zhāng Liáo
Styled: Wényuǎn
General Zhāng!
General Guān!
Xiǎopèi's
Western Gate
General Zhāng, we have met each other many a time.
I've long known of your exemplary character!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
But what is Lǚ Bù?
Sir, you should know best!
General, you are man among men. Why debase yourself to serving a bastard of three surnames?
Hold the city. Don't meet them outside!
Yes, sir!
To the Eastern gate!
Open the Eastern gate!
Xiǎopèi's
Eastern Gate
Third Brother!
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Third Brother!
We mustn't underestimate Zhāng Liáo's power.
Furthermore, he is an honorable man.
Having thus spoken, my words will surely
influence him to have regrets at heart;
It is evident he does not want to fight us.
Xǔdū (Xǔchāng)
Lǚ Bù indeed attacked Xiǎopèi.
Lǚ Bù is that brave...
If he allies with Yuán Shù once again,
it would be hard to plan against them.
We can exploit his 'rebellion'
to disrupt the hearts of his people.
Good!
An army to Xú-Province!
Xiàhóu Dūn
Styled: Yuánràng
Report!
Report! Ahead is Lǚ Bù's subordinate
Gāo Shùn! He's blocking the way!
Destroy them!
Charge!
Gāo Shùn
Cáo Xìng
Essence of my father and blood of my mother!
How could I waste it?
Father.
Chén Guī
Father, Lord Cáo has joined forces with
Liú Bèi and have marched here.
I want help them in a major way.
Father, do you have any instructions?
Lord Cáo once said,
"Everything in Xú-Province will be in your hands."
Soon, Lǚ Bù will be defeated.
My son, you ought to exploit the absence of Lǚ Bù
to help Cáo from the inside!
Regarding outside matters,
I will take care of them.
Father, you should ask Lǚ Bù to guard Xú-Province with Mí Zhú.
If Lǚ Bù is routed, he shall not be allowed to enter the city.
The plan is not bad.
However, you will be with Lǚ Bù outside as well.
Your son will find a means of escape.
It is easy to prevent Lǚ Bù from entering the city,
however, his family resides in Xú-Province.
In addition, within the city are many loyalists.
What do to about them?
Of his loyalists and family,
your son has a plan to deal with them.
Father, you may rest assured.
Good. But due to Lǚ Bù's unfaithful and erratic behavior,
my son, you must proceed with caution.
You mustn't be too cocky.
Yes, father.
General!
Yuánlóng.
Here.
Chén Gōng persuaded me to guard Xiāo-Pass.
How to make the Cáo army retreat?
Yuánlóng, explain in detail.
Yes.
General, Cáo Cāo intends to seize Xú-Province this time.
Now Xú-Province is surrounded on all sides, a dangerous position.
General, you should first think of a way to fallback.
General, better to move your provisions and economy to Xiàpī.
That way, if Xú-Province happens to fall,
Xiàpī will be able to supply you.
General, act on this plan as soon as you can.
Yuánlóng, your words are utmostly correct.
Sòng Xiàn and Wèi Xù!
Here!
I want you two to move the provisions and
transfer them to Xiàpī as soon as you can.
And bring my family as well!
Yes, sir!
Yuánlóng!
Here.
Follow me to reinforce Xiāo-Pass.
Heed my orders!
General!
Let me go to Xiāo-Pass first and investigate this Cáo army.
Then you may advance, General.
So this is even better!
General, I will depart now.
Xiāo Pass
Our lord resents you for not advancing.
He will come here to admonish you.
Their army is mighty and
we cannot underestimate them.
My army is here to guard the pass.
I would rather die than lose it!
You may return and inform our lord to
guard Xiǎopèi himself. That is the best plan.
Yes.
Wait.
You mustn't persuade our lord
with a go along with plan to abandon the city.
Yes.
Someone's firing arrows from the wall!
My lord?
Chén Dēng pays his deepest respects to Lord Cáo.
This letter will help you, sire, seize Xiāo-Pass.
Tomorrow night, a fire will start on the city walls,
I will lay a trap that will cause Lǚ Bù and Chén Gōng to fight each other.
Sire, you can then take the pass and reach Xú-Province.
This letter will help you, sire, seize Xú-Province.
When Lǚ Bù retreats to Xú-Province,
my father and Mí Zhú would have already seized control.
Sire must send an army to receive them.
This letter will help you, sire, seize Xiǎopèi.
I will first lure Gāo Shùn and
Zhāng Liáo out of Xiǎopèi,
Sire, can exploit this opportunity,
then Xiǎopèi will belong to you, sire!
Good!
Chén Yuánlóng stands within fierce and bellowing waves,
but toyed with it all!
Good!
General-
Of Xiāo-Pass?
Had I not went there,
it would've been in danger.
Sūn Guān and company dreaded the ferocity of
Cáo's army and wished to surrender the pass.
I have left Chén Gōng to guard it.
General, at night, you ought to reinforce them.
Return to Xiāo-Pass first and inform
Chén Gōng to prevent sedition.
At evening, I shall aid him.
Signal us using a torch and have
Chén Gōng kill the rebels from within.
Yes.
Cáo's army took a small road
and is outside the pass.
I fear that Xú-Province will fall. I hope you, Gōngtái,
will lead an army to save it.
Charge!
Xiāo Pass
Kill!
Charge!
How can it be you...?!
We've been deceived! We need to save Xú-Province!
Go!
Xú-Province
Open the gates!
I am Lǚ Bù!
Lǚ Bù! You stole my lord's city!
Now you ought to return it to him!
Where is Chén Dēng's father?!
Him? We already killed him!
Mí Zhú
Styled: Zǐzhòng
Where is Chén Dēng?!
Chén Dēng!
My lord! We already fell for Chén Dēng's dirty trick!
Chén Dēng! Chén Dēng-
My lord! We have to go and save Xiǎopèi now!
Chén Dēng!
Why aren't you guarding Xiǎopèi? Why come here?
Chén Dēng reported that you were surrounded,
so we came to save you!
Chén Dēng! I swear I will kill you!
Go!
Xiǎopèi
Chén Dēng!
Traitor!
My lord! Retreat now to Xiàpī!
Fine... go!
Charge!
Xiàpī
Lady Yán
My lady, cheers.
General, you mustn't be too angry.
Chén Dēng betrayed you by relinquishing the city. That is detestable.
But think about it,
if it weren't for Yuánlóng urging you to move to Xiàpī,
Today... this wine would-
A woman's opinion!
If it weren't for Chén Dēng's plan,
then how could I lose Xiāo Pass and Xiǎopèi?
And how then could Xú-Province
fall into the hands of others so easily?
Perhaps to use another ploy?
Before then, you've blamed Chén Gōng.
Now, you blame Chén Dēng.
General, whom are you angry with?
I am just a woman. How could I know?
You have no place for these matters!
Prepare more wine and food.
I will meet Chén Gōng personally.
Together, we can remove all our worries.