This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 5
Three Heroes Duel Lǚ Bù
In the first month of the first year
of the Chūpíng era (190 AD),
eighteen lords formed an coalition
to help the Hàn Empire,
swearing a blood oath.
They elected Yuán Shào as the leader of the alliance
and together declared war against Dǒng Zhuō.
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
Sūn Jiān
Styled: Wéntái
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Gōngsūn Zàn
Styled: Bóguī
Yuán Shù
Styled: Gōnglù
Bào Xìn
Our Hàn Dynasty is in turmoil, its imperium lost!
The bastard Dǒng Zhuō exploits this unrest for his vices,
degrading the noble and suppressing the people.
We of those fearing for the spirits of the realm
have all gathered here, united, to save our nation!
Allied in purpose, together as one!
Loyalty till the end, wills split by none!
Those who would dare our league desert,
let them be razed by heaven and earth!
August gods, ancestral spirits, be our witness!
Allied in purpose, together as one!
Loyalty till the end, wills split by none!
Those who would dare our league desert,
let them be razed by heaven and earth!
I hereby order Sūn Jiān, Administrator of Chǎngshā,
to be the vanguard and advance to Sìshuǐ Pass!
The main force shall march at dawn!
Onward, to Luòyáng!
Those eighteen lords are marching their army towards Luòyáng.
Dǒng Zhuō
Styled: Zhòngyǐng
How shall we deal with them?
Father, do not worry.
Those 'lords' outside are but rank grass.
Lǚ Bù
Styled: Fèngxiān
I can lead our fiercest men and hang their heads on the capital gates!
With you, Fèngxiān, your old man can rest carefree!
Premier!
No need to kill chickens with an ox-cleaver!
General Huà!
Premier!
Huà Xióng
No need to burden Lǚ Bù with this!
I will cut off their heads easily!
We are willing to follow him!
Good, General Huà, I appoint you as
Commander of the Valiant Cavalry!
Thank you sir!
The four of you will go to Sìshuǐ Pass to oppose the enemy.
Behead them all and you'll be greatly rewarded!
Thank you sir!
Lǐ Sù
Brother,
that Sūn Jiān is known as the Tiger of Jiāngdōng.
Now the alliance leader named him as the vanguard.
But if you defeat them first,
the merit will be ours, brother.
Brother, do you mean...
I will give you 3,000 troops.
You can take a short cut to
Sìshuǐ Pass to strike them!
If you annihilate them,
you would draw first-blood, yes?
Correct! I will bring us the honor of drawing first blood!
Bào Zhōng
Report!
Report, Bào Zhōng has rushed to Sìshuǐ Pass!
He's been beheaded by Huà Xióng!
Cheers?
Cheers!
General Huà, victorious from just your first battle!
And now that Bào Zhōng is off with his head.
Didn't he realize he was
doomed from the very start?
The eighteen lords are nothing but a motley gang!
Drink!
Cheers, general!
Report, sir.
Bào Zhōng's head has been sent to the capital.
The Premier has promoted you to Field-Marshal!
Congratulations, Field-Marshal Huà!
Report!
Sir, Sūn Jiān is challenging you below the pass.
After I finish this cup,
I will deal with him!
Let's go!
Sir!
Sir, Sūn Jiān commands four valiant officers. Don't underestimate him.
Report!
Report! Hú Zhěn was slain by Sūn Jiān!
His fame really was warranted.
Heed my orders!
Shoot them!
Do not panic!
Report, sir.
We have the advantage and
will soon seize Sìshuǐ Pass.
The wicked Hú Zhěn was slain!
We'll take the pass in a matter of time,
only that our forces needs supplies!
We hope you, sir, will supply us soon,
Yuán Shù
Styled: Gōnglù
so it'll be easy to storm Sìshuǐ Pass and the capital, seizing Dǒng Zhuō.
Sūn Jiān is really a talented general,
that is not empty praise!
He holds your family in great esteem;
in return, we hope you can supply us!
You may first go back and inform General Sūn
that provisions will be issued on the day we leave.
Many thanks, General!
No need for courtesy.
All of us have a duty to eliminate an
evil traitor. I'm just doing my part.
Thank you, General!
My lord, about the provisions,
Naturally, we would provide Sūn Jiān his lacking provisions.
Only that...
If Sūn Jiān storms Sìshuǐ Pass,
he'd be hailed as a hero, eclipsing all others.
Your worry is correct.
My lord, Sūn Wéntái is famed as the Tiger of Jiāngdōng.
If he breaks through Sìshuǐ Pass and
Luòyáng as well, he'll kill Dǒng Zhuō.
That is akin to replacing a wolf with a tiger.
It would be better not to supply him
and let his forces disintegrate.
Wouldn't my lord then rid himself a potential rival?
That makes sense.
Sir!
Reports say Yuán Shù refused to supply Sūn Jiān.
Sūn Jiān's camp is in utter dissaray!
As I expected, they are nothing but a motley gang!
Yuán Shù fears Sūn Jiān will win
first blood, so he won't supply him!
With squabbles like that,
what use is an alliance for?
This is your chance, sir,
to return home a great victor.
What are your ideas?
In my opinion, we should take action.
You can destroy Sūn Jiān's forces tonight.
Order! Order! Disobedience means death!
My lord, please evacuate!
Where you think you are going?!
My lord, your red plumed helmet is too distinct!
Switch with mine now!
Zǔ Mào
Go there! I will rally our remaining troops!
I can't believe Sūn Wéntái was defeated by Huà Xióng!
Two days ago, General Bào's brother, ignored our warnings and attacked.
It cost his life and many of our soldiers!
Now Sūn Jiān was defeated by Huá Xióng
our morale has suffered grievously! What now?
Gentlemen. Gentlemen!
Why won't any of you speak!
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Administrator Gōngsūn, who's that man behind you?
This is my brother-in-arms who shared
the same house as me since youth: Liú Bèi!
We both agreed to fight Dǒng Zhuō.
Is this the Liú Xuándé who fought
the Yellow Turbans?
None other!
I have long admired your name!
He is the descendant of
Prince Jìng of Zhōngshān and Emperor Jǐng!
As a scion of the Hàn, he should be seated.
Bring a seat!
This is not due to your fame nor rank,
but because you're a scion of the imperial clan.
Please?
Many thanks, sir, for the seat!
Report! Report!
Report, sir.
Huà Xióng led his heavy cavalry here,
displaying Sūn Jiān's helmet.
He demands a challenge from us!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúnchǎng
Who'll accept?
I will go!
Good!
Report!
Report, sir!
Yú Shè and Huà Xióng dueled for three bouts,
and he... Huà Xióng cut him down.
What!
Don't worry, sir! I have Great General Pān Fèng, he can behead Huà Xióng!
Good! Send General Pān to fight!
Pān Fèng
Roger, sir!
Bring my weapon!
Report, sir!
Pān Fèng was also cut down by Huà Xióng!
A pity that my two best men,
Yán Liáng and Wén Chǒu aren't here!
If even one of them was here,
why be afraid of this Huá Xióng!
I will behead Huá Xióng and bring back his head!
And who is he?
That's Liú Xuándé's sworn brother, Guān Yǔ, styled Yúnchǎng.
What is his rank?
He is Liú Xuándé's mounted archer.
The gall! Who does he think he is!?
A paltry horse-archer dares to crow such drivel!
Guards! Get him out!
Please calm down!
This man dares to speak up, so he is a bold one.
Let him fight. If he loses, then we can reprimand him.
If we let out a mere horse-archer, we'll be mocked by Huá Xióng!
This man does not look ordinary.
How could Huà Xióng know he is but an archer?
If I lose, my head will be yours!
Well said! Bring wine!
Yúnchǎng, have this hot wine to embolden you.
Leave it be! I will be back in no time!
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Victory!
This wine is still warm. Cheers!
My brother has killed Huá Xióng!
Why not break through the pass now and capture Dǒng Zhuō?
Go!
Halt!
We nobles have been most modest,
but you are just a petty soldier for that magistrate,
yet you dare grandstand here!
Guards! Expel them from the camp!
Victors should be rewarded. Why argue over petty titles?
If you hold a county magistrate to such honor, then there is no place for me!
Let's go!
Why let petty talk impede the overall goal?!
What trash!
Lǐ Rú
Premier,
Huá Xióng is slain.
Those rebels are stronger than expected;
we can't take them lightly any more.
Yuán Shào's uncle Yuán Wěi is the Grand Tutor.
They likely could plot together from within.
Be cautious of them.
This matter cannot be ignored.
Send men to Yuán Shào's household. Kill them all!
My lord! My lord!
Dǒng Zhuō, decrepit bastard...!
I will see you burn!
Lǐ Jué and Guō Sì!
Here!
You two lead 500,000 troops to guard Sìshuǐ Pass.
Hold your positions. Do not engage the enemy.
Yes, sir!
Lǐ Rú, Fèngxiān, Fán Chóu, and Zhāng Jì!
You will follow me to Hǔláo Pass with 150,000 troops to resist the enemy.
Yes, sir!
Qiáo Mào, Bào Xìn, Yuán Yí, Kǒng Róng, Zhāng Yáng, Táo Qiān, and Gōngsūn Zàn!
Here!
Your armies will merge into one force;
march to Hǔláo Pass to meet the enemy!
Mèngdé will coordinate the troops between the passes.
Yes!
March to Hǔláo; vow to catch Dong Zhuo!
Hǔláo Pass
Who will engage?
I will!
Who is he?
He is Fāng Yuè of Hénèi.
Lǚ Bù, wait!
He's my subordinate, Mù Shùn!
Lǚ Bù's prowess is peerless.
We should summon the eighteen lords to devise a proper plan!
Only if Lǚ Bù is eliminated, can that traitor be killed!
I will challenge him!
Three-named mongrel!
I am Zhāng Fēi of Yàn!
Beat the war drum!
Look out!
My brothers, here I come!
Beat the war drum!
Charge!
Chase him!
Shut the gates now!
We got them!
Withdraw!
Elder brother, that was fantastic!
Today, before Hǔláo Pass, we eight lords fought a major battle with Lǚ Bù.
We won but withdrew.
Now the alliance leader orders us to march into Sìshuǐ Pass.
What should we do?
My lord, two days ago, we suffered a major setback and lost Zǔ Mào.
We lost a great deal of strength; we can't send our troops to attack.
My lord, that Yuán Shù is in charge of the supplies of the Eighteen Lords,
but he envies those with virtue, and refused us supplies!
My Lord, why endanger yourself for the Yuáns?
Chéng Pǔ and Hán Dāng!
Here!
You two come with me to Yuán Shù's camp!
As you wish!
Be careful.
Alright.
Gōnglù!
I had no quarrel with Dǒng Zhuō
yet I fight him tooth and nail regardless.
Risking our lives in bloody battles
so as to rid my nation of a traitor
and for your clan's benefit too!
Yet you listen to slander and refused us supplies, thus my defeat by Huà Xióng!
How do you explain that, General?
It was his idea not to give you provisions!
General, it was not my idea!
You dare deny it?
Men!
Here!
Send him to execution!
Have mercy on me! Have mercy on me!
Mercy! Mercy, please! Mercy!
I made a mistake heeding his advice.
Please accept my apology.
Sir, now that the guilty is punished,
There is no more strife between us.
From now on, let us work as one.
We can't let anything divide us.
Wéntái, your words are utmostly correct.
Sir, someone is requesting your presence at the camp.
Alright then, I shall take my leave.
Wéntái, please!
Lǐ Jué pays his respects to General Sūn!
You?
Why have you come here?
The Premier ordered me here.
What did Dǒng Zhuō send you for?
The Premier holds you, sir, in high esteem;
he has sent me for a marriage proposal.
A marriage?
The Premier has a young daughter most suitable for your son, sir.
Shut up!
Dǒng Zhuō is despicable without equal. He terrorizes the Han court!
I would kill nine generations of his clan for the realm!
You think I would ally with that traitor!
General, but-
Out!
Get out! Tell that bastard to give up the pass!
Get out!
If you surrender the pass, I may show mercy!
Any more delay, and I will
break your bones to powder!
Yes! Yes!
Sūn Jiān was too imprudent; it's not my fault!
Get out of my sight!
Ok!
The marriage proposal won't do. What next?
My lord, the Marquis of Wēn was recently defeated and our morale is low.
Best to recall the troops back to Luòyáng and move the capital to Cháng'ān.
Move the capital?
Correct. Move the capital.
Cháng'ān is vast, with a flourishing population.
It served as the capital for the previous dynasties.
Moreover, my lord, you've lived there for many years and laid a strong foundation.
It also has Tóng Pass and other natural barriers
to put a distance between us and those lords, and it is easy to guard.
My lord, have you not heard of this children's folk rhyme?
Children's folk rhyme?
"A Hàn in the west; a Hàn in the east."
"The deer within Cháng'ān will worry the least."
What does it mean?
The Hàn in the west refers to
Gāozǔ, who made the Cháng'ān the capital,
Hàn Gāozǔ AKA. Liú Bāng, first emperor of the Western Han.
which lasted for twelve reigns.
The Hàn in the east refers to
Guāngwǔ, who made the Luòyáng the new capital,
Hàn Guāngwǔ AKA. Liú Xiù, first emperor of the Eastern Han
which also lasted for twelve reigns.
The heavens revolved back;
Premier, if you move the capital back to Cháng'ān,
your worries would be gone!
Had you not clarified, I would never have understood!
The Heaven's will lies in a children's folk rhyme!
Good! Recall the troops back to Luòyáng, and arrange the relocation of the capital!
Emperor Xiàn of Hàn
This minister pays his respects to Your Majesty!
Sir!
What are we waiting for?
Why not pursue Dǒng Zhuō now?
Běnchū, that traitor burned the palace and holds the emperor hostage.
His actions have appalled the whole realm!
There's a crisis within our hands. How can we do nothing?
That traitor fears our power,
thus, he moved the capital west to avoid our army.
Lǚ Bù was soundly defeated at Hǔláo Pass!
Their morale is low; ours is high!
If we destroy them now, peace will be restored!
How can we miss this pivotal moment?
Our soldiers are exhausted.
We can't possibly continue the fight.
Yes! We mustn't act rashly!
Ignorant fools! A waste of time!