This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 3
Dǒng Zhuó domineers the capital
I see the current Emperor is weak and incapable,
but the Prince of Chénliú is
smart and studious, like a true monarch.
Today, before the army,
His Grace displayed his authority.
Such a commanding presence
is rare in a boy his age.
I agree.
Do you think...
Dǒng Zhuó
Styled: Zhòngyǐng
if I were to depose the emperor and enthrone the Prince of Chénliú,
would this be feasible?
Lǐ Rú
If your lordship wishes to gain authority
by deposing the emperor,
then it is a splendid idea.
I've long garrisoned at Xīliáng.
These problems in the court...
How can I establish my authority in just a few days?
I believe the answer is to depose the emperor.
and crown a new sovereign!
Depose the old and crown the new.
Very well.
By deposing the Emperor,
you will earn two boons.
Go ahead.
Of old, both Yī Yǐn and Huò Guāng deposed their ruler to enthrone a new one.
Note: Yī Yǐn was a chancellor who helped the founding of the Shang dynasty.
Note: Huo Guang was a general, later minister of Han dynasty who helped stabilize the government following Emperor Wu's death.
They became respected, outstanding figures of their era.
If you, my lord, follow their example,
You are sure to go down in history.
This is the first boon.
What's the second?
For the great deed of saving the Emperor,
you can use it to lord over all ministers.
With this, who would dare to oppose you?
When the new monarch is enthroned,
your lordship can overrule the Son of Heaven to command the ministers.
Thus, you can take over the realm.
This is the second boon.
You truly give wit to these old bones!
With these two boon, why not act now?
Though there are boons, there is still one problem.
One problem?
Speak.
Ever since the two Emperors
Zhāng and Hé ascended to the throne,
those who held the authority within the imperial court,
such as Dòu Xiàn, Dèng Zhì, Yán Xiǎn, Chén Fān,
and until recently, Generalissimo Hé Jìn, murdered by the Ten Attendants,
there is not one who didn't suffer a violent death.
I ask of you, my lord, to forgive my blunt words,
but the one who controls the emperor
will undoubtedly be the real authority at the court,
but will also make himself a target to others.
I hope my lord would take this one trouble into consideration and acts cautiously!
Knowing the past, understanding the present!
Good!
Your words are honest,
very good. Very true!
However, I, Dǒng Zhuó,
am not Dòu Xiàn, Dèng Zhì, or those others.
And I am definitely not that lowly butcher, Hé Jìn.
Since there are two boons but only one problem,
what's there to fear?
Bào Xìn
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
The nation is in trouble,
the spirits are in turmoil.
Note: The spirits mentioned are the spirits of grain and soil, which received regular sacrifices during the Hàn.
Though the Ten Attendants were eliminated,
now...
now Dǒng Zhuó has come.
Every day, he goes to the districts running amok,
with his elite soldiers to clear the way.
The commoners hide from him as if he were a demon.
He's causing panic in and around the capital city.
Had we known then,
we wouldn't have involved him!
Now he goes in and out the palace as he pleases.
He is unscrupulous, all the officials fear him, and the Emperor feels no peace.
Before, Zhèng Tài and Lú Zhí had warned that
Dǒng Zhuó may look kind, but is cruel as can be
that once he entered
the palace, disaster would follow.
Their concerns proved to be true.
I sense Dǒng Zhuó harbors grand ambitions.
Eliminate him as soon as possible!
What do you two think? Speak up!
Colonel Bào, how can't I know?!
But the chaos caused by
the Ten Attendants has only just subsided.
This court has only recently established,
it's too soon to act rashly.
That's...
Excellency of the Masses,
what do you propose?
Wáng Yǔn
Styled: Zǐshī
We may discuss this issue again later.
In this case, I shall lead my army out of the capital for a while.
When you're ready to fight Dǒng Zhuó, I shall return.
Sir, Lord Dǒng sends this invitation.
Tomorrow, Dǒng Zhuó invites all the officials to Wēn Garden for a party.
Dīng Yuán
Styled: Jiànyáng
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Běnchū.
Lǚ Bù
Styled: Fèngxiān
Lord Dǒng arrives!
I have arrived late.
Forgive me, forgive me.
Sit, sit, sit.
Forgive me.
Sit, sit.
Gentlemen,
I have come from Xīliáng to the capital.
Recently, I wanted to consult with you all on one or two things.
Today, I have prepared some light wine.
Would you fellows drink some?
Merely the presence being with you all makes me feel honored.
Everyone!
Please!
Please
Lord Dǒng, after you.
I ask you gentlemen not to be alarmed. I have something to say, so listen carefully.
Since ancient times, the Emperor served as the overlord for thousands of people.
Exalted by all, and must never fail
to pay his respects at the ancestral temple,
and uphold the national spirit.
And now? His Majesty is
cowardly, weak, and uncouth.
He is inferior to the Prince of Chénliú, who is intelligent and astute.
I propose we depose the young emperor
and replace him with the Prince of Chénliú.
Gentlemen,
what do you think?
Otherwise, if you fellows have no objections-
Who do you think you are?
Daring to speak blasphemy!
The Emperor is his late majesty's legitimate son!
He has made no transgression,
how could we depose him?
This is akin to usurping the throne!
From this day...
those who obey me prosper,
those that don't die!
My lord!
Today is for feasts.
Let's not talk about politics.
No more politics.
Jiànyáng, please calm!
Go!
Dǒng Zhuó, you traitor!
You won't get away with this!
Go!
Those were my honest words! Am I wrong?
Sir, the Ten Attendants may be gone
but the new regime has only been established!
Hundreds of issues need addressing!
The situation is unstable.
this will only cause problems.
I considered it! This is what's
best for the nation's spirit!
Běnchū, what do you have to fear?
Sire, this is wrong.
Lú Zhí
Styled: Zǐgàn
Of old, during Tài Jiǎ's reign,
Yī Yǐn imprisoned him at Tóng Palace.
When the Prince of Chāngyì was enthroned, merely 27 days after,
his crimes numbered over 3,000,
and thus Huò Guāng deposed him in the ancestral temple.
Today, the Emperor, while young, is still wise and keen.
He has not committed the slightest of crimes.
You, sir, are only an Overseer of a frontier region, not adept in state affairs.
You also lack the talent of Yī Yǐn and Huò Guāng.
How could you talk about an
important matter like deposition so lightly?
Sages have said, "Allowed are those of Yī Yǐn's will,"
"usurpers are those lost of Yī Yǐn's will!"
I will kill you first, villain!
Lú Zhí
Styled: Zǐgàn
Lord Dǒng, please calm!
Lord Dǒng!
Lord Dǒng, please calm.
Lord Dǒng, Director Lú is respected by people the world over.
Killing him would appall all in the nation.
Sorry for the scare!
Sit!
Sit...
Gentlemen,
the proposal by Lord Dǒng to depose the emperor
is of a foremost matter to the state.
Respectfully, it is improper to discuss it after drinking.
Let's discuss it at a later date.
Lord Dǒng, your thoughts?
Wáng Yǔn takes his leave.
We take our leave.
Dǒng Zhuó, you traitor!
The nation is unfortunate for the eunuchs to
seize power, and now you abuse the people!
How dare you, Dīng Yuán!?
Yes!
Charge!
What are you looking at?
Kneel!
If I had Lǚ Bù,
nothing in the world could worry me.
My lord?
Lǚ Bù and I are from the same village.
I know him very well.
He's very brave, but not bright
and would sell his soul to the devil.
I am willing to use my silver tongue
to convince Lǚ Bù to turn over.
You can convince Lǚ Bù?
Yes.
Heaven is on my side!
Quickly tell me!
How can you win him over?
I've hear, my lord, has a famous steed by the name of Red Hare.
In order to persuade Lǚ Bù, I need that horse.
You can't convince him without the horse?
My lord.
Lǚ Bù is a valiant warrior.
Among the things that a warrior loves,
the first is a weapon,
Second is a horse, and the third is armor.
These are the three things
that a soldier needs to excel.
Today, what Lǚ Bù rode is
merely an ordinary warhorse.
How can he not crave for a fine steed?
Red Hare, a precious horse,
as far as Your Lordship is concerned,
is nothing but a pet.
But for fighting on the battlefield,
especially for a renowned general,
it's as important as his own life.
Lǚ Bù already possesses the Sky Piercing halberd
and on his body, he wears a fine suit of armor.
All of these are no ordinary things.
He only lacks a good steed.
If he obtains Red Hare, it would
be like giving a tiger wings.
My lord, if you want Lǚ Bù on your side,
here is what I suggest:
Any other horse is not enough to sway his heart
and not enough to show Your Lordship's sincerity because,
my lord, can you really give up this horse?
If he gets the horse, add some precious jewels to help sway his heart.
I can persuade him by explaining the advantages.
I am sure that Lǚ Bù will betray Dīng Yuán
and come to your side, my lord.
My lord, if you want to seize the realm,
why care about a horse?
Lǐ Sù
Very well, I shall give up my horse!
lièhuǒ juǎn xióngfēng
Raging flames blow the wild wind
hóngyún yìng bìkōng
The red clouds shine in the clear sky
Galloping in the wilderness
mǎngyuán hǎo chíchěng
fēngyān tiānbiān yōng
A beacon fire on the horizon
qí jì yǒu liángzhǒng
There is one among fine steeds
bǎomǎ dài yīngxióng
A precious horse awaiting a hero
It pushes deep, swift like lightning
chángqū jí rú diàn
zhēn kān tuō sǐshēng
Their lives and death depending on each other
lièhuǒ juǎn xióngfēng
Raging flames blow the wild wind
hóngyún yìng bìkōng
The red clouds shine in the clear sky
mǎngyuán hǎo chíchěng
Galloping in the wilderness
fēngyān tiānbiān yōng
A beacon fire on the horizon
qí jì yǒu liángzhǒng
There is one among fine steeds
bǎomǎ dài yīngxióng
A precious horse awaiting a hero
chángqū jí rú diàn
It pushes deep, swift like lightning
zhēn kān tuō sǐshēng
Their lives and death depending on each other
iúxiá jì zhuàngzhì
The drifting rosy clouds holding great ambitions
cānghǎi shū háoqíng
The azure ocean conveying their lofty aspirations
míng cháo fèn pǐ tí
In the future, the steed shall race with blazing hooves
dízhèn lì dàgōng
Against foes, the hero shall perform exceptional deeds
liúxiá jì zhuàngzhì
The drifting rosy clouds holding great ambitions
cānghǎi shū háoqíng
The azure ocean conveying their lofty aspirations
míng cháo fèn pǐ tí
In the future, the steed shall race with blazing hooves
dízhèn lì dàgōng
Against foes, the hero shall perform exceptional deeds
Please?
Please.
Brother Sù,
Didn't expect you'd come visit me!
Quick, bring food and wine!
Please?
Please.
Many thanks, Brother Sù, for gifting me such a fine steed!
I truly don't know how to repay you.
A precious sword belongs to a warrior,
a precious horse belongs to a hero.
Brother, you're a tiger of the world,
Red Hare is a dragon among horses.
This horse could only belong to you, brother!
Cheers?
Cheers.
Time does flies. Brother Sù, what are you doing now?
I am Tiger-General of the Gentlemen of the Household.
Look how far you've gone!
Virtuous brother, are you content?
Well, now I serve under Overseer Dīng.
Virtuous brother, I hardly see you anymore
but I do often see your esteemed father.
Brother, you must be drunk!
My father has been dead for many years.
How could you meet him, brother?
Oh no, I am talking about...
Overseer Dīng!
Very witty, brother.
Brother,
I am not saying this to flatter you,
but with your talents...
why are you wasting them under Overseer Dīng?
Because I don't have a choice.
Please.
Light the torches!
Brother, you possess the talent to
hold the sky and sail the sea.
Is there anyone within the four seas
that doesn't admire you?
Achieving wealth and prestige for you is as easy as taking from a pocket.
Why did you say...
that you have no choice?
Brother, don't you know this story,
that a good bird chooses a good tree to perch,
a good minister chooses a worthy lord to serve.
Nowadays, there are more people and heroes
in the world that have extraordinary talent!
Brother, if you continue to follow Dīng Jiànyáng,
how can you build a meritorious career?
It's difficult to find a worthy lord.
Foolish brother, I've come here
precisely for your future career.
Brother, who do you think is the hero of our era?
Brother, there is no harm in speaking your mind.
No harm?
There is no harm.
Very well.
Having observed the vast realm, among all the
ministers, I consider them all inferior to...
Who?
Dǒng Zhuó!
You!
Why are you laughing?
Brother, even a hero such as yourself,
as soon he hears Dǒng Zhuó's name,
changes the color of his face!
Dǒng Zhuó truly is a hero!
Brother, you really know how to joke!
But how can that traitor be a hero?
Dǒng Zhuó is tyrannical and eyes of usurpation.
How could everyone within the court not know?
But you-
Brother,
you only know his image,
and not his heart.
You only know one aspect,
and not the second.
The Emperor is weak,
unable to control the ministers.
How could all the officials at court not know this?
The Prince of Chénliú is
intelligent, strong, and astute,
apter than the Emperor a hundred fold.
Again, how could all the officials at court not know this?
They all have these thoughts,
but nobody says it out loud.
Why is that?
They fear leaving a reputation of disloyalty
and being labeled as criminals,
exploiting the chaos to usurp the throne.
A weak Son of Heaven is easy to fool,
but a strong Son of Heaven is hard to fool.
The court officials are loyal on the outside,
but deep down they think of their own benefit.
Who do you think truly serves
the empire and nation's spirits?
Lord Dǒng is not like them,
he dares to say what others dare not.
He speaks words others would not say out loud.
He dares the risk of leaving a bad reputation.
He bears the accusations of usurpation.
The heart of Lord Dǒng is pure,
the actions of Lord Dǒng are righteous!
Though I 've never heard such words before,
they don't seem unreasonable.
However...
to depose the Emperor
is the road to usurpation!
Brother!
Since ancient times, only the virtuous were able to hold paramount authority.
Presently, the Prince and Emperor
are both sons of the late emperor.
If he assists the Prince in taking the throne,
how is that usurpation? This is my first point.
The second:
When the late emperor was still reigning,
he favored the Prince of Chénliú,
that he intended to have him succeed him.
It was Empress Hé and Hé Jìn who forced a change in heir, a terrible mistake.
Lord Dǒng will now depose the Emperor
and enthrone the Prince of Chénliú
in accordance with the late emperor's original will,
restoring the throne to the Prince of Chénliú.
How is that treacherous?
My dear brother, hearing your words is like
clouds parting to for the sun!
You have enlightened me!
Brother, there are 10,000 reasons why you shouldn't
hesitate and miss such an opportunity!
If someone as insignificant as me under Lord Dǒng can become Tiger-General of the Household,
then you, with your great courage and talents,
are sure to have a meteoric
rise under Lord Dǒng.
You would quickly climb up the ranks and be rewarded beyond what you could imagine.
I want to serve him.
But...
I have no way to do so.
Brother,
please look.
This is?
Lord Dǒng has long admired your reputation.
He intends to make a friend of you.
Lord Dǒng ordered me to give you
these gifts to pay his respects.
That precious horse, Red Hare,
was Lord Dǒng's favorite mount.
Lord Dǒng sends it as a special gift to you.
Lord Dǒng
shows me such kindness.
Virtuous brother, Lord Dǒng has been thinking of your great name for a long time.
Lord Dǒng has shown me so much favor,
but I regret that I, Lǚ Bù,
have done nothing in return,
I have no gift to offer when I meet him!
Virtuous brother, the merits you seek are here and it is as easy as turning your hand over.
Whom does Lord Dǒng want to eliminate?
You must know who.
I only fear...
You wouldn't be willing to do it.
My son, what's the matter?
How could I, a real man, ever be your son?
Fèngxiān! Why are you saying this?!
Obtaining you, General, is like a seedling tasting sweet-dew in a drought!
My lord
Quickly, please rise.
My lord,
Please sit.
I have wandered half my life. My only regret was not having met such a worthy lord!
My lord, if you would allow,
I, Bù, would treat you as his own father.
Now Fèngxiān is by my side! Heaven has blessed me with such an outstanding hero!
My son, please rise.
Father, from now on, your son will follow you.
Through water and fire, I will never give in!
I aid you to achieve this grand undertaking!
With Fèngxiān with me,
I can accomplish my ambitions!
Fèngxiān, my son.
Here.
I hereby name you Chief Cavalry-Commander of the Gentlemen of the Household
with the noble rank of Marquis.
Thank you, father.
Present golden armor
and silk brocade robe.
Tomorrow, your father will summon the officials to re-discuss deposing the Emperor.
Your son is willing to escort you, father!
I order you to bring 1,000 armed men
to be your father's bodyguards.
I accept!
Gentlemen,
the current emperor is ignorant,
unworthy to his forefathers.
I shall follow the examples of Yī Yǐn and Huò Guāng.
The emperor hereafter shall be
known as the Prince of Hóngnóng,
the Prince of Chénliú will be the new sovereign.
Those who disobey will be...
executed!
Right now, the regime is still new,
you were summoned to assist
the Emperor to restore order!
Yet you...
have repeatedly called meetings to
depose an imperial firstborn son!
Do you plan to rebel?!
The realm's affairs rely on me.
If this is my command,
who'd dare to oppose me?
The realm relies on the Emperor and the loyal ministers here!
You...
are merely just a traitor and a usurper!
Why should you matter?
Want to see if my sword is sharp enough, whelp?
Mine isn't dull either!
Nothing's been settled yet! No need for strife!
Běnchū!
Běnchū...
On the ninth month on the first day, we shall hold a ceremony of deposition and ascension at Jiādé Hall.
All the civil and military officials must be present.
Dismissed!
Yuán Shào!
What an useless official you are, unworthy of the empire's favor.
Dǒng Zhuó, you traitor!
Who told you to assassinate me?
You dare conspire against me?
Wǔ Fú
Styled: Déyú
You are not my monarch, I am not your subject.
What is there to 'conspire'?!
Your crimes upheave the very Heavens!
Everyone wants to see you dead!
I only regret not cutting you to
pieces as to appease the world!
Fool!
Bastard! Vile traitor!
You will go down in history as a byword of infamy for 10,000 years!
Emperor Shǎo of Hàn
Emperor Xiàolíng left his subjects all too early.
The Emperor succeeded him as the heir and everyone within the four seas looked up at him.
However the Emperor is frivolous, inmajestic, and insolemn.
In the mourning of his predecessor, his father, he proved to be slow and indolent.
He is an embarrassment to the throne.
Empress Dowager Hé
The Empress Dowager didn't teach her son
properly as a mother should,
consequently the affairs of the realm are in chaos.
Empress Yǒnglè died suddenly,
which aroused public suspicion.
Isn't evident that the rules of the three essentials:
Heaven, Earth, and Human, have been violated?
The Prince of Chénliú is dutiful, divinely virtuous,
and solemnly observes proper etiquette.
During the national mourning, he was sorrowful and has never said anything improper.
The entire realm has heard of his excellent behavior.
He is therefore suitable to rule the vast empire and unify it for the next 10,000 generations.
We hereby depose the Emperor,
demoting him to the Prince of Hóngnóng.
The Empress Dowager
shall relinquish all her authority.
We beg the Prince of Chénliú
to ascend as Emperor,
in accordance with Heaven's will and the desire of the people, to give hope and inspiration!
Mother!
Dǒng Zhuó crowned the nine year old Prince of Chénliú, Liú Xié as the new Emperor.
Emperor
Xiàn of Hàn
He would become Emperor Xiàn of Hàn.
Dǒng Zhuó was then named  'the Premier of State.'
He held no respect for law nor etiquette
and brazenly wielded his sword at will.
He slept in the palace and lived in debauchery, even depraving the imperial chambers.
His actions aroused the resentment of the
court, the masses, and the entire realm.
Thus begun the struggle against Dǒng Zhuó.