This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 14
Heroes over Wine
On the third year of the Jian'an era (198 AD),
Cao Cao, with the help of Liu Bei, conquered Xuzhou and Xiapi.
He strangled Lü Bu at White Gate Tower and accepted Zhang Liao's surrender.
He thus removed a cause for great trouble.
Ministers who have rendered merits shall be rewarded.
With the nation maintained through your efforts, We can be at rest.
Those of you with achievements shall
request Sire Cao for your rewards.
Cao Cao
Styled: Mengde
As you command, Your Majesty.
Beloved liege-man, you memorialized yesterday about Liu Bei's exploits.
Why not call him to an audience with us?
As you command.
Liu Bei is called for an audience with His Majesty!
Liú Bèi,
styled Xuándé
My humblest respects, Your Majesty.
Long live! Long, long live!
Emperor Xian of Hàn
You may rise.
Thank you, Your Majesty.
You do look majestic. Who are your ancestors?
Your subject is a descendant of Prince Jing of Zhongshan,
Note: Liu Sheng, Prince of Zhongshan, born ? - 113 BC
and a distant descendant of Emperor Jing.
I am the grandson of Liu Xiong and the son of Liu Hong.
Quickly. Let us check the imperial clan's record.
Yes!
Your Majesty?
Read it out loud.
Very well.
Emperor Jing had fourteen sons.
Note: Emperor Jing of Hàn, born 188 BC – 9 March 141 BC
The seventh was Prince Jing
of Zhongshan, Liu Sheng.
Sheng beget the Marquis of Lucheng, Liu Ang.
Ang beget the Marquis of Zhang, Liu Lu.
Lu beget the Marquis of Yishui, Liu Lian.
Lian beget the Marquis of Qinyang, Liu Ying.
Ying beget the Marquis of Anguo, Liu Jian.
Jian beget the Marquis of Guangling, Liu Ai.
Ai beget the Marquis of Jiaoshui, Liu Xian.
Xian beget the Marquis of Zuyi, Liu Shu.
Shu beget the Marquis of Qiyang, Liu Yi.
Yi beget the Marquis of Yuanze, Liu Bi.
Bi beget the Marquis of Yingchuan, Liu Da.
Da beget the Marquis of Banling, Liu Buyi.
Buyi beget the Marquis of Jichuan, Liu Hui.
Hui beget the Prefect of Fan,
of Dōng-commandery, Liu Xiong.
Xiong beget Liu Hóng, who held no rank.
Liu Bei is Liu Hóng's son.
Cáo Cāo has amassed power.
Not one matter of the state is of my doing.
Now that I have found this hero,
I will finally have salvation.
Please, rise, Imperial Uncle.
Thank you, Your Majesty!
Follow Us to the main hall to pay our respects, as Our relative.
Court is dismissed!
Chancellor,
Xún Yōu
Styled: Gōng Dá
the Emperor acknowledged
Liu Bei as the Imperial Uncle.
This may be problematic to you.
Though Liu Bei acts as the Imperial Uncle,
I am the one issuing the decrees in the Emperor's name.
How could he not obey them?
Besides, if I keep Liu Bei here in Xǔdū (Xǔchāng),
his bond with the Emperor all the more has him deeper in my grasp.
Why fear him?
Chancellor, your might and prestige increases every day.
Why not conduct yourself like a king?
Before that, let us raise a toast.
The imperial family currently has many supporters and must not be underestimated.
I already asked for the Emperor
to go hunting tommorow.
We shall see how they act.
Chancellor! Chancellor.
Chancellor, on your orders,
I have prepared a house in the vicinity of your mansion for Liu Bei.
Good. Send people to keep an eye on Liu Bei at all times.
Report back when possible.
Yes sir.
Brothers, you cannot make too much noise.
This is our courtyard. What's it to them?
Brother, why are you neglecting your duties?
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
You're just growing vegetables everyday!
The Emperor has acknowledged me as his uncle,
so everyone is keeping an eye on me.
We must be very cautious in our manners and our words.
This is so that others will not see us as impudent.
Also, we live next to the Chancellor, so all the more to be vigilant.
He's just too paranoid!
We haven't caused any trouble!
Why do they care about
what we do or say?
Third Brother, he hasn't spoken very clearly.
We have to be careful, otherwise he might get in trouble.
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
The realm is not at ease.
Is hunting really appropriate?
Your Majesty is mistaken.
Sovereigns of old toured during autumn and hunted during winter.
To leave the palace every season
would show your magnanimity.
Whatever the turmoil,
Your Majesty would still display your authority.
What problem is there?
Your Majesty. Please?
Go call the Imperial Uncle.
The Imperial Uncle is called!
I offer my respects, Your Majesty.
We wish to see you hunt, Imperial Uncle.
As you command.
Nice! Nice! Good shot, Imperial Uncle!
Your Majesty, you praise me too highly.
Let His Majesty hunt!
Dǒng Chéng
Why don't you try it?
The Chancellor has hit his target! He has hit his target!
The Emperor has hit his target!
He has hit his target!
It's the Emperor's golden arrow!
He's hit his target!
Long live the Emperor!
May he live 10,000 years!
Chancellor, such a divine shot is seldom in this world.
That was a blessing from the Emperor!
A blessing from the Emperor.
Had I lacked the Emperor's bow,
how could I have made such a shot?
Brother!
Brother, that bastard Cao Cao humiliated his Majesty!
I would have rid the land of a villain had I killed him!
Why did you stop me?
Cao Cao and the Emperor were only a few inches apart,
and his aides were all around him too.
Second Brother, if you acted recklessly in a fit of rage,
the Emperor would've been harmed!
The fault would have been ours. You have to let a rat go lest you smash the dishes.
If we don't kill this bastard today,
there will be grave consequences!
All of the ministers received the nation's grace,
yet in this crisis, not one comes to our aid!
Your Majesty!
Who's there?
Fu Wan
The General of the Chariots and the State Uncle, Dǒng Chéng
Note: State Uncle（国舅）is either the maternal uncle of the Emperor, or Emperor's brother-in-law
Summon him now. We have urgent matters to discuss.
We can't act recklessly.
If such is the case, what do you suggest we do?
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, use your brocade robe and jade belt,
and hide an edict in them.
Later, summon Dǒng Chéng,
gift him these clothes and send him back to read the edict, to show intention to rid of traitors.
Not even the gods or spirits will know of it.
Worthy subject, wear this robe
and fasten this jade belt,
so that you feel you're always by Our side!
Your Majesty!
Our liege-man, when you go back, examine it very carefully. Don't reject Our good will.
Here comes the Chancellor!
How is Liu Bei doing these days?
I asked his servants.
They say he reads in his chamber
or is sipping tea in the veranda.
After returning from the imperial hunt, he started growing vegetables.
He tends the orchard every day without rest.
Oh? He grows vegetables?
He seems to be quite idle.
Are you sure he isn't just avoiding me?
State Uncle, why are you hiding from me also?
Chancellor!
Sir, you came to the palace quite early. What's the matter?
His Majesty has summoned me to give me a brocade robe and a belt.
Today of all days? Why has he has given you a present?
His Majesty recalled when I rescued him in the Western Capital (Cháng'ān).
He summoned me to talk about the past and gave me this present.
Hand over the belt.
Seize it from him!
So it is an exquisite jade belt.
How does it look on me?
It fits you perfectly, Chancellor!
If that's the case, how about you give me the robe and belt as a present, State Uncle?
I dare not give away the sovereign's gifts.
If you like it, Chancellor, I can present another robe for you.
State Uncle, could those robes hide plots in it?
Chancellor, if you insist, you may have it.
Why the accusation of a hidden plot?
State Uncle, how could I keep a gift from the Emperor?
Our liege-man, when you go back, examine it very carefully. Don't reject Our good will.
"It is said amongst people's relations,
that of a father and his son comes first."
"Amongst social ties, that of a sovereign and his minister is the strongest."
"The rebel Cao Cao abuses power for his enjoyment."
"He oppresses the family and, with the support of his armies,"
"undermining the imperium."
"Policies, rewards and punishments no longer depend on Us."
"At all times, We have troubled thoughts, that the world may be at the brink of peril."
"You are a grand minister of
the nation and a dear relative of Ours."
"Remember the struggle met by our First Emperor."
"Gather both loyal and righteous heroes to eliminate the villains within court."
"To pacify the state, honour the spirit of the nation."
"We entrust you this edict, written with the blood of Our finger."
"Consider this carefully, do not let down Our wishes."
The impudence!
Zǐfú.
If Lord Cao is in danger,
I must inform him immediately!
Zifu, if that's what you want, my life is worth little compared to the fate of the Hàn dynasty!
Wáng Zǐfú
Lord Dǒng, I would not be where I am without the Hàn Empire.
How could I lack a loyal heart?
I am willing to lend you a hand in purging the traitors to the state!
If you come to visit me so late, Imperial Uncle, you must have a reason.
To come in plain daylight would make Cao Cao suspicious, so I've come late at night.
Fetch wine for our guest.
Yes.
Yesterday, Yunchang wanted to kill Cao Cao in the hunting grounds.
You signaled him to stop and shook your head. Why is that, General?
How did you realize, my lord?
Nobody else knows it. Only I saw it.
My brother saw Cao Cao humiliate our sovereign and he was enraged.
State Uncle.
If all ministers were like you, Yunchang, who would worry about peace in the Empire?
How is Chancellor Cao's regime not peaceful?
State Uncle.
Sir, you are the Imperial Uncle of the Hàn dynasty.
Your words are usually so honest. Why are you lying?
State Uncle.
I feared you were lying, so I was just testing you, nothing more.
How could I lie?
Sir, look!
Second Brother.
Third Brother.
This...  Our glorious Hàn Empire...
To think that our Emperor, who stands above all...
has to... has to... has to resort to a blood edict to his ministers!
Elder Brother!
General!
General of the Chariots; Dǒng Chéng,
Deputy Minister of Works; Wang Zifu,
Cavalry Colonel; Zhǒng Jí,
Faithful Gentleman; Wú Shuò,
General of Clear Loyalty; Wú Zǐlán and the Administrator of Xīliáng; Mǎ Téng.
Since I have received an imperial order to expel the rebels, I will do my utmost!
Second Brother. Bring me a brush.
Yes.
Orders from the Chancellor.
You must go immediately.
What's the matter?
I don't know. He only told me to call you.
Let me pull the bucket from the well first.
Lord Liu has arrived!
You've been doing really great work at your house!
You seem to be pretty carefree growing your orchard, Xuande. It must be hard work.
Such things are irrelevant. Chancellor, why have you summoned me?
Xuande, I just saw the plums on the trees were green and felt some nostalgia.
When I was campaigning against Zhang Xiu,
there was no water on the way
and the troops were extremely thirsty.
I thought of something brilliant. I pointed ahead and said that there was a plum forest there.
Note: This is the origin of the Chinese idiom "望梅止渴", from A New Account of the Tales of the World.
As soon as they heard that, their mouths started watering and they were no longer thirsty.
Seeing a plum tree today, I can't help but to behold it in admiration.
It also happens that it is ripe. Let us have a toast with it!
Chancellor. Look. There's a dragon hanging on the sky.
The dragon hanging from the heavens
looks like he's curling about,
as if to turn seas and rivers over.
A truly admirable sight.
Sire, do you understand the many forms of dragons?
I do not know. Please, explain.
Dragons can be large or small, they can soar or hide.
The large ones births clouds and breathes mist.
The small ones conceal themselves from sight.
Those that fly soar across creation,
those that hide dwell within the great waves.
Here, deep within spring, is when dragons form,
like men with the will to conquer Four Seas.
The large ones births clouds and breathes mist.
The small ones conceal themselves from sight.
Those that fly soar across creation,
Those that hide dwell within the great waves.
Among all creatures, the dragon can be compared to the heroes in the world.
Xuande, since you have ventured across the land, I assume you know such heroes.
I ask thee to inform me who they are.
How could I recognize these heroes with just my eyes?
Don't be so modest!
Thanks to your favor, I have a post as an official.
As for the heroes of the world, I regretfully do not know.
Perhaps you don't remember their faces, but you must heard of their reputation.
Is Yuán Shù of Huáinán,
with his abundant lands
and troops, count as a hero?
Nothing but dried bones in a grave! His defeat is inevitable.
Yuán Shào of Héběi! His clan with
four generations of Excellencies.
Note: The Excellencies are the highest
officials in the Imperial Court
He waits in Jì Province like a crouching tiger,
and has many capable men under his command. Is he a hero?
Yuan Shao appears fierce, but has no guts!
He schemes, but lacks decisiveness!
Conservative, despite his ambitions.
Only sees minutiae over the big picture.
He's not a hero!
There's one renowned for his nobility,
whose name echoes throughout the land—
Is Liú Jǐngshēng a hero?
Liú Biǎo has nothing behind his reputation.
A magpie, not a hero.
There's a man of valour who rules over Jiāngdōng.
Surely, Sūn Bófū is a hero!
Sūn Cè rides on his father's name! He's no hero!
What of Liú Jìyù of Yì Province, is he a hero?
Liú Zhāng may be of the imperial family, but he's nothing more than a watchdog.
How can he be a hero?
What about Zhāng Xiù,
Zhāng Lǔ, Hán Suì and the rest?
All these lesser men,
are they really worth mentioning?
Other than these, I don't know.
Heroes harbor grand ideals in their hearts and have methods to fulfill them.
Schemes within schemes all-embracing,
and the will to bring all to their mercy.
Who can be considered one?
Right now, the heroes of these lands,
are only you, sire, and I!
Such tremendous ferocity! That was really close.
How can a grown man be afraid of thunder?
Note: "The Sage One" refers to Confucius.
The Sage One said that one must change his countenance before the sudden thunder.
How can I not be afraid?
If we stay in Xǔdū, Cao Cao will harm us sooner or later.
It is said that Yuan Shu has rebelled in Huáinán.
He wants to forfeit the imperial seal
and his title to Yuan Shao.
If Yuan Shu is going to surrender to Shao, he must go through Xu Province.
We must seize this chance and ask to halt Yuan Shu,
claiming to block the two Yuan's merge,
but really for us to gain independence.
Elder Brother's right!
If we ask for troops
to block off Yuan Shu,
this too will be ridding
Cao Cao of a great threat.
He will have no reason to decline.
Very well. I will memorialize to the throne immediately, asking for troops and march off.
Chancellor.
Guō Jiā
Styled: Fèngxiào
Chancellor, I know you must have
a greater reason for not killing Liu Bei.
However, you must not let him go either.
As ancients say: Letting an enemy go will bring trouble for generations!
I hope you reconsider!
I've already sent Zhū Líng
and Lù Zhāo to accompany Liu Bei.
They may leave as his deputy officers,
but I have them to keep watch on him.
I know Liu Bei wouldn't...
Attendants.
Here!
Summon Xu Chu now.
Yes, sir!
General, look. The men sent by the Chancellor have arrived.
What have you come for, General Xǔ Chǔ?
Xǔ Chǔ
Styled: Zhòngkāng
By order of the Chancellor, you must go back, for there is a meeting.
Once the general is on the field, he can't accept the sovereign's orders.
I already took my leave before the Emperor with the Chancellor's permission. There's nothing to discuss.
You should leave.
If you insist, I will return to the Chancellor and pass your message.
Farewell!
Zhu Ling and Lu Zhao!
Here!
Order both the infantry and cavalry to march faster and maintain it!
Brother, why are you in
such a hurry to campaign?
I am like a bird in a cage, or like a fish in a net.
If we hurry, we will be like a bird soaring through heaven, or a fish within the sea.
We will never be restrained again! Let's go!
Elder Brother!