This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 22
The Battle of Guāndù (2)
My childhood friend, I never thought we'd meet like this!
I failed to pick the better lord,
as I was under that wicked Yuán Shào.
My words ignored and my ideas disregarded,
I chose to abandon him.
That's why I've come to an old friend,
and I hope I can be of service!
How brilliant! How brilliant! With your arrival,
the blessing of heaven is now mine.
Zǐyuǎn, what plan did you have for me to defeat Yuan?
I had told Yuan Shao to target Xǔdū, your most precious territory,
and attack you from both front and rear.
If Yuan Shao followed your plan,
I would have been destroyed.
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
How much grain is there left in your camp?
We could manage for a year.
Xǔ Yōu
Styled: Zǐyuǎn
Surely not.
I'm only jesting. We've only got half a year left.
Ziyuan, why act like this?
Come back! Sit down, Ziyuan!
I came to you in sincerity,
yet you'd deceived me so. You disappoint me!
Let's not hide from each other.
The grain in the camp is only enough for three months.
Ziyuan, why are you laughing?
Many have said you were devious!
Didn't you know that war is devious?
Tell this to no one.
We've only got one month of grain left.
Don't you lie to me! You're already out of grain.
How did you know that?
You sent someone towards Xǔdū to urge the grain shipments.
The letter fell into my hands.
Since you already know the truth,
I humbly ask for your strategy against Yuán!
Chancellor?
Away! No one enters my tent without my orders!
Yes...
Esteemed sire, you fight with a lone army against a vast enemy.
Mm-hmm.
Why didn't you ask a plan for a quick victory?
Is that not a path to suicide?
Whatever you want to say, Ziyuan, please say it.
My one plan, in only three days,
could have Yuan Shao's 700,000 man army fall apart on its own.
Would my esteemed lord like to hear it?
Don't be like that!
Whatever you wish to say, I will heed it.
I know well that my esteemed lord excels at war,
and that he surely knows what's most critical in defeating an opponent.
Sever his supply route?
Severing his supply route is like choking his throat.
But to defeat Yuan Shao,
merely cutting him from his supplies,
may still not mean striking him in the throat.
Ziyuan, there is no need to beat around the bush.
Just say it.
Yuan Shao's provisions for all 700,000 of his army.
All of it is stored in Wūcháo, that is his'throat'.
But if that's the 'throat', then surely
Yuan Shao has placed heavy guard.
How could we feasibly strike it?
This is why I say we can beat Yuan Shao in three days.
Although Wūcháo is very important,
Yuan Shao hardly pays notice to it.
He actually sent Chúnyú Qióng to garrison it.
That Chunyu Qiong is a careless drunkard,
so isn't that like offering Wūcháo
to you with open palms, my esteemed sir?
May I ask, Ziyuan, how should our army seize Wūcháo?
It won't be hard! Just select your elite cavalry,
disguise themselves as Yuan Shao's officer Jiǎng Qí,
and head towards Wūcháo to 'protect' it,
using this chance to burn it's supplies.
Thus in three days, Yuan's army will be in disarray.
Good. I'll head to Wūcháo personally!
Chancellor, seizing supplies is risky!
You should not lead the attack!
Xǔ Chǔ
Styled: Zhòngkāng
If the Chancellor goes personally, there may be disaster! Please reconsider!
Zhang Liáo
Styled: Wényuăn
The validity of Xǔ Yōu's plan is still unknown!
You should not be so trusting!
Wūcháo is Yuan Shao's granary.
How could he not defend it?
Xǔ Yōu may be duplicitous. Do not go.
Moreover, how could 5,000 men beat
Chunyu Qiong’s tens of thousands?
Report!
Chancellor, 5,000 elite soldiers are ready!
Excellent.
Chancellor!
How is this good?
Wūcháo is the 'throat' for Yuan Shao.
Raiding his supplies is
what determines our final outcome.
Xǔ Yōu's defection is Heaven's will helping me defeat Yuan.
Our supplies are gone, so entrenchment is difficult.
If we do not use Xǔ Yōu's plan,
it is no different than waiting for death.
Moreover, raiding the supplies had occupied my mind for long.
Gentlemen, do not doubt it!
If you go, I fear Yuan Shao will exploit this feint to attack!
I've made my decision!
Chancellor, please give the order!
When dusk parts, we shall head towards Wūcháo.
Yes sir!
Relay my orders!
Raise a fire on all sides! We shall strike together!
Yes!
Chúnyú Qióng
Styled: Zhòngjiān
What's this commotion?
General, look! Wūcháo is on fire!
Wūcháo is in danger! Have the rear-troops save the provisions!
Everyone else, follow me!
Yes sir!
Reporting! Suī Yuánjìn and Zhào Ruì
led troops to attack us from behind!
Officeers, keep charging forward with all your strength!
Deal with them when they get behind us! Now onward!
Chancellor, Yuan's troops are already here!
Rearguard, turn and fight to the death!
Force your way through!
Yes!
My lord, Wūcháo is in flames!
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
Gāo Lǎn
My lord, Zhāng Hé and I are willing to rescue it!
My lord, no! If they're seizing the supplies, then Cáo Cāo must be there himself.
Guō Tú
Styled: Gōngzé
In his absence, his camp must be empty!
We should send troops to attack their camp!
Upon hearing of this, Cao Cao will rush there!
His troops will be exhausted. Thus we can crush him, and inflict a great loss!
This is Sūn Bìn's "Besiege Wèi to rescue Zhào"
Note: Sūn Bìn of the Warring States period suggested sieging Wèi to distract the troops attacking Zhào, thus rescuing it.
Reasonable!
No! Cao Cao is cunning, if he left camp he would've already made preparations.
If we attack the camp and fail,
when they return from Wūcháo,
we'll be caught in a pincer attack!
That would only exasperate our situation!
Cao Cao only cares about larceny.
How could he spare troops for his camp?
Please! My lord, make your
choice now, and raid their camp!
My lord! Wūcháo is more important!
Both of your plans...
you two...
My lord!
Your words are...
They're both correct.
Zhang He and Gāo Lǎn!
Here!
Lead 5,000 men towards
Guāndù and raid their camp!
Yes!
Order Jiang Qi to take 10,000 men towards Wūcháo!
General,
were you sober last night?
If you are indeed sober, raise your eyes and see
that this is your dear, heavily guarded Wūcháo.
It's just as Ziyuan said:
How could Wūcháo not be lost
when Yuan Shao sent you to defend it?
Men?
Here!
Tattoo Chunyu Qiong's face and body.
Let him go back to Yuan Shao to humiliate him!
Yes!
Have all regiments disguise as Chunyu Qiong's
defeated soldiers and rush back to Guāndù!
If any come to save Wūcháo, kill them along the way.
Yes!
Xiàhóu Yuān
Styled: Miàocái
General, if we go any further, I fear
we'll be recognized by the Yuan troops!
Which group are you from?
We're Chunyu Qiong's subordinates!
We were defeated by Cao Cao's forces!
Jiǎng Qí
Hurry! Onward to Wūcháo!
Jiang Qi, halt!
We surrender! We surrender!
Send men to disguise as Jiang Qi's
subordinates to Yuan Shao's main camp.
Just say Jiang Qi has already defeated our forces and recovered Wūcháo.
Yes!
Hurry back to Guāndù!
Lift your head for me.
My lord...
What's that on your face?
Words...
What words?
My lord...!
Talk!
It is... the Drunkard of Wūcháo!
You drunk? You drunk!?
I'll let you drink your fill!
Men!
Here!
Take him away!
Drown him in wine!
My lord!
Let him drink his fill!
My lord! My lord!
Report!
Speak!
My lord, General Jiang Qi sent a messenger!
He's already defeated the Cao troops at Wūcháo, and recaptured it!
Then... then... then what about Guāndù?
Zhang He and Gao Lan are currently engaged in battle.
The results are unclear.
Then... then send more troops to Guāndù!
You must take Guāndù!
Yes!
How is the battle?
It's just as Zhang He said.
Zhang He and Gao Lan's persistent attack failed.
Cao Cao got them from behind.
Where are Zhang He and Gao Lan now?
According to defeated troops, they broke out with a hundred or so cavalry.
Their current location is unknown.
If they return,
how could our lord not want to blame you?
Did those two survive?
Yes.
How fares Guāndù?
It is not going well!
It is not going well?
Well, if it is like that, does Cao Cao have an elite force at Guāndù?
What happened?
My lord, are you still unaware of this?
Guāndù had small defenses,
but Zhang He and Gao Lan had no will to fight!
What are you saying?
Those two have long wanted to surrender!
They intentionally refused to fight!
They dare to mock me!?
Emergency! Emergency!
Zhāng Hé
What is it?
Master Guō Tú sent me to report this to you!
The lord is furious!
Gāo Lǎn
He said you two didn't even try to fight.
What!
He wants you executed as an example to the entire army!
Who said we didn't fight!?
This is an emergency, so I wouldn't dare remain here!
Farewell!
Please be careful my generals.
We fought with all we had,
yet this is what we get for it!
Our Lordship's messenger has arrived!
Salutations to two generals.
Generals, our lord has asked you two to return to camp.
Why has our lord summoned us?
I don't know.
I truly don't know!
You don't know?!
General don't!
Yuan Shao listens only to slander and lies!
He will be defeated sooner or later.
How could we sit and wait for death?
Better to surrender to Cao Cao!
By the Chancellor's orders,
Zhang He and Gao Lan may enter the camp!
Chancellor...
The surrendering general is the one at Guāndù who
matched against Zhāng Liáo in a fifty-bout duel, Zhang He!
I shall go out to meet them personally.
Chancellor,
Zhang He and Gao Lan coming to defect so suddenly is suspicious.
Should you really meet them?
I shall treat them graciously.
If they possess ulterior motives, I will change their heart.
Chancellor!
Generals, since you've come from afar to join me,
you have gained my respect.
Chancellor!
Please rise.
You generals joining me is like Weizi leaving Yīn(-Shāng) and Hán Xìn joining Hàn.
Note: Weizi was a duke known for his virtue who joined the Zhou to defeat
the Shang dynasty, and Han Xin was instrumental in the rise of the Han dynasty.
Now now, please rise.
Please rise.
Beat him!
Anyone else who spreads rumors and disturbs morale,
beat them!
Yuán Tán
Styled: Xiǎnsī
Beat him!
Who's there?
Father, it's me.
It is you.
What are you doing here instead
of staying in your camp?
Father,
a few defeats won't decide our fate.
Father, I know you're upset, but you shoudn't drink!
Xǔ Yōu left.
Zhang He and Gao Lan have betrayed me!
Right now, the people are aggrieved!
My lord!
My lord! He died! He died!
What?
You scum!
Men!
Here!
Have this ill-tongued bastard taken away!
And flog him 300 times!
Yes!
My lord! My lord! Spare–
Afterwards, ask him who died!
Father!
Scum! I want him beaten!
Spare me!
Father!
Beat him!
We are falling apart, not due to
the enemy, but due to ourselves.
What did you say?
Father, you should rest now for your own good.
My lord, I've discovered someone else
who seeks to disturb our military's morale.
An officer in the rear camp said to someone,
"At the rate things are going, it won't take long
for us to be defeated by Cao Cao."
Are you sure?
Every word and sentence.
Seize that man! Execute him!
Let his body be shown to the entire army! Anyone else who disturbs morale,
anyone else who spreads rumors, I'll kill them myself!
Yes!
Come back!
My lord?
You must ensure our units are on guard.
This is most important to our military's morale.
Yes, yes!
You!
Generals!
Tonight, we defeat the Yuan's forces!
Surround them from all sides!
Annihilate them!
Mister Tián Fēng!
Tián Fēng
Styled: Yuánhào
Sir, why are you here?
Mister Tian, my utmost felicitations for you!
Why are you congratulating me?
General Yuan is returning from Guandu in great defeat!
700,000 troops were all annihilated!
In the beginning, you urged our lordship
not to raise a too large an army too early.
Now you've been proven right! Our lordship is returning!
Wouldn't this mean getting back your position?
Mister Tian, what is the matter?
I will die soon.
Mister Tian Feng!
What are you saying?
General Yuan seems open but is petty,
he does not heed loyalty and honesty.
If he had won, in his bliss I would be pardoned.
Yet he had lost, he will meet with me in shame.
There is no hope for me!
Mister Tian Feng, that...
Out of the way!
What's the matter?
By our lord's orders, we shall take Tian Feng's head!
Mister Tian Feng!
Chancellor, Yuan Shao escaped
with only 800 of his remaining cavalry!
This is Heaven's will! They are doomed to have an arduous escape!
Master Jǔ Shòu?
Master Ju Shou!
Jǔ Shòu
Master Ju Shou.
Hurry. Release this gentleman.
Yes!
I will never surrender!
Yuan Benchu had no wit and never used thy words.
Why the fervor for the ignorant?
Had I received you, nothing on this realm could worry me.
Sir, you have great ability,
but could not find a wise lord.
I value your knowledge and talent,
I would like to achieve greatness with you.
I would enjoy your tutelage.
Build a tomb for Master Ju
on the banks of the Yellow River.
Chancellor, look!
What are you so rattled about?
Chancellor, people within Xǔdū messaged with Yuan Shao in secrecy.
The letters were written in most sycophantic words.
Really?
Chancellor,
Chancellor can mark down every name on these letters, then arrest and execute each.
Have them torched.
Yes sir!
Chancellor?
Chancellor, why?
When Yuán Shào had the upper-hand, I could barely even save myself...
... Let alone them?
Chancellor.
These elders have come to offer wine to the Chancellor!
Chancellor!
Chancellor, during the reign of Emperor Huán,
Emperor Huán of Hàn, 132 – 168 AD.
there were people that predicted that after 50 years,
a certain benevolent man would climb here.
From today, 50 years have passed!
Yuan Shao has burdened his people, and thus they all dislike him.
Chancellor, you raised a most righteous campaign
to relieve their suffering. And in the battle of Guāndù,
you defeated the hundred-thousand hordes of the Yuan.
This is what was said 50 years ago.
It's a sign that the people may now look forward to peace!
Yes! Yes!
I can't possibly receive this boon!
Chancellor, we were born of this yellow earth
and drank from the yellow river for nearly a century.
How could I deceive before this great river?
Yes!
Chancellor, please!
If so, forgive your junior for acting on his own,
but I shall offer to this earth the wine and this water
to nurture such kindness as yours for ten thousand years.