This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 11
Battle of Wǎnchéng
What brings your esteemed presence here today?
Chén Guī
Placing troops along Beichang district...
...the horses are eager for another "radish" after those two cities...
This poses a military threat we must stop.
Lǚ Bù
Styled- Fèngxiān
Sir?
Why do you speak thus?
I'm just saying, my lord,
you...!
Not long ago, when Lord Yuán sent you
gold, silk, and lots of rice,
his true purpose was to bribe you
to eliminate Liú Xuándé!
But you, sir, shot an arrow through your
halberd to shut the issue down.
Now today, he has come to propose a marriage!
Intending to..?
He intends to take your daughter hostage!
Afterwards, he will come to attack Liú Bèi
and snatch Xiǎopèi from you.
If Xiǎopèi falls, then Xú province will...
Be in peril?
We would be done for...
This is known as the 'isolating a family' strategy!
'Isolating a family'?
In the future, Yuán Shù may come to ask for grain
or he will ask us for troops.
If you were to accept,
he will surely exhaust your supplies.
If you were to decline,
there will be trouble towards your family.
That would be abandoning your
relatives and inviting hostilities.
Regardless, I was told that Yuán Shù
had intentions to declare himself emperor.
That is an act leading to rebellion!
If you ally with him and he rebels,
then you, General, will be a relative of a traitor!
How could the world tolerate you then?
Chén Gōng misled me!
Men!
Here!
Order Zhāng Liáo and a few men to chase them!
I must get my daughter back now!
As you wish!
General Zhāng! You must chase my daughter and get her back!
Yes!
Zhāng Fēi, you oaf!
Leave the horses you've stolen behind!
General, the horses we bought were stolen!
Who did this?! The audacity!
I found out he is Liú Bèi's brother, Zhāng Fēi!
Large-eyed brute!
He's terrorized me too much!
Muster the troops! Muster the troops!
Zhāng Fēi, I will fight you and
see who's superior and inferior!
Liú Bèi
Styled - Xuándé
My brother, why did you lead your troops here?
I shot an arrow through my halberd, saving you,
but now you steal my horses!
Well, we needed horses.
I sent people to purchase them!
How could I ever steal your horses?
You told your brother Zhāng Fēi to be a bandit!
The horses from Shāndōng were coming
when he stole them!
Now you dare deny reality?
Zhāng Fēi
Styled - Yìdé
I stole your horses!
What're you gonna do about it?
Large-eyed brute!
You've repeatedly abused me!
When I steal your horses, you're angry!
When you stole my brother's land,
how did we feel?
Hurry! Sound the retreat signal!
My lord!
What is it?
We have returned all of the horses.
Sūn Qián
Styled - Gōngyòu
But that Lǚ Bù...
Bastard of three fathers!
Elder Brother, Lǚ Bù's attack on us is
so intense! Xiǎopèi won't last long.
Guān Yǔ
Styled - Yúnchǎng
Cáo Cāo despises Lǚ Bù the most.
Even though you, My Lord,
have already returned the horses,
Lǚ Bù still won't withdraw.
As I see it, it would be better to abandon Xiǎopèi,
go to Xǔdū, and seek shelter under Cáo Cāo.
We could ask for troops and
defeat Lǚ Bù again in no time!
Why need aid from Cáo Cāo?
Brother, I'm not scared of that Lǚ Bù!
Silence!
You! You always end up causing unneeded trouble!
Elder Brother, you!
Third Brother, you can't over drink!
Second Brother, are you against me as well?
What I'm drinking isn't wine, it's water!
We go under Lǚ Bù, then go under Cáo Cāo!
You may be able to endure it, but I can't take it anymore!
Who'll lead the vanguard and break the siege?
The sin is mine. I will give my life to get through!
My beloved brother...
We all know that you are a just and frank man,
and that you hate erratic and
dishonest people like Lǚ Bù.
Don't you think I feel the same?
But when a true man acts in troubled times,
they must be open-minded and upright.
In the face of adversity, we must bow to others and wait for the right time to rise again.
You can't oppose our fate.
At the third watch, we'll break out from the Northern Gate.
Yìdé, be the vanguard; Yúncháng, guard the rear.
Sūn Qián, Mí Zhú, and I will be in the middle,
protecting our families.
Yes!
We shall obey you!
Cáo Cāo
Styled - Mèngdé
Ah, Lord Xuándé, I assume
you've been well since we last met?
We've come to seek shelter.
I'm ashamed to ask it from you.
Ah, what are you saying, Xuándé?
You and I are like brothers.
Third Brother.
Come!
Lǚ Bù is one of the most wicked men.
He won't achieve anything.
I ought to punish him alongside you!
Today's banquet will help ease
your pain from losing your land!
Please?
Please.
My Lord, Liú Bèi is one of
many ambitious men in the world.
If we don't plan against him now,
we will surely suffer later.
Wénruò, you conceived both the 'two tigers competing for food'
and 'driving the tiger to devour the wolf' plans.
Both of them should've worked but failed.
Weren't they all plans against him?
Now this tiger was defeated and has come to us.
My Lord, you only need one phrase to eliminate Liú Bèi;
why use strategies?
My Lord?
Ah, Fèngxiào!
Fèngxiào, Xún Yù advised me to kill Xuándé.
What do you think about this?
Do not.
Why is that?
Liú Bèi is ambitious too.
If he lives, isn't he going to stir trouble?
My Lord, you formed a righteous army
to rid the people of evil.
Only your integrity will lure prodigies;
the lack thereof will repel them.
Xuándé has made quite a name for himself.
Now he has come to you in great peril.
To kill him would be killing a virtuous man!
Talents across the realm will be fearful
and will hesitate to join you.
Who else would you rely on
to pacify the realm then, My Lord?
You can eliminate one potentially dangerous person,
but dash the hopes of all within the four seas.
My Lord, you can't be too rash;
you must consider it carefully.
Sir, your words are what I truly think!
I was just speaking in jest!
Very well. I will make a statement to the court tomorrow
to recommend Liú Bèi as Governor of Yùzhōu!
My Lord, do not do that at all!
My Lord, do not recommend
Liú Bèi to the throne at all!
Liú Bèi is a hero and holds lofty ambitions,
never content to be a subordinate.
Giving him any land would be like caring for a tiger!
In the end, he won't stand being under other men;
better to get rid of him forever!
We should not dispose of this tiger,
let alone eliminate him this way!
This is an era where having heroes is essential.
I can't lose the hearts of them just because I want to kill him!
Guō Fèngxiào's belief is the same I have.
Say no more!
In the 2nd year of the Jiàn'ān era
under Emperor Xiàn,
while Cáo Cāo joined forces
with Liú Bèi to invade Lǚ Bù,
Zhāng Xiù, with Liú Biǎo,
stationed troops at the City of Wǎn,
wanting to attack Cáo Cāo and seize power.
On one side, Cáo Cāo attacked Lǚ Bù;
on the other, he led a grand army through three different roads to punish Zhāng Xiù.
Report! Xiàhóu Dūn, vanguard of Cáo Cāo's army,
has set up camp at Yùshuǐ!
Scout again!
Yes!
Jiǎ Xǔ
Styled - Wénhé
General?
Zhāng Xiù
Cáo Cāo is a capable commander.
All civil officials and generals
under his banner are experts in warfare.
Now he's leading 150,000 troops divided in three from three different directions.
This is a testament to his might.
We can't possibly face him.
Then according to your statement, Wénhé,
what do think I should do?
With your uncle dead and the
insufficiency of Liú Biǎo's army,
in my modest opinion... the best course of action...
we might as well do him a favor and just surrender.
What?!
So what you are saying...
is that it would be better to be
under Cáo Cāo's banner
with my eyebrows low as a
defeated enemy general?
That... this is a matter of time and might! A matter of time and might!
A matter of time and might?!
Receive the official seal!
Lead the way for my horse!
Diǎn Wéi
Is there any beauties within this city?
Dismissed!
Yesterday at night,
through the side of the chambers,
I saw a married woman, who looked very beautiful.
After asking, they told me she was the wife of Zhāng Jì.
A very beautiful woman...?
However, Zhāng Jì is the uncle of Zhāng Xiù.
Moreover, as he's recently
left this world, I'm afraid—
What about Zhāng Xiù?
He's just a defeated general.
So what if he gets mad?
How dare he complain about her!
Go. Take 50 armed men and bring them to me.
Go!
Yes.
My Lord, she's here.
May I dare ask for your name, ma'am?
I am the wife of Zhāng Jì, Lady Zōu.
Ma'am, have you've heard of me?
I've long heard of your name, General.
I am fortunate to meet you tonight.
It was for you that I allowed
Zhāng Xiù to surrender and live.
Otherwise the Zhāng clan
would have been exterminated.
I'm grateful, for I owe my
very life to your kindness.
To finally meet you today, ma'am, is heaven's blessing.
Ma'am, are you willing
to sleep with me tonight?
Being looked after by you, General, is the blessing of three lives.
But if you stay in the city for too long,
Zhāng Xiù will have suspicions, and
I fear outsiders will begin to gossip.
Tommorow, you will go with me
and dwell in my camp outside the city.
Am I willing to suffer such a big disgrace?
This won't do!
General, calm down!
Calm down?!
He kidnapped my aunt!
How can one hide their feelings
and do nothing?
If Cáo Cāo flees the city, he will camp outside.
Then there's his valiant general, Diǎn Wéi,
who acts as his bodyguard.
Nobody else may enter unless stated otherwise.
By restricting access from outside or inside,
they can be on guard.
If you act rashly, the consequences
will be extremely disastrous.
General?
For this matter... you must heed my advice.
Make sure not to leak it out!
In the following days, that
bastard will come out to discuss matters.
General, you need to...
You need to do it like this, in that way...
General, why have you called me?
Hú Chē'er.
Yesterday, Cáo Cāo called his
officers to a meeting.
I ordered many of my soldiers
to desert en masse.
With that excuse, I was able to camp
in the center of his camp.
Do you know my plan?
How could I not know?
Hú Chē'er
Then that's good.
Though my plan to move troops
hasn't made Cáo Cāo suspicious,
there is a man guarding the tent in the camp, Diǎn Wéi.
This man is very brave and fierce, and getting in will be most difficult.
I summoned you to discuss this.
What's fearsome about
Diǎn Wéi is his twin halberds.
My Lord, invite him tomorrow to have some wine.
Assure he gets really drunk, then have him return. Then—
Then what? What are you going to do?
I'll sneak into the tent and steal his halberds; no need to fear him anymore.
Good. Enact your plan.
Yes.
General, you sure can handle large amounts!
Cheers?
It's late already.
I can't get too drunk.
You're very famous! It's rare to even see you!
Just this once, drink as much as you want!
I must always be by my lord to protect him!
Like a leaf in the wind, I now wander.
Wǒ běn piāolíng rén.
Born under an unlucky star,
my life has been bitter;
Bómìng lì kǔxīn.
escaping from the chaos, I encountered you.
Lìluàn de yùjūn.
I am most grateful for
your kindness when we met;
Gǎn jūn píngshuǐ ēn.
your love brings but temporary happiness.
Jūn ài yīshì huān.
The beacon signals an auspicious occasion.
fēngyān zuò liángchén.
With tears in my eyes for your life,
Hánleì wéi jūn shòu,
wine conceals the scars of warfare.
Jiǔhén yǎn zhēngchén
Dim, so dim is the lamplight;
Dēng hūn hūn
deep, so deep is this tent.
Zhàng shēnshēn
The soft pouring of wine;
Jūn wàngqíng
the soft words spoken.
Qiè shàngshēn
An instant of elation;
Yīshà huānxīn
an instant of comfort.
Yīshà wēnxīn
Who will understand the meaning of my verse;
Míngri Yùshuǐ tóu
who will empathize with the person in this song?
Yí wèi yùn mái xiāng hún
My Lord! My Lord!
Your son, Cáo Áng, and nephew, Cáo Ānmín...
we found their bodies!
But General Diǎn Wéi...
General Diǎn Wéi?
Yes.
Where's Diǎn Wéi?!
My Lord!
Hurry! Hurry!
General Yú Jìn... he...
What about Yú Jìn?
Yú Jìn took advantage and rebelled,
attacking Xiàhóu Dūn's Qīngzhōu regiment!
He's killed many of our men!
How could this be?
When Yú Jìn heard of my defeat,
he did not come to rescue us.
Instead, he took advantage and rebelled,
like dropping stones on someone stuck in a well.
I will fight him with all I have!
Report!
My Lord!
Yú Jìn led his troops to pursue Zhāng Xiù
for more than 100 lǐ!
He won total victory!
My Lord!
We followed Yú Jìn, who pursued
Zhāng Xiù through several roads.
His strength is exhausted, and he found himself isolated.
The defeated troops have fled to Liú Biǎo!
My Lord!
Yú Jìn,
Some fellows accused you
of excessive cruelty and rebellion.
My lord, that—
My lord!
When the Qīngzhōu army rebelled,
Why didn't you tell me first
but fight them yourself instead?
Explain.
They were coming rapidly;
there was no time to report it.
My Lord, this affair was never General Yú Jìn's fault!
It is mine; I was too laid back!
The Qīngzhōu regiment took advantage and raided the countryside!
Thereafter, Yú Jìn killed those curs,
calming the people along the way.
Yú Jìn, when you saw me coming your way,
you didn't explain your actions.
Instead, you prepared for battle.
Explain.
Yú Jìn
Styled - Wénzé
The rebels were on us. If we didn't prepare,
how could we have resisted?
You didn't come to me to explain; did you not fear I'd wrong you?
Explanations are trivial;
defense is important!
My Lord!
General, even under pressure,
you were able to build a firm base.
You ignored slander and turned defeat into victory.
Even the famed generals of old...
could hardly compare!
My Lord!
Cáo Cāo not only lost his favorite general, Diǎn Wéi,
but also his beloved son and nephew, Cáo Áng and Cáo Ānmín.
Luckily, Yú Jìn and others did their best to aid him,
allowing Cáo Cāo to turn defeat into victory and danger into safety.
In the 3rd year of the Jiàn'ān era,
Yuán Shù proclaimed himself Emperor in Huáinán.
When he heard of it,
Cáo Cāo led an army of 170,000 troops,
joining forces with Sūn Cè of Jiāngdōng,
Liú Bèi of Yùzhōu, and Lǚ Bù of Xúzhōu,
to attack Yuán Shù through three directions.
Seeing himself surrounded by enemies,
Yuán Shú was forced to sail across the Huái River,
bringing treasures with him.
He ordered Lǐ Fēng and others to
garrison and defend Shòuchūn to the death.
Cáo Cāo was facing another enemy in a prolonged and bloody battle once again.
Please ask Rèn Jùn's subordinate, the supplies overseer, Wáng Hòu,
to come to my tent right away.
Yes.
My Lord?
Sit.
Alright.
Out of those 400,000 hú of grain we borrowed from Sūn Cè,
how much are left?
Not that much left.
There's barely enough to feed 170,000 men.
Then you need to reduce the rations
for each soldier at the moment.
But if they complain, what to do then?
I have another solution.
My Lord, even if we reduce the rations,
it's only enough for three days!
Three days?
Yes.
Is that so?
Three days?
Three days.
Who thought to reduce our rations?!
Why are they taking our food?
Yes!
Speak!
Whose idea was it?!
Whose idea was it?
Speak up!
Beat him up!
My Lord!
Look what's happening out there!
By reducing rations, the soldiers are rioting!
They're saying that you've cheated them!
My Lord!
My Lord! Think of a way!
Otherwise, they will all mutiny against us!
I...
I was thinking of borrowing
one thing from you to calm them.
I hope you won't resent me for this.
What 'resentment?'
What does My Lordship want to borrow from me?
I...
I will borrow your head and expose it to them.
What?
My Lord!
I've done nothing wrong! How can you-
I know that you're innocent,
but if I don't kill you, the army will mutiny.
After you die, your wife
and children shall be in my care.
You need not worry for them.
My Lord!
Men!
Here!
Wáng Hòu knowingly distributed small rations.
The crime for withholding rations, according to military law, is...
death!
Yes!
It was him, the supplies overseer?
You deserve death!
He deserves death! Kill him now!
My Lord, I will take my leave for the last time...