This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 31
Riling of Zhōu Yú
Gentlemen, please.
I have long heard of Zǐjìng speak of your talents.
I'm honored to meet you today and wanted to ask your advice face to face.
Zhūgě Liàng
Styled: Kǒngmíng
I am only of modest ability,
please forgive my boorishness.
Since you, sir, have been assisting
Liú of Yù-Province, battling Cáo Cāo at Xinye.
Sūn Quán
Styled: Zhòngmóu
Surely you must know of Cáo Cāo's actual strength.
Do you not know how many troops the Cao army has altogether?
With cavalry, infantry, and naval troops combined: more than a million.
Are you sure it's not a trick?
It is no trick. Cáo Cāo initially had 200,000 Qing-Province troops.
He gained 500,000 or 600,000 by defeating Yuan Shao —
— 300,000 or 400,000 via recruiting in the Central Plains —
— and 200,000 and 300,000 via surrendered soldiers from Jing Province.
Calculating from this, it is no less than a million and a half.
I only said a million so as not to scare everyone here at Jiangdong.
Huáng Gài
Styled: Gōngfù
Lǔ Sù
Styled: Zǐjìng
How many generals are under Cáo Cāo?
Counting crafty, sharp advisors,
and capable, veteran officers?
Hardly less than one or two thousand.
After taking Jīng Province, does Cáo Cāo have other plans?
Why else, other than to take Jiangdong —
— is he constructing defenses along the river and preparing warships?
Since he indeed wants to conquer us —
— War, or peace?
Why not, sir, decide this for me?
Chaos abounds in the world,
and lords contest for their place —
And today's Cáo Cāo's reputation is mighty and his strength seems invincible.
Although Lord Líu Bèi continues to struggle, he's been defeated repeatedly.
I would suggest the General to measure first  —
— If with the peoples of Wú and Yue, you can contend with Cáo Cāo  —
— then might as well break off ties now.
If you feel your foundations are weak  —
— Why not kneel to his rule and avoid slaughter?
This morning, I said this to the men of Jiangdong.
Zhāng Zhāo
Styled: Zǐbù
Everyone seems quite willing to surrender to Cáo Cāo,
General, why not follow Heaven's will and the people's wishes, and seek peace and ease?
If it is indeed as you say, why does Líu Xuande not surrender?
In history, when Qí-State's Tían Hēng  —
Note: Tían Hēng was one of many leaders of the rebellions against the late
Qin Dynasty in 209-207 BCE, and was a member of the Qí-State's royal family.
— led five hundred warriors to an island, and swore never to surrender,
All five hundred heroically kept their oaths.
The Imperial Uncle Líu is of imperial lineage!
His talent is unparalleled, he is admired by all. If he is defeated, then it is the will of Heaven.
Rather be as Tían Hēng and break like jade —
— so how could he kneel and beg,
and go to serve the nation's villain?
Sir, that was far too wanton!
I admonished you many times, but you refused to listen!
Today, if my lord was not magnanimous, he would surely chastise you.
Your words, sir, are entirely too contemptuous of my lord.
Why does Sun Zhongmou have such little forbearance?
Though I have the plan to defeat Cáo Cāo,
he refused to ask, so why should I tell him?
If your plan to defeat Cáo Cāo is so good, then I earnestly ask you to tell me now!
In my view, Cáo Cāo's million-man army —
— is but a horde of ants.
I need but wave my hand, and the million Cáo troops are but dust and powder.
Sir, please wait a moment— let me bring my lord to hear this.
Libelous, that Kongming!
My lord, I too have thus criticized Kǒngmíng—
— yet he laughed sire as shallow-minded in return.
It seems that Kǒngmíng already has a plan to defeat Cáo Cāo in his mind.
He would not say this lightly, so my lord, why not seek to learn this from him?
So Kǒngmíng already has a strategy,
and purposefully used wordplay to goad me?
I was shallow-minded, and nearly put great matters at risk.
Let us go!  My lord, please.
Sir Sleeping Dragon  —
My words were offensive, may the general please forgive me.
Servants!  Here!
Prepare a banquet in the rear hall, to host the Sleeping Dragon.
-Yes sir!
-Sir, please.
Please
Oh, does sir also enjoy listening to music?
Sir Sleeping Dragon is talented in old musics.
When in Longzhong, he was skilled in playing the Liángfùyín.
Ah no, I merely enjoy music.
Come, sir, please.
Pity that Gōngjǐng is not with us —
— else, Sir Sleeping Dragon would have met a kindred spirit.
I have long heard of his charms.
Even the children's songs of Jiangdong say thus.
'If the song has err, Zhōu-láng can take care.'
But, pray tell, where is Gōngjǐng now?
I ordered him to Lake Fanyang, to conduct naval exercises.
Sir, please —
At the start of all this, many men rose and each dominated a region.
But now, Yuan Shao, Yuan Shu, Lu Bu, Líu Biao and others, have all perished—
Only me, Liu of Yu-Province, and Cáo Cāo remain.
I cannot cede all the lands of Wú to another—
— But since Líu Bèi was just recently defeated, how could he resist Cáo Cāo?
Though my lord is defeated, Guan Yunchang still leads ten thousand elite troops—
— While Líu Qi also has ten thousand soldiers at Jiangxia.
As well , Cáo Cāos's army, having marched south over such long distances, are extremely exhausted—
Not long before, while pursuing my lord—
— His light cavalry ran 300li in a single day and night —
— As they say, the bolt at the end of a strong crossbow's range cannot pierce even raw silk.
Besides, northern troops are unskilled at naval combat—
— while the people of Jing-Province are unwilling to serve Cáo Cāo.
If the General and my lord could unite in purpose —
— then Cáo Cāo will surely be defeated.
If Cáo Cāo is beaten, then he will return north.
With the waxing might of Jing-Province and Eastern Wú —
— we can stand as the legs of a crucible,
in a balance of power.
Victory or defeat depends on this battle. May the General decide!
Your words are enlightening.
I have decided, and will hesitate no longer.
Come, come, drink a few more cups!
To tell you the truth, I have not ate like this for many days.
My lord —
My lord has fallen for Kǒngmíng's plot!
Yes! Yes!
If you battle Cáo Cāo, my lord, how do you think you compare to Yuan Shao?
Back then Cáo Cāo's army was small and his generals few,
but he could still wipe out Yuan Shao in one fell swoop.
Not to mention, today he wields an army of a million to march southward —
— how could you take your enemy so lightly?
Yes! Yes!
My lord, if you listen to the words of Zhuge Liang, and rashly march out —
— then it's as if you are putting out a fire while carrying dry twigs on your back.
-Indeed, indeed!
-Lord must reconsider.
My lord, Líu Bèi is in defeat and only seeks to borrow the armies of Jiangdong to stop Cáo Cāo's forces!
Gù Yōng
Styled: Yuántàn
How could my lord bear to be used by others?
Sire!
My lord!
My lord, you are sagacious,
— so do not be shaken by those coward gentry who fear death and seek to live.
If my lord hesitates like so, you will used by others
Please retire, and let me think on this.
Yes.
My lord, the State Mother has arrived.
Mother.
Mother, everything is peaceful here,
and you need not worry.
Son, I have heard you do not eat nor drink, and cannot sleep. Is there something troubling you?
State Mother Wú
Cáo armies press upon my borders, and seek to devour our Eastern Wú.
My military and civil officials cannot decide between peace or war, and debate endlessly.
I had thought to fight, but I fear we are outnumbered.
But if I surrender, then I fear that Cáo Cāo would not tolerate my survival, and thus I cannot decide.
Do you still remember their last words?
'In internal matters, inquire Zhāng Zhāo' —
— 'In external matters, inquire Zhōu Yú!'
Why not invite Zhōu Yú here and ask him?
Thank you, mother! In my bustling, I had forgotten his words.
Zhongmou, no matter how important the matter, your health is vital.
If my son ever fell to misfortune —
Then how could I face our family who have passed?
Mother, please be at ease, I will send someone to Fanyang —
— and invite Gōngjǐng back.
Zhōu Yú
Styled: Gōngjǐn
-My husband!
-My wife!
Husband!
The lord had just sent someone here, order you to return quickly—
— but you have returned.
My dear, Cáo Cāo's army is upon our borders —
— but sire has not yet decided between peace and war, so I cannot be at ease.
My dear, you must be tired from the long journey.
Xiǎo Qiáo
My dear wife, when I rushed back here overnight, all I could think about was you.
You just exaggerate!
As your wife, how could I not know my husband's nature?
For state matters and military duty, you could forget to eat and sleep.
How can there be time for his family?
Sir Zhang Zhao is here!
You've just come back, and we can't even have a moment of peace.
All right then, tell them to go back, I am going to spend tonight with my wife.
Go, my dear.
Grand Marshal!
Everyone, please.
Grand Marshal, please.
Please.
No, no, you talk first.
Grand Marshal!
Zibu, if you have something to say, please say it.
Grand Marshal, do you know of Jiangdong's current plight?
I do not know.
Cáo Cāo has a million men, assembled upon the great river.
His war declaration arrived yesterday, inviting our lord to hunt with him at Jiangxia.
While he does mean to devour us,
he has not revealed the intention —
So we will persuade our lord to surrender tomorrow, to prevent calamity from coming to Jiangdong.
But we didn't think Lu Zijing would bring
Líu Bèi's strategist Zhuge Liang from Jiangxia.
They want revenge on Cao army, so purposely used his words to goad my lord
But Zijing... is blind and stubborn. We wish the Grand Marshal would make his decision.
Does everyone here favor surrendering?
Bù Zhì
Styled: Zǐshān
All of our opinions are the same as Zibu's.
I have long favored surrendering.
Everyone, please, go back now.
When meeting our lord tomorrow morning, I will indeed have something to say.
Please.
Gōngjǐng, do the gentry favor fighting or surrendering?
According to your opinion, my dear, should we fight or surrender?
Our lord dominates Jiangdong, and has been established for three generations.
With the river to the north, and fertile lands to the South,
Virtuous lords above, and famed generals below.
How could we kneel before the tyrant of the Hàn?
Cheng Pu and other generals have arrived.
-Grand Marshal.
-Senior General Huang.
Senior General Cheng
Please...
Grand Marshal, did you know that the southlands are soon to belong to another?
I did not know.
Grand Marshal—
— We have built our realm with General Sun —
Chéng Pǔ
Styled: Démóu
— and fought hundreds of battles large and small to have the six commanderies of Jiangdong.
But now, a group of advisors dare to persuade our lord to surrender to Cáo.
It is shameful! Despicable!
We would rather die than surrender!
May the general persuade our lord to plan decisively and muster the armies —
— so we can do our duty unto death!
Everyone, do you all agree on this?
We would rather die than surrender!
I, Huang Gai can lose my head, but I swear to never kneel and surrender!
Good!
I've been looking forward to fight Cáo Cāo, how could I kneel and surrender?
Generals, please go back.
Wait until I have met our lord tomorrow, and I will have an answer.
Please.
Grand Marshal, farewell.
Grand Marshal.
Grand Marshal. My brother Zhuge Liang has arrived from Jiangxia as envoy.
Zhūgě Jǐn
Styled: Zǐyú
He says Líu Bèi wishes to ally with Eastern Wú, to defeat Cáo Cāo together.
The officials have not come to a decision —
— but because my brother is
the envoy, I dared not say much —
— and waited for Grand-Marshal to decide on this matter.
What is your opinion on this, sir?
Those who surrender find safety.
Those who fight... May not survive.
I have made my own decision.
Officials, generals.
I have already chosen between war and peace.
I will discuss this with our lord tomorrow.
Farewell.
My dear.
My dear, I have already seen off the military and civil officials  —
—  so no one else will disturb us.
Perhaps not.
Grand Marshal, Lu Su has arrived.
See?  Didn't I tell you?
The nation is in crisis,
and yet you are so relaxed here.
Zijing, you need not say more. Just invite Sir Kǒngmíng here.
Good, I will let this fine couple reunite for a moment.
The strings on the qin-zither have been neglected thus.
My dear, I am sorry.
Grand-Marshal.
Please.
Marshal,
Right now Cáo Cāo's army is gathered on
the river, sire cannot decide at the moment.
I'm not sure what the Marshal's opinion is?
Cáo Cāo seized the emperor and commands the lords —
His strength is great
and his might cannot be stopped,
Fighting will lead to defeat, while surrendering would lead to safety. I've already made up my mind.
Tomorrow when I meet with the lord, envoys shall be sent to offer surrender.
Sir Kǒngmíng, please.
Please.
You speak wrongly, sir.
The realm of Jiangdong was built over three generations, how could it be ceded to another?
And now the very fate of the nation is in just the General's hands.
Why do you listen to the discourse of cowards?
Countless lives reside in the six commanderies of the southlands.
If war breaks out, then the people will fall to deprivation.
If I propose war, then would not all the young and old of the southlands heap blame upon me?
Wrong. With the general's heroism,
and the natural barriers of Eastern Wú —
— Cáo Cāo may not get his way.
Why does sir laugh so?
I laugh because Zijing refuses to see the truth!
Why does sir laugh at me also?
Gōngjǐn's idea to surrender to Cáo Cāo is indeed reasonable.
Cáo Cāo is a master of war, unrivalled in the world.
Of the many heroes who contested him, almost all have perished.
Only Liu of Yu-Province fails to understand this, and fights back—
— only to fall to routing to Jiangxia, barely alive.
Should the general decide to surrender to Cao.
You protect your family on one hand,
and on the other can preserve your riches and luxury.
My lord's fate is up to heaven, do we really need to pity him?
Sir, do you want my lord to kneel before the nation's villain?
Do not worry, Zijing, I have a plan.
We need neither cede our territory,
nor offer our seals and declare servitude —
—in order to drive back Cáo Cāo's million strong host.
What brilliant plan do you have, sir?
You merely need to send a single messenger to ferry two persons across the river —
If Cáo Cāo can have these two, his hordes will furl their banners, and retire from the field.
The Southland's parting with these two would be no more than a leaf from a tree —
—or a grain of millet from a granary.
Who are these two persons?
When I was in Longzhong—
—I heard that Cáo Cāo was building a new pavilion near River Zhang.
It was to be named 'the Bronze Sparrow Terrace'.
A magnificent edifice.
AKA. Tóngquètái (铜雀台)
He sought far and wide for beautiful women to fill its chambers.
We know Cáo Cāo as a lecherous man. He has heard patriarch Qiao of Jiangdong has two daughters —
Eldest called 	"Dà Qiáo", younger called "Xiǎo Qiáo".
— beauties who make birds alight and fishes drown, abash the very blossoms and outshine the moon.
Cáo Cāo has once vowed —
— to have only two dreams; 'To sweep the realm and see the imperial throne in peace —
—and the sight of those two women
on the Bronze Sparrow Terraces —
— and retire in pleasure, and die without regret.
His million-fold host that threatens Jiangnan, has for its real aim these two women.
Why not seek the patriarch Qiao and his daughers with gold, and exchange them over the river?
Once has these two, he will be content and return to the capital.
What proof do you have for Cáo Cāo desiring the two Qiaos?
Cáo Cāo has a son, Cáo Zhí, styled Zǐjiàn.
A prodigy and a writer of great genius —
At the command of his father wrote a poem
‘An Ode to the Bronze Sparrow Terrace' —
Its theme the fitness of his house for sovereignty and his possession of the Two Qiaos.
Can sir recite this poem?
I admired the gorgeous language of this poem, thus I committed it to memory.
May I request a recitation?
I will try.
Ode to the Bronze Sparrow Terrace ("铜雀台赋")
by Cáo Zhí, edited by Luó Guànzhōng
Beside His Esteemed steps I do rejoice so —
mounting storied towers in delight —
Peering down on River Zhang's ever-flow —
whence fruits abundant promise glory —
Aloft rises twin towers either flank —
one Jade Dragon, and a Phoenix Gold —
With 'Two Qiaos' holding from Southeast thus —
Note: The surname "Qiáo" sounds similar to the word for "bridge", so Cao Cao's words were heard differently by Zhou Yu.
would joys last dawn to dusk evermore  —
Look upon the royal city's beauty —
behold the clouds lie floating beneath —
Oh rest, Oh grace! —
To only be bound by heaven and earth —
bright as the glory of sun and moon —
Ever honored and ever enduring —
age immortal as the Father-East —
May I wish this tower ever standing —
for joys of ages never failing!
That bastard Cao dares to mock me!
Recall when the Son of Heaven granted a princess of Hàn to wed with Xiongnu for peace—
Why should we miss for two women of the crowd?
Sir might not be aware—
Da Qiao was the wife of my former lord Sūn Bófú, and Xiao Qiao- !
Xiao Qiao is Grand Marshal's very own wife!
I truly did not know!
My words were poor, it's a crime worthy of death! Please forgive me!
Grand Marshal!
I swear this world cannot hold both Cáo Cāo and I!
Grand Marshal, though this is infuriating, please think carefully before proceeding.
Sun Bofu and I have such a deep friendship —
— And now upon me is great responsibility for the state —
— so how could I kneel before Cáo Cāo?
To speak frankly, I was merely testing you, sir.
Since the moment I left Fanyang, I had already made up my mind to campaign against Cáo Cāo.
Though the path might be filled with blades, I will not waver.
May sir lend me his strength, so we may break Cáo Cāo together.
If you deem me worthy, I wish to aid you with to my utmost —
— and will be as the Grand Marshal commands.
Good!
Tomorrow we will go and see our lord, and discuss the matter of raising an army!
My dear.
I have heard all of Kǒngmíng's words back there.
Even if Cáo Cāo did not raise his armies specifically for us —
If the southern lands fall, then I fear—
Me and our children will fall into the hands of the Cáo villain.
My wife, please don't worry, I will convince my Lord to fight Cáo Cāo
Are the children asleep?
They are asleep.
For a great general, yet such a heart for children.
Men are not wood or grass,
how could I be heartless?
I will be giving orders from the terrace, spurring the horses and armies.
Above I can return my lord's deep generosity —
— Below I can bring glory for my wife and family, my life's wishes fulfilled.
I have always loved your talent —
— and I wish for you to build unparalleled achievements—
— something that I and the children can feel pride for as well.
Zhuge Liang, in order to unite with Wú to resist Cáo, using his ingenuity—
— cleverly changed the meaning of the "Two Qiáos" in the "Ode to the Bronze Sparrow Terrace."—
—thus enraging Zhōu Yú to act —
— and revealing his hidden will to challenge Cáo Cāo to the death.
The blade's light and sword's shadow fade,
Àndànliao dāoguāngjiànyǐng
Far away is the drum and horn's serenade;
yuǎn qùliao gǔjiǎo zhēng míng
Before my eyes appear, one by one,
Yǎnqián fēiyángzhe yīgè gè
Such vibrant visages.
xiān huó de miànróng
The old paths are buried now—
yānmòliao huáng chén gǔdào
—by a fire burning through every town.
huāngwúliao fēnghuǒ biānchéng
But time, you cannot take away that string—
Suìyuè a nǐ dài bù zǒu, nà yī chuàn chuàn
—of still familiar names.
shúxī di xìngmíng
What man will determine victory or death?
Xīngwáng shéi rén dìng a
Prosperity and decline have no cause, indeed!
shèngshuāi qǐ wú píng a
A single breeze scatters the clouds—
yī yè fēngyún sàn nà
—and the world as we knew it vansih with them.
biànhuànliao shíkōng
Meetings and partings happen for their reasons—
Jù sàn jiē shì yuán a
—but these comings and going still rouse our feelings!
líhé zǒng guān qíng a
We carry the weight of our pasts—
dāndāng shēngqián shì a
—and account little for the opinions left behind.
hé jì shēnhòu píng
The Long River turns to tears—
Chángjiāng yǒuyì huà zuò lèi
—its waters rise in a song;
Chángjiāng yǒuqíng qǐ gēshēng
In the skies of history there yet shines a few stars—
lìshǐ di tiānkōng shǎnshuò jǐ kē xīng
—as in the world of man dwells a spirit of heroism, ever galloping forward.
rénjiān yī gǔ yīngxióng qì zài chíchěng zònghéng