This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 15
Yuán and Cáo Raise Troops
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Liu Bei has left Xǔdū,
just as Fengxiao had said!
By releasing the enemy one day, I have brought everlasting trouble upon myself.
Chancellor,
Xún Yù
Styled: Wénruò
Che Zhou is a trusted subordinate.
He was originally intended to be govern over Xú-Province.
You can send a letter to Che Zhou and order him to think of a way to kill Liu Bei.
Chen Deng has come.
Chē Zhòu
Lord Che, what have you summoned
me for?
The Chancellor has sent me a secret letter, telling me to get rid of Liu Bei immediately.
This way, he can avoid future trouble.
I have called you to discuss this matter.
That...
Chén Dēng
Styled: Yuánlóng
Liu Bei has received an order to suppress
Yuan Shu, thus gaining merits from the court.
Why does the Chancellor want to kill him?
Besides, he has won the hearts of Xú-Province's citizens.
I know the people burnt incense and blocked the streets
just to ask the Chancellor to have Liu Bei manage Xú-Province.
That hasn't changed.
However, when the Chancellor gives an order, how can we refuse?
Liu Bei will eventually return after pacifying the people.
You can set up an ambush
outside the city and engage him.
I will hold off his rearguard using crossbows from the city.
So?
We shall follow your plan, Yuanlong.
Then I take my leave.
Yuanlong.
If we can work together with one heart and mind,
we can report the success to the Chancellor.
Of course.
General Chen, what irks for you to come here?
Che Zhou was ordered by the Chancellor to kill Liu Bei!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
Che Zhou has placed 1,000 troops outside the city
to attack the imperial uncle when he returns!
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
That bastard Che Zhou! I will kill his entire force!
Che Zhou is already prepared.
If we act rashly, we will be defeated.
Better to think of a plan to capture him.
Plans, plans, plans! Let's see if that bastard
Che Zhou can stop my serpent spear!
Brother, you must restrain yourself.
You!
Who's goes?
General Zhang Liao, sent by Chancellor Cao!
Wait until I report to general Che.
Report it quickly!
General Che.
Yuanlong, what is it?
Why didn't you open the gates for them?
If they're the Chancellor's troops, he will be suspicious if I don't let them in,
but if they're not and I go
welcome them, I fear it's a trap.
Yuanlong, I can't be at ease since
I placed my men into an ambush.
I think this issue does not bode well.
Are you the army of General Zhang?
Yes, sir!
It's hard to identify people at night.
Station your troops outside for now.
After dawn, you may enter the city.
But Liu Bei is onto us!
We can't wait, open the gates now!
Yuanlong, look there!
Yuanlong?
Yuanlong!
Have the ambush troops follow me
outside the city to investigate.
Yes.
Where is General Zhang?
Wretch, You dare plot to kill my brother?
Prepare to die!
Open the gate! Open the gate!
I have showed the Chancellor's letter to General Guan.
If you changed your mind, please
get off your horse and surrender, general!
Chen Deng, you traitor!
You have led me into your trap, but I will kill you!
General Guan!
General Guan, your blade is too hasty!
Second Brother and Yuanlong,
thank you for welcoming me.
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Where is Third Brother and Inspector Che?
I wanted to tell you myself.
That traitor, Che Zhou, tried to kill you, so I took his head.
Would he really try to do such a thing?
It wasn't Che Zhou's idea.
The one who wanted to kill the Imperial Uncle was Cao Cao!
Where's Yide?
He wanted to kill Che Zhou's family in vengeance, he's in the city.
Is he trying to ruin me?!
Elder Brother!
I have exterminated Che Zhou's entire...!
Elder Brother, the one who deserved it is dead,
but those who didn't are dead too.
What's the use of lamenting anymore?
Who should we kill? Who shouldn't we kill?!
Che Zhou was a trusted officer of Cao Cao. Didn't you know that?
When we left Xuchang,
you said it yourself, brother.
From now on, we would no longer be tied back.
If we must kill, then kill we shall! Isn't it too late to regret it?
Too late?
If Cao Cao has an excuse to raise
troops against us, what are we going to do?
Don't worry, brother.
When Cao Cao comes, Yide and I will meet him and that will be it.
Second and Third Brothers, you are mistaken.
Your unworthy brother knows that you don't fear Cao Cao,
but we have just come back to
Xú-Province without a secure foothold.
Besides, our men are few and provisions scarce. What do we have to boast about?
If the people of Xu-Province get caught up in war once more...
because of us...
Elder Brother!
Lord Xuande, you needn't worry. I have a plan that can fend off Cao Cao.
Right now, the only one Cao Cao fears is Yuan Shao.
Yuan Shao watches over Ji, Qing, You, and Bing provinces.
His army numbers a million; he has a myriad of talents.
Why not send a message to Yuan Shao asking for reinforcements?
I have never made contact with Yuan Shao.
I had just defeated his younger brother, Yuan Shu.
Why would he want to help me?
There is a man who has had good relations with the Yuan family for three generations.
If he writes a letter, Yuan Shao will certainly send help.
Lord Xuande, why not try?
Elder Brother.
Liu Bei just destroyed my brother,
so I did not want to help him.
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
However, he had Master Zheng Xuan send a letter, asking for help.
Master Zheng...
Liu Xuande is a hero of our age.
If I listen to Master Zheng and aid Liu to oppose Cao,
what would you all think?
My lord!
After years of raising troops,
the people have suffered greatly.
The granaries are empty and taxes are heavier by the day.
We cannot draft more into your grand army!
We could claim victories to the Son of Heaven.
If we can't reach the Emperor,
then we can memorialize that
Cao Cao has been abusing power.
After that, we only need to station troops at Liyang.
Concurrently, we can use our righteous army to launch an expedition against the rebel,
and settle the land within 3 years!
Tian Feng is right!
However...
His words are improper.
With your divine might and the strength of the north,
destroying Cao Cao is as easy as turning one's palm.
What need is there
for a three-year plan?
If we hold off, it may ruin your great plans.
Your words make sense!
Wanting to pacify such a scourge
will make the army feel righteous.
Yet confident from their numbers, the army is arrogant.
A righteous army is strong,
but an arrogant army will perish.
Cao Cao's laws are pragmatic and his men are well trained.
If we don't use the 'petition' strategy
Tian Feng's strategy.
and instead raise nameless troops,
then our army will be at a disadvantage.
I beseech for you to reconsider.
Fine.
He is wrong!
Our men are better than Cao Cao's.
How could they be called 'nameless'?
Our warriors are brave; our men are in high spirits.
If we don't settle this matter swiftly, we will be inviting disaster.
I ask that you listen to Master Zheng, my lord.
Join Liu Bei in his righteousness and destroy that rebel, Cao Cao.
This is the wish of both Heaven and the people.
Gentlemen!
All of your words seem reasonable,
but it is hard to discern who is right and who is wrong. What should I do?
Master Zheng...
Chancellor, if your migraine is unbearable, why don't you rest for a while?
If Liu Bei makes contact with Yuan Shao and ally together, what can I do?
We can't underestimate Yuan Shao's power.
We can't send men at the moment. We can only ask for peace.
Yuan Shao is a incompetent fellow. What need is there for peace?
Sir, you are mistaken.
Yuan Shao's territories are vast and strong.
His subordinates, such as Xǔ Yōu,
Guō Tú, Shěn Pèi, Páng Ji,
are all wise strategists.
There is also Tián Fēng and
Jǔ Shòu. Both are loyal ministers.
Yan Liang and Wen Chou are men of peerless bravery.
Others, like Gāo Lǎn, Zhāng Hé, and Chúnyú Qióng,
are all renowned generals of the land.
Sir, why say that Yuan Shao is a incompetent fellow?
Even though Yuan Shao's troops and warriors are numerous,
his laws aren't scrupulous and his discipline lacking.
Tian Feng is willful but obstinate;
Xu You is gluttonous but not bright;
Shen Pei is devoted but not resourceful; and Pang Ji is resolute but inept.
All these people are incompatible with each other.
Sooner or later, there will be internal conflict.
Furthermore, Yuan Shao relies on the numbers and is indecisive.
Even with thousands of his men, how can he succeed?
Jǔ Shòu
Report!
Report, my lord! Master Xu You is here.
Gentlemen.
Gentlemen!
Lord Xu has a lot of insight.
Let's listen to what he has to say.
My lord?
Lord Xu, you came at the right time.
Master Zheng has asked me to send reinforcements to Liu Bei against Cao Cao.
Should I mobilize the army or not? Please enlighten me, Lord Xu.
Xǔ Yōu
Styled: Zǐyuǎn
My lord, if you use the many to invade the few
and use the strong to attack the weak,
you can punish the rebels and restore the ruling house.
You must mobilize an army!
Lord Xu, that is exactly what I thought of!
I want Shen Pei and Pang Ji to oversee conscription.
Tian Feng and Xu You will be my advisors.
Yan Liang and Wen Chou will be my commanders.
Gather 150,000 cavalry and 150,000 infantry,
a total of 300,000!
Have them march to Liyang at once!
Yes!
My lord!
My lord, if we are to justly punish
Cao Cao, we must first list his vices.
Send a declaration of war to every commandery, denouncing him.
This is the proper way of doing things.
Excellent!
Kongzhang?
Here.
Enumerate the many crimes of Cao Cao and send it to every commandery.
Yes!
Chén Lín
Styled: Kǒngzhāng
Of old, the strength of Qin was debased by a weak ruler, thus Zhao Gao domineered.
Empire acted to his bidding,
it's wealth and power behest to his whims,
for those against him were subdued, and none dared to speak with candor.
To this end there came to be the Disaster of Wangyi, the massacre of many families.
Note: Referring to late Qin dynasty, when Zhao Gao forced Qin Er Shi to commit suicide in order to gain more power.
Reviled to this day,
forever is his name served as a warning.
Why did you stop reading?
Keep reading.
Don't stop without my orders.
The Ducal Minister of Works, Cáo Cāo,
whose grandfather was the Regular Attendant Cao Teng, who, with Zuo Guan
and Xú Huáng, tormentors of the common men,
violate the state with depravity.
His father, Cao Song, this eunuch-adopted groveler,
with his venal false-name, now a briber of the powerful,
stealer of titles, and corrupter of imperium.
Cao Cao, his obscenity inherent,
loves only to carnage, revels only in ruin...
My... my head feels better now!
Who wrote this Essay of Denunciation?
Essays of Denunciation (檄文) were manifestos written as condemnations of character and declaration of war, written as far back as the Xia-Shang dynasties and as late as 1920s.
I have heard it comes from Chen Lin's own hand.
Those who write these letters need to back it up with real spirit.
Even though Chen Lin's style is excellent, it's a shame...
that Yuan Shao's strategy is lacking!
His strategy is lacking!
Chancellor, Yuan Shao and his 350,000 army are marching from Liyang.
Call everybody here to discuss. We must prepare!
Yes.
Liu Dai and Wang Zhong!
Here!
You two will lead 50,000 men.
The vanguard will be Liu Dai
and the rear will be Wang Zhong!
When you march out, you will go to Xú-Province and attack Liu Bei!
Roger!
After Generals Liu and Wang have set out,
the rest are to follow me towards Liyang to counter Yuan Shao.
Understood!
Bring us the commander's banner.
Give it to general's Liu and Wang.
Yes.
This...
This is your own banner.
How could we dare to fly it in your name?
An order for you to fly my own banner when attacking Xú-Province
is just to make an empty show of strength.
Once you've set up camp, don't advance recklessly.
Once I have defeated Yuan Shao, I will march to defeat Liu Bei.
Yes sir!
Excellent.
I don't know if the Chancellor has already arrived at Liyang.
I'm more concerned about when he can go to Xú-Province.
The Chancellor's army should come as fast as possible.
That way, I can return this banner, lest it be destroyed.
There's no need to worry about someone as irrelevant as Liu Bei.
When we arrive to Xu-Province, just send someone to Hebei
to inform the Chancellor, nothing more.
Elder Brother!
Our spies at Hebei have returned!
How is the military situation?
Yuan and Cao have not
engaged in combat yet.
They haven't engaged yet?
Yes!
Have some water and explain!
Yuan and Cao have brought their men. Even though their armies are fierce,
Liyang has a strong defense. They're locked in a stalemate.
Why won't they fight?
It's said Xu You is unhappy with Shen Pei's command.
Ju Shou resents that Yuan Shao hasn't used his advice.
All have selfish motives and won't press the attack.
Yuan Shao was unable to make up his mind.
Now that he is even more uncertain, he will not make a move.
And why won't Cao Cao make a move?
I couldn't get enough information.
I only heard that Cao Cao ordered Lü Bu's former general, Zang Ba, to guard Qing- and Xu-provinces.
Yu Jin and Li Dian are along the Yellow River.
Cao Cao himself has stationed his men at Guandu.
Where is Cao Cao now?
He could be at Liyang.
He could be at Xǔdū (Xǔchāng). He could be at...
Where?
At Xú-Province!
What?
If he's in Xú-Province,
Then if this is true, then doesn't that mean
Cao Cao is the one camped outside?
Wáng Zhōng
The Chancellor didn't engage Yuan Shao. He's come back to Xǔdū secretly.
When he left, he ordered us to meet Liu Bei in battle.
Liú Dài
Styled: Gōngshān
Why won't you attack, General?
Liu Bei is a clever man.
If he discovers the Chancellor is not in the camp
he will join up with Yuan Shao.
How can you sit idly and not seize this opportunity?
How would you explain it before the Chancellor?
Since the Chancellor has ordered us to attack, you go first.
He has ordered you to go first.
I am the commanding general.
How could I go?
Let's stop arguing over who is the commander.
Per the orders of the Chancellor, we'll attack together.
So?
Is it proper to fight over who goes first?
Let's draw lots. Whoever draws the written note goes first.
Fine, let's draw!
You have to write them again!
You can't back down now, General.
March at once.
Fine!
The Cao army have left camp to march here.
Whose banner do they have?
The center holds Cao's.
We can't wait for their armies to attack us!
Elder Brother, send me with Second Brother to meet the enemy!
I heard Cao Cao's banner is nowhere to be seen in Liyang.
Why is his banner here, instead?
Cao Cao is full of tricks
and likes to supervise battles himself.
Thus, he decided not to fly his banner at Liyang,
which means the banner is being falsely raised here.
I think Cao Cao is actually not here!
We can send somebody to find out the truth.
I want to go!
You're too reckless and violent.
If the commander in the center really is Cao Cao,
I will capture him and bring him to you.
Elder Brother, I can scout out.
If you go, Yunchang, I can be at peace. You may bring 3,000 men with you.
Third Brother, defend the city. I'll be right back.
You only need to find out whether that's really Cao Cao!
Elder Brother!
Elder Brother, you may ask this man about the truth!
And who may you be?
My name is Wang Zhong.
What rank do you hold?
I am an assistant officer under Chancellor Cao.
Preposterous! How dare you march
under the Chancellor's banner?
I wouldn't dare! I was only following orders!
He ordered me to use his reputation to confuse the troops.
Where is Cao Cao now?
That...
Speak!
He's already returned to Xǔdū!
Men.
Here!
Prepare clothes and food for General Wang and put him in jail.
We'll discuss what to do once we have Liu Dai.
Thank you!
It's all thanks to you.
Elder Brother,
I shouldn't have killed Che Zhou, so I brought Wang Zhong alive.
This way you may use him in the future.
You were only keeping me safe. What are you saying? If anything, I should be ashamed!
Elder Brother...
Second Brother...
Elder Brother! Now that Wang Zhong is captured, let me go for Liu Dai!
Liu Dai was the Overseer of Shandong. When we fought Dong Zhuo at Hulao Gate,
he too was one of the lords there.
We can't underestimate him.
What can someone like him do?
Well, like Second Brother, I will just bring him here alive!
I just fear that you will take his life and ruin my cause.
If I kill him, you may take my head!
Very well.
I will give you another 3,000 men. Bring Liu Dai to me.
Liu Dai, you coward! Come out if you can!
Insult them! As much as you can!
Insult him! Louder!
Come on, insult them!
Insult them until dusk. See if they can stand it.
I cannot accept that my brother can take Wang Zhong alive,
but I can only throw empty insults!
Get up! Keep insulting them! Now!
Curse them!
Curse them! Come on!
Liu Dai, you coward!
Did you curse his ancestors?
We did!
Liu Dai must be furious!
He hasn't even stirred!
General Zhang!
Beat him up!
Harder!
General Zhang, a few strikes is enough. Must you be so angry?
That's my own business as a general! It has nothing to do with you!
Pass down my orders.
That rat Liu Dai doesn't even leave his camp!
He just stays in his camp, doing who knows what!
If he doesn't come, I'll go to him!
General?
Tell every camp to ready the troops.
Tonight, at the third watch, we shall lead a surprise attack on their camp.
I'll break down their gates!
How can you capture the camp if you are drunk?
Can we not postpone?
Coward!
It's just a few liters of wine.
How can that intoxicate me?
Pass down my orders. Everyone must prepare.
Yes.
And also...
don't forget to tie this soldier real tight.
When we strike the enemy... I'll... I'll offer him as a sacrifice before the banner!
Yes.
That Zhang Fei said...
that he would offer me as a sacrifice
before attacking the camp!
So that Zhang Fei is just a reckless idiot!
Just a few days without fighting and that's enough to work him up.
This is the opportunity for us to meet one plan with another.
Let him bring his troops to an empty camp.
I'll lure him into my trap!
I reckon that soldier is at Liu Dai's camp.
We will go by three separate ways at the third watch.
I'll lead the elite troops and cut off his rear.
On the middle route, thirty men will sneak into their camp and light a fire.
The two other groups will launch a surprise attack against Liu Dai when they see the fire.
Yes!
I wagered my own head before my brother.
If someone kills Liu Dai, I will kill the offender!
Officers, do you understand me?
Understood!
That's good. Don't you forget it!
Pass my orders! It's the third watch! We will assault their camp!