This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 9
Sūn Cè's Founding
Charge!
When Cáo Cāo and Lǚ Bù fought
each other at the borders of Shāndōng,
Sūn Cè, reduced to a lower rank, was quietly building up his power in Jiāngdōng.
After his father Sūn Jiān had died,
Sūn Cè started planning his grand undertaking.
First, he escorted his mother and
other family members to Qū'ē,
then he led his father's old troops
and attacked Lújiāng for Yuán Shù.
Yuán Shù
Styled: Gōnglù
Come, come!
Gentlemen, cheers!
Cheers!
Report!
Report! Sūn Cè has returned in triumph from Lújiāng!
Sūn Cè
Styled: Bófú
My respects, general!
You've returned victorious! Good! Good!
You're brave, Bófú!
Thanks to our tigerish generals and loyal soldiers!
Well said!
Today's banquet is to
welcome Bófú back!
Men, come!
Bring seating!
Yes!
Thank you.
Bófú.
Sit there.
Sit there!
Bófú!
Thank you.
If I were to have a son just like Young Sūn,
I would die without regrets!
Come come come! Everyone! Cheers!
Our Lord values you, Bófú.
Why not acknowledge him as your foster father?
He hit him!
You!
Bófú!
What is the meaning of this?
The senior generals Chéng Pǔ
and Huáng Gài have come to visit you, sir.
They're already at the gates.
Get them out! Don't bother me!
Yes.
My father used traverse across the nation.
What a hero he was!
Yet today, I... I...
Father!
Why are you giving me such a look?
Do you blame me?
That day, they all mocked me.
I couldn't retaliate.
Instead, I had to endure insults.
The senior generals refused to leave and waited here!
Your esteemed father
had once employed us.
Chéng Pǔ
Styled: Démóu
If you are unsure of something,
why not ask us?
Yet here you are, lamenting alone.
Sir, for your grand strategy...
why not ask Yuán Shù to borrow
troops and go to Jiāngdōng
in the name of saving your mother,
but in reality to build your own legacy.
Borrow troops?
But that Yuán Shù is paranoid.
How could he lend the troops?
But then...
Are we just going to be imprisoned to others' will?
I have the Heirloom Seal that my father left behind.
That Yuán Shù has long wanted to obtain such a treasure.
What if I gave it to him in exchange for troops?
Don't!
Huáng Gài
Styled: Gōngfù
Yuán Shù desires the Jade Seal.
Your father, esteemed general Sūn Jiān,
from this very Jade Seal had the grudges of all the other lords cast upon him.
Thus he was shot dead by Liú Biǎo's soldiers.
The life of your father in exchange for the Jade Seal.
How could you gift it to Yuán Shù?
Your concerns are reasonable.
The seal is indeed the treasure of the nation.
But without troops, we will eventually lose everything.
I want to trade the Jade Seal that took my father's life
for a nation he always dreamed of!
Bófú has the courage and
shrewdness to do great deeds!
He will succeed!
Bring us wine!
Yes!
My Lord!
Bófú, if you have something to say,
I will support you.
I... I always think about avenging my late father...
and now my old mother and younger siblings
are all at Qū'ē, in imminent danger!
So...
Avenging your father and saving your mother.
That is the way of a filial child indeed.
Sir, please let me lead a few 1,000 men
across the Yángzǐ to save my mother.
Let's not be impatient!
When I have spare soldiers,
I'll naturally let you lead them.
Of course, lending soldiers...
My Lord, right now, I have the
Heirloom Seal my father once had.
My Lord, if you lend me the troops,
I would gladly give it.
Bófú, are you serious about this?
My Lord?
Fine. I will lend you
3,000 soldiers and 500 horses.
Your status is modest, difficult to hold any power.
Ok! I will appoint you as Colonel of Assault,
and General of Bandit-Fighting.
Tomorrow, you can march to Jiāngdōng. How's that?
Thanks a lot, My Lord!
Could that person be Zhōu the Youth?
Brother Bófú!
Hah! It really is Zhōu the Youth!
Gōngjǐn!
Brother Bófú!
Zhōu Yú
Styled: Gōngjǐn
I was just going to Dānyáng to visit my uncle!
I never thought I would meet you along the way!
Truly, this is Heaven's will!
Just as I was leaving Yuán Shù,
I met you, Gōngjǐn! That would be Heaven's will!
I've heard much of your service under Yuán Shù and your skills in battle.
I wonder what are your orders now for this expedition?
This expedition was not directed by Yuán Shù,
but the will of my late father's soul.
Cheers.
I will march to Qū'ē, first to conquer
Liú Yáo, and avenge my father.
Yuán Shù has always been
suspicious of others.
Yet this time, he gave his army to you.
It seems Yuán Shù has not treated you that poorly!
Obtaining this army was not without cost.
I borrowed it from him.
Borrowed?
Yuán Shù gave me soldiers and horses
in exchange for the Heirloom Seal.
The Jade Seal?
You mean, the one from when the Luòyáng's palace was burning?
The seal your father found inside that well?
That is correct.
Damn it, that won't do!
Won't do?
Even after you've return his troops,
that Yuán Shù won't give up the Jade Seal!
He won't?
Absolutely won't!
What if he were to return the Jade Seal,
but I refuse to return his troops?
Damn it! This is no time to jest!
For just a mere army,
how can it ever compare to the Heirloom Seal?
Brother, you borrowed an army...
could it be that...
Right now, lords fight amongst each other.
The nation is in anarchy.
That Jade Seal, in the hands of someone like Yuán Shù,
will only just stoke his delusions of grandeur for a while.
But with an army in my hands, I can expand my domain.
One day, I will have all the six commanderies
and eighty counties of Jiāngdōng.
I will complete my father's great undertaking.
Brother, your ambitions are grand!
Come rain or shine, you have my sword!
Gōngjǐn! With you by my side,
my undertaking is as good as done!
Cheers!
You have lofty ambitions, brother,
but these troops are not enough.
You need the aid of Jiāngdōng's prodigies.
Elder Brother, do you know the two Zhāngs of Jiāngdōng?
The two Zhāngs?
One of them is Zhāng Zhāo
of Péngchéng, styled Zǐbù,
And the other is Zhāng Hóng
from Guǎnglíng, styled Zǐgāng.
Both of them possess the talent to rule the country.
They live here in seclusion to avoid chaos.
Why not acquire them?
Good! I will personally invite them!
Good!
Brother, be cautious when assaulting Qū'ē!
Cautious?
Within the city of Qū'ē, there is a fearsome general.
His name is Tàishǐ Cí.
A fearsome general?
Better than me?
Than you?
His valor is equal to yours!
If so,
then I must meet with him.
It seems you are eager about him!
Report!
Report! Sūn Cè led a force of
thirteen cavalrymen to scout on us!
Liú Yáo
Sūn Cè plans to lure us!
Do not fall for it!
I can lead the vanguard and capture Sūn Cè!
Tàishǐ Cí
Styled: Zǐyì
What would you know?
Sūn Cè, stop!
Which of you is Sūn Cè?
Who are you?
I am Tàishǐ Cí of Dōnglái,
coming to capture Sūn Cè!
So you are Tàishǐ Cí?
Just who I wanted to see!
Who are you?
I am Sūn Cè.
I won't fear even with the two of you!
Only a coward flees!
General Tàishǐ Cí! Lord Liú Yáo has come to your rescue!
General Sūn Cè! Gōngjǐn is here!
My Lord?
My Lord, today was dangerous!
If it weren't for Zhōu Gōngjǐn's
troops, you would have been...
Tàishǐ Cí really is a true warrior!
Tàishǐ Cí dueled sire for
many bouts, matching every move!
Truly remarkable!
I will capture him!
Were it that easy!
Wait, unfold it.
Take it away!
Yes.
Don't move.
Sir, keeping this brings ill omen!
Hang the robe on the tent.
My lord!
Brilliant, brilliant!
Gōngjǐn, what does this mean?
I think Brother Bófú keeping
this robe is not without reason.
Elaborate.
Brother, hold on!
Wait until I subdue Tàishǐ Cí,
then we can explain.
Tomorrow, I will lead a cavalry wing to strike Qū'ē. How does that sound?
Good! It is decided!
Sūn Cè's helmet is here!
Sūn Cè, come fight me, man against man, if you have the nerve!
Careful!
Sire killed a general by holding him, and another one by shouting!
A true Hegemon reborn!
Liú Yáo has been defeated.
I will capture Tàishǐ Cí!
I heard Tàishǐ Cí has recruited
able-bodied men from Jīng County!
Now he has over 2,000 men!
He claims vengeance for Liú Yáo!
All he has recruited in his haste are savages.
Zhāng Zhāo
Styled: Zǐbù
Unseasoned and vulnerable.
I want to capture Tàishǐ Cí!
Gentlemen, what are your suggestions?
It's easy.
We can divide our army into three routes,
From West, North, and South,
Attack Jīng County from three sides.
Leave only the East gate for passage
then lay an ambush about
twenty-five lǐ from the East gate.
Tàishǐ Cí will be there, exhausted, and ripe for capture!
A good plan!
Zhōu Tài!
Yes?
Scale the city walls at night, and start a fire.
Tàishǐ Cí will run!
Zhōu Tài
Styled: Yòupíng
Yes, sir!
Huáng Gài.
Here.
Have your squad to set up
ambushes at all vital crossings,
Dig out pitfalls or set a horse-tripper.
Be sure to catch Tàishǐ Cí alive!
Yes sir!
Good! Zhōu Tài has succeeded!
Capture Tàishǐ Cí, alive!
Breach the city!
Tàishǐ Cí! Where are you!?
Capture Tàishǐ Cí!
Why treat the general like this?
Untie him.
My apologies for the discourtesy, general.
Please.
I've longed to have your cooperation
like good rain after a drought.
I know you're a true fighter.
Liú Yáo is a pismire, unable to use your skills, thus he was defeated!
It must have been suffocating for you, great general.
If my subordinates have offended you,
I would ask for you to forgive me as their superior.
I'm just a defeated soldier, why waste time?
I crave Jiāngnán, so I long wanted to meet a foe such as you!
I could hardly rest.
I only regret that I didn't meet you sooner!
Now, I can't ever perform great deeds with you.
A great pity!
Zǐyì, why are you still standing there?
Just please come in!
Zǐyì, we are at war with one another.
If you were to capture me, would you harm me?
I don't... know.
Good. How frank.
If we fought each other, if I were
to receive no reinforcements,
if you and I went on like this,
would you know who wins?
I don't... know.
Good, good!
Zǐyì, ever since I led my first army,
I have not met a rival such as you!
Zǐyì, you are a true hero!
This robe is a proof of that, Zǐyì!
I had the robe hung to remind me that
there are people beyond a person,
and skies beyond a sky!
I've wandered for so long, and have never met a worthy lord!
General, if you don't mind,
I will serve you and dedicate my all to your cause!
With you by my side,
we can accomplish great things!
Come! Prepare a banquet!
Bring wine for Zǐyì!
Wait!
Lord Liú suffered a massive defeat
and their morale is low.
I want to go back, rally the remnants,
then lead them to assist you!
Will you trust me?
Thank you, General, for your loyal heart!
Good. I will return with my men, tomorrow at noon.
So it is agreed.
Zǐyì takes his leave!
Wait! Sir!
Get out of the way!
Let Zǐyì through!
What is this?
Sire, of old, when Shāng Yāng was enacting his reforms,
Note: Shāng Yāng was a Legalist scholar during the Warring States era
who reformed and strengthened the state of Qin.
he put a log as a symbol of trust.
We are following his example,
and put up this pole as a symbol of trust too
to indicate if it's noon,
and see if Tàishǐ Cí would come!
To build a legacy, you must first employ the able.
To employ the able, you must never suspect them.
To hold such suspicions,
how would their trust be won?
When my father left,
he left behind two items.
One was the Heirloom Seal.
I have traded it for an army.
And the other? It is this sword!
Today, this sword shall be my pledge!
I, Sūn Cè, employ people, not suspect them!
I believe Zǐyì is a man of his words!
By noon, Zǐyì will return!
My Lord! It's almost noon already,
and Tàishǐ Cí hasn't come!
You  shouldn't have let him go!
You shouldn't have trusted that knave!
It is already noon, yet there is no sight of him!
He fled!
What time is it?
It's noon!
Generals, don't worry.
We agreed to meet at noon.
It's not past noon yet.
How could you say that Zǐyì will be late?
Come, let's go and check!
Am I late?
Exactly at noon!
You truly are a just and honorable warrior, Ziyì!
Please look.
Gōngjǐn!
After the battle of Shéntíng Ridge,
I hung your torn robe in the tent.
Everyone was confused,
but only Gōngjǐn understood.
Today, you can explain it to everyone!
When heroes meet in battle,
they are elated for the spoils!
Bófú took the robe from the battle,
keeping it as a trophy to the Battle of Shéntíng Ridge!
That is reason one.
The second, Brother Bófú inherited his father's ambitions.
To plot his great cause, he must recruit prodigies. This robe keeps him aware that
to build a legacy, one must have prodigies.
The third...
Wait!
I dreamed if Zǐyì were to return, we would drink facing the robe.
Wouldn't that be living!
Come! Everyone with me, come welcome Zǐyì!