Episode 26
Returning to Recommend
HanziOverwrite
Zhang Fei
Styled: Yide StyleName·
It wasn't until meeting you that my horizons broadened.
Never did I expect our times together to be so short.
My heart is overwhelmed with grief.
My lord.
I know. Please.
Please.
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
I am sorely deprived of the fate to spend more time with you.
I hope you will serve the new Lord well, so that you will achieve status and fame.
I am but a man with little talent, yet you regarded me so highly.
Today's unfortunate parting is for my elderly mother.
Xú Shù
Styled, Yuánzhí
Even if Cao Cao threatens me  —
— I shall never, for the rest of my life, offer a single plan for him.
After you have gone —
— I shall also hide myself deep within the mountains and woods.
With my mother in distress, my state of mind is in turmoil.
Even if I stayed, I wouldn't be able to improve the situation.
My lord should find another talented and virtuous man to assist you in achieving your great cause.
My lord should not be so discouraged.
Among all the able men under the heavens, I am afraid none can compete with you.
How can I, a mediocre man, be deserving of such high praise?
I hope all your officers will serve the Lord well
so that your names are recorded in silk and your achievements go down in history.
My work will remain incomplete, you should not follow after me.
Please return, my Lord, and take care.
Even if I send you off for a 1000 li, farewells are unavoidable.
I will take my leave.
Yuanzhi!
Attendants! Attendants! Cut down all those trees over there!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
They are preventing me from seeing Yuanzhi.
They are hindering my view.
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Brother...
Go!
You have returned, can it be that you will not go to Xudu?
No.
In my turmoil, I forgot a thing of utmost importance.
There exists this ingenious man —
— who resides in Lóngzhōng, which is 20 li from the city of Xiangyang.
Why not seek for his assistance?
My heart is reduced to ashes with your departure.
Your words are incorrect, my lord.
If you remain this way then I will make my leave with a heart of stone.
Never looking back.
Yuanzhi!
What I said was indeed words of my heart!
I naturally know of my lord's heart of benevolence.
But uttering such words while your great cause is incomplete —
— will only disappoint me.
There are numerous talented men above me. I am neither jesting nor being humble.
Sire ought to seek after them for achieving your great cause.
In this case —
— I will trouble you to invite him to see me.
This man cannot be recruited with such informalities.
My lord must go seek him in person.
If sire is successful —
— it will be no different from the Zhōu gaining Lü Wàng, or the Hàn gaining Zhāng Liáng!
Lü Wàng AKA. Jiāng Zǐyá
How does this man compare with mister?
If you are to compare me with him —
— it is like comparing a frail horse with a qilin, or a jackdaw with a phoenix.
This man compares himself with Guǎn Zhòng  and Yuè Yì  —
Note: Guǎn Zhòng and Yuè Yì are two of the greatest philosopher-statesmen and military- generals of the Spring and Autumn and Warring States period respectively.
He has the ability to sew Heaven and Earth together, a genius who looms over all others.
I wish to know his name.
This man is from Yángdū  of Lángyá-commandery.
His name is Zhūgě Liàng, styled Kǒngmíng
He lives on a ridge of hills called Wolong-Hillock —
Note: Literally "Sleeping Dragon-Hillock"
— which is why he calls himself the Sleeping Dragon.
If you have this man's assistance you will have no worries about securing the realm.
Could he be the one from when people speak of
Sleeping Dragon  and Fledgling Phoenix?
Fledgling Phoenix is Páng Tǒng  from Xiāngyáng.
That Sleeping Dragon is indeed Zhuge Kongming!
Today I finally know who
Sleeping Dragon and Fledgling Phoenix are!
I did not expect them to be right before me.
If not for Mister's words, I would remain blind.
My lord!
I will take my leave.
Farewell.
With this departure, we are now separated by the earth.
I wonder when we might meet again.
In order to weaken Liu Bei's influence and gain the capable man for his own use —
— Cao Cao schemed to lure Xu Shu into Xudu.
After turning back 10 li to recommend Zhuge Liang to Liu Bei —
— Xu Shu took a detour to meet Zhuge Liang in Nanyang to tell him of his recommendation.
Having sent Xu Shu away, Liu Bei prepared to visit Zhuge Liang along with Guan Yu and Zhang Fei.
Mother!
Mother of Xu Shu
Mother, please forgive your impious son for arriving late!
It's you?
My son!
Mother!
Why have you come to Xudu?
Mother, I was assisting Lord Liu in Xinye.
Then I saw your handwritten letter to call for me, so I rushed here night and day.
Since when did I write a letter to you?
Then—
This...this is not my letter!
Then that is?
How muddled you are!
After you have roamed the world for so many years —
— I would think your learning had progressed, but you have regressed!
My son, you are an educated man —
— you know you can only fulfill either filial piety and loyalty, not both.
How can you not see that Cao Cao deceives and insults the Dynasty?
Liu Xuande's compassion stretches across the whole realm!
On top of that, he is also a kinsman of
the House of Hàn! You were assisting him!
You were serving a noble lord!
Mother, I...
But now, because of a scrap of forged letter—
— you left the light for darkness! You tarnish your own name!
You are a fool!
Mother...
My son —
How can I even look at you!
You have brought disgrace upon our family!
Now there is nothing left for you in this world!
Mother...
Mother, I...
Third brother!
Look, the gifts have all been prepared!
We can now go to Wolong-Hillock to visit Mister Zhuge Kongming.
Why should you trouble yourself? Just send me and Second Brother if you are concerned.
We shouldn't.
Mister Zhuge Liang is a sagacious prodigy of our time. I must go in person.
Alright, Elder Brother! Third Brother and I will go with you!
We can leave the matters here with Zilong.
My Lord, there is a gentleman outside. He is wearing a wide belt —
— has the shape of a pine and the frame of a crane, and he wishes to see you!
Could it be Sir Kongming?
Open the main gate and invite him in!
Mister Shuijing!
Since leaving you, I have been preoccupied with military affairs and couldn't visit.
Your arrival today comforts my longing heart.
Please.
I have heard that Yuanzhi is here, so I have come to see him in particular.
Yuanzhi has left for Xudu.
How can that be?
Yuanzhi hates Cao Cao the most.
Why would he go to Xudu?
Cao Cao imprisoned his mother and she wrote a letter for him to come.
So, Yuanzhi left for Xudu.
He was tricked! That was a trap of Cao Cao.
How is it so?
Please take a seat to talk, sir.
I have known that his mother is a honorable woman.
Sīmǎ Huī
Styled: Décāo)
Even if she was imprisoned, she would never write a letter to tell her son to follow Cao Cao.
This letter must have been forged.
If Yuanzhi didn't go, his mother would live,
but if he did go, she will definitely die.
Why is that?
She is a woman of high principles with a deep hatred for Cao Cao.
But also, she has a fierce personality.
Having witnessed her son abandon the light for darkness, she must feel ashamed.
She will die for honor.
She lived upholding it, and will die for it as well.
What a muddled man Yuanzhi is...
What a muddled man he is!
After Xu's mother hanged herself —
— Cao Cao led both his military and civil officials to commemorate her.
Xu Shu buried his mother in Nanyuan of Xudu and kept vigil at her tomb —
— As long as the gift was from Cao Cao, Xu Shu would firmly reject them —
— and secretly vowed to never come up with any strategem for Cao Cao —
— to keep his promise to Liu Bei.
I was a fool!
Mother!
Before he parted, he recommended Zhuge Liang from Nanyang.
What is this man like, sire?
If Yuanzhi went, then so be it.
But why should he ask Zhuge Liang to spit blood sweat, and tears?
Why say such a thing?
Kongming is a close friend with Cui Zhouping, Shi Guang —
— Meng Gongwei, and Xu Yuanzhi.
The talents of these four men surpass many.
Only Kongming is has superior talent and strategies.
He once joked to the four that —
—they would be governors and prefects if they went into politics.
The four then asked where his ambitions lay,
but he laughed without answering.
He regularly compared himself with Guǎn Zhòng and Yuè Yì.
His talents cannot be measured!
Hmph, Mister Shuijing,
Though I am no scholar, I have read
the Spring and Autumn Annals.
Guǎn Zhòng and Yuè Yì were two of
the greatest men of the Eastern Zhōu era.
Their achievements encompassed the world. For Kongming to compare himself with them —
— isn't that not too much?
In my opinion, he not only can compare with these two —
— he can also be compared with two other people.
Oh? Which two?
Jiang Ziya, who kept Zhōu lasting for 800 years —
— and Zhang (Liang) Zifang who set up the 400 years of Hàn.
Since the general is busy, I should not disturb him and will make my leave.
Sir, to be frank, I was just about visit Wolonggang to seek Mister Kongming with my two brothers.
Although the Sleeping Dragon has found his lord, he has not been born in the right time.
Pity, oh what a pity!
He's a true wise hermit, indeed!
The sky is like a round lid, oh!
The earth is like a chessboard, oh!
Humans are split into black and white chess pieces, ah!
They struggle for glory and honour, oh!
The victors are naturally at peace, ah!
While the losers are definitely busy and mediocre, oh!
There is a hermit in Nanyang, oh!
He sleeps but does not rest enough, oh!
The sky is like a round lid, oh!
The earth is like a qi-board, oh...
This ballad sees through the rise and fall of mankind.
I wonder who composed it?
...They struggle for glory and honour, oh!
The victors are naturally at peace, ah!
While the losers are definitely busy and mediocre, oh...
I heard a song pleasing to the ears from the field with elegant and deep verses —
— and would dare to ask, who is it composed by?
It was composed by Mister Wolong.
Where does Mister Sleeping Dragon reside?
Go south along this path and you will reach Wolong-Hillock.
There is a hut among the bamboo groves before the h.
That's where Mister Sleeping Dragon resides.
Thank you very much!
Thank you!
What a wonderful place!
Who is knocking at the door?
Please pass on that Hàn General-of-
the-Left, Precinct-Marquis of Yicheng —
— Potentate-candidate of Yù-Province,
Imperial Uncle Liu Bei, is here to visit Mister Zhuge.
So wordy, I can't remember that many titles.
Then simply tell him that
Liu Bei has come to seek him.
Teacher has already left this morning.
Where has he gone?
His journey is uncertain. I don't know where he has gone.
When will he return?
That is uncertain, could be three, five, or a dozen days.
Elder brother, since he's not here, why not return?
Let's wait a while more.
Elder brother.
The page already said that
the return date is uncertain.
We can go back for now, and later send for someone to find out when he will return.
It would not be late to visit him then.
When your teacher returns, please tell him about Liu Bei's visit.
Please take these gifts.
I can't take the gifts, but I will remember your words.
That man holds himself well, he must be Sir Wolong.
Excuse me, are you Sleeping Dragon?
Cuī
Zhōupìng
I am Kong Ming's friend, Cui Zhouping of Boling.
I have heard of your name, and am honored to meet you.
Can we please have a seat, I would like to inquire about some things.
Please!
Please.
Why do you wish to see Kongming?
The world is now in turmoil, and warfare is constant.
We have come to visit Mister Sleeping Dragon for a plan to pacify and reform the nation.
I see.
Eh, though sir seeks to pacify, while with kindness, chaos is but a constant since ancient times.
Untouched by the strength of men.
If you seek to ask Kongming to take the stage,
to restore the Hàn dynasty,
—I'm afraid it will be a wasted effort.
General must know that those who follow Heaven lives in harmony, while those who defy it fail.
How could men oppose the natural order of things?
Your words do carry insight —
But, as a kinsman of the House of Hàn, I should be restoring the Dynasty.
How can I cast away this Heaven's mandate?
Elder brother...
Your aspirations are understandable.
I am but a mere peasant, and am not enough to discuss such great matters with the emperor's uncle.
Since you have asked, I can only answer impromptu.
I receive your words.
But I wonder where Sir Kongming has gone?
I am also visiting Sir Kongming.
If so, shall we go to Xinye together?
I've been a free spirit for long,
I have no need for making a name.
Thank you for your intentions, I hope to meet again.
Didn't see Kongming, instead saw
an egghead! What a waste of time.
Those were the words of
a hermit... A hermit indeed...
The warrior has yet to create a name for himself.
Alas! For he hasn't met a sagacious lord!
Come! Another cup!
The warrior has yet to create a name for himself.
Alas! For he hasn't met his sagacious lord!
Don't you see, the sage is alone with the wine in a remote valley.
With whom can he discuss statesmanship and statecraft?
Instead of training troops in the winter —
— we're trudging here to meet with some braggart!
This cold will harm Elder Brother's health.
Why don't we return to Xinye?
I want Kongming to know my sincerity.
If Third Brother is afraid of the cold, you may return.
I will go ahead with Yunchang.
I am not afraid of death, let alone the cold!
I just don't want Elder Brother waste his effort.
Elder Brother, listen!
Elder Brother, look! There's an inn there.
Just the place for a drink to warm ourselves up!
Yeah.
Have another!
People speak of the history long past;
the valiant soaring eagle crowns the military officer.
For my life, I only have aspirations for the whole world.
Who is willing to comment on the heroes now?
Brilliant! What a brilliant song!
Must be another song by Sir Wolong!
Third brother, have some wine!
Come on in, come on in!
Good wine!
May I ask who among you is Sir Wolong?
Shi
Guangyuan
Who are you? What are you seeking Mister Sleeping Dragon for?
I am Liu Bei and would like to visit Mister Wolong —
— to ask for methods to cure the world and help the people.
We are all friends of Mister Wolong.
I am Shi Guangyuan from Yingchuan, this is Meng Gongwei from Runan.
We're nearly frozen, and we still haven't seen Kongming!
Elder brother, let's be on our way!
I have long heard of your great name, what a pleasure to meet you.
I have horses here for you.
May I invite you to visit Sleeping Dragons's Retreat for a chat?
We are mere peasants of the mountains and know nothing of state affairs.
Not to be bothered with.
Sir should mount your horse and seek Wolong yourself.
Please go ahead, as you wish!
Sorry to disturb, please continue drinking.
What arrogant men, and Elder Brother still wants to treat them with respect.
Elder Brother!
Elder Brother, you lower yourself too much!
If we are the kind to forsake strategy and just fight at the command table —
— how can we secure the world?
Innkeeper, innkeeper! Bring the wine!
I'm coming!
Hurry up!
Elder brother  —
— I accompany you through hell or high waters.
I only ask you to not suffer this kind of misery.
I understand your good intentions, my brothers.
But do both of you know what's in my mind?
Without the help of a sage man, how can the vows that we swore when we became brothers come true?
What great cause is there to talk about?
In terms of valor, no one can match you two and Zilong.
Yet, we have suffered continuous defeat all these years —
— roaming here and there without any firm foothold.
As Shuijing said, it was because we had no wise men to help!
Elder brother, say no more.
Let's be on our way after this cup of wine!
Kongming! Kongming! Are you at home?
Oh, dear third brother.
Let's go!
Oh, it's you again?
Is your teacher here today?
Teacher is reading in his room, please come in.
"The phoenix soars high, and won't perch on anything other than a parasol."
"The scholar is hidden somewhere and won't follow anyone other than his lord."
"While he is content with tilling his fields, how I love my hut."
"For now, he is above the qin and books, waiting for the right time."
I have longed to meet you, but haven't had the fate to do so earlier.
Since Teacher Shuijing and Xu Yuanzhi has recommended you many times —
— we came to visit your retreat, but had to return when you weren't here.
Today we have braved the snow and storm, and it is our great fortune to be able to see your noble face.