This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 27
Three Visits to the Thatched Cottage
General, are you not Liú of Yù-Province? Do you wish to see my brother?
Zhūgě Jun
This way, General.
Please, take a seat.
-This way.
-After you.
And sir, you are...?
I am the Sleeping Dragon's
younger brother, Zhūgě Jūn.
We are three brothers. My eldest is Zhūgě Jǐn, he is now an apparitor of Sūn Zhòngmóu in Jiangdong.
Kǒngmíng is our middle brother.
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
So, is the Sleeping Dragon at home today?
You've arrived too late, General.
My brother went with Cuī Zhōupíng yesterday to wander.
And where did he go?
Perhaps he went sailing on the river on a small boat —
—or to visit Daoist priests
in the mountains.
Or else, gone to a village where his friend resides —
— or to play the qin-zither
and weiqi in a mountain retreat.
His journeys are unpredictable. I know not where he has gone.
It seems we weren't meant to meet each other after all.
Twice I came yet haven't encountered this virtuous man. How regrettable.
Please, sit for a while.
Servant! Pour some tea.
Brother, the snow's falling fast. We better leave soon!
Since my brother isn't here,
I dare not keep you any longer.
Sir, I will visit again in a few days.
May I borrow a brush and ink?
I wish to leave a letter to your brother.
Bring a brush and ink.
Understood.
I, Liú Bèi, have long admired your exalted brilliance, sir Sleeping Dragon.
Twice I came to offer you my respects and twice went back empty handed. It is most regrettable.
I am a member of the imperial clan
and have witnessed crumbling of the dynasty and the rise of warlords.
Sinister forces abuse the sovereign and it makes my insides split with grief.
Although I have the ambition to uphold the House of Hàn—
I am truly lacking in statesmanship and grand strategy.
I wish in your benevolence and righteousness—
—Were you to generously use the talents of
Lǚ Wàng and carry out the brilliant plans of Zǐfáng —
Note: Lǚ Wàng AKA. Jiāng Zǐyá was the strategist who helped establish the Zhōu Dynasty.
Zǐfáng AKA. Zhāng Liáng was the strategist who helped establish the Hàn dynasty.
—then the Empire and the spirits of the nation would be fortunate indeed!
Allow me to express my intentions to you: I wish to once again purify myself—
—so that I can personally offer my respects and to receive your teachings.
Give this letter to your brother.
I shall take my leave.
Have a safe return, General.
...The freezing northern wind at night.
-The old master has arrived.
...Thick, dark clouds ten thousand li away.
In the vast sky snow disorderly flutters.
The mountains of old have completely changed.
I face upward and gaze upon creation.
Is it a fight between jade dragons?
One after another, scales are flying—
—and in an instant spread all over the world.
The mule is crossing a small bridge.
I regret alone that plum-flowers are so thin...
-Who is this gentleman?
My brother's father-in-law:
Master Huáng Chéngyàn.
Greetings, sir.
Lord Huáng, the lines you just recited are most inspired.
Huáng Chéngyàn
I learnt these lines of the Liángfùyín at my son-in-law's house.
Note: Liángfùyín (梁父吟) was a real folk-song from Shandong in the Han Dynasty.
According to Records,  Zhuge Liang had a particular liking for this ballad.
I remembered it as I saw the plum flowers and crossed the bridge, so I started to sing.
I didn't think such an august character was listening!
Dear sir, have you seen your son-in-law?
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
I also came to visit him.
My lord, four days from now is a most auspicious day!
You should part then.
Excellent, excellent!
I will fast for three days starting now
so as to purify myself for this meeting.
Note: Part of old Zhōu etiquette and ritual, as an utmost show of respect and reverence to someone.
We'll then go to Wòlóng-Ridge to visit Kǒngmíng.
No need to accompany me further, my lord.
No need.
Have a safe trip.
Brother, I have held back
the other two times.
But now I must speak my mind.
You have personally visited Kǒngmíng at Wòlóng-Ridge twice already.
The favor you show him is too great.
I'm afraid that Zhūgě Liàng fellow's reputation is but an empty one.
—That's why he's avoiding you
and doesn't dare meet with you.
Brother, you're familiar with the Spring and Autumn Annals. You should know!
In ancient times, before meeting the Commoner East of the Walls, Duke Huán of Qí had to go five times!
Note: Duke Huán of Qí was the first of the Five-Hegemons in the Spring and Autumn period.
How could it be less for me when I want to meet such a great talent of our age?
You don't need to go there personally, brother.
I will bring him here.
Servants! Ready my horse and bring me some rope. I'm going to Wòlóng-Ridge.
Brother!
Brother, what are you going to do?
Zhang Fei
Styled: Yide
I'm going to get Sleeping Dragon here on your behalf, elder brother.
And how will you do that?
If he doesn't come, I will use this rope
to bring him here!
Third brother!
Do you wish to ruin everything for me!?
It is because Cáo Cāo has so many strategists, could he defeat Yuan Shao.
That Sun Quan can command the lands of Jiangdong is thanks to the talents he has acquired.
They will surely become hegemons.
But I depend on Liu Biao, condemned to be entrenched a tiny place such as Xinye.
All this because I lack a great gentleman by my side who can administer stratagems and cultivate armies.
You are like my brother. We live and die together, yet—
—how could you still distort all that I care for...
Elder brother!
Elder brother.
Have you not heard the story of how King Wen of Zhou visited Jiang Ziya?
If even King Wen had to be so respectful, why do you intend to be this barbaric?
You will not go.
I shall go with Yunchang.
Brother.
Since you are both going, brothers, how can I stay behind?
Elder brother.
If you come with us, you must not be rude under any circumstance.
I understand, Elder Brother, I understand!
Sir Zhūgě Jun, is your brother at home?
He arrived at dusk yesterday.
You may meet with him today, General.
Many thanks.
How insolent! Why not just lead us inside?
He just waved his hands and left!
Each has their own matters.
We shouldn't step out of line.
I already told you. Mind your manners.
Understood, Elder Brother.
So you visit again, General Liú?
May I trouble you to tell your master that Liú Bèi has arrived to pay his respects?
The master is at home, but he is taking a nap in the thatched cottage.
Since that's the case, don't call him yet.
Brothers, wait outside for now.
The master is sleeping,
we shouldn't disturb him.
This way, General.
Why don't you wait inside, General?
I will wait until the master is awake.
Third brother!
The arrogance of this man!
Our brother is at his porch, and he's still sleeping!
-Third Brother...
I'll burn the cottage down,
see if he still sleeps then!
Third Brother! Third Brother! Third Brother!
Third Brother, you boor!
Third Brother...
I will go wake the master.
Do not disturb him.
As you wish.
Whom can wake one's dream,
all life have I known.
Long has spring-sleep last,
days go slowly past.
Are there any visitors?
Imperial Uncle Liú has been waiting outside for a while.
Why didn't you tell me sooner?
Let me change my clothes and meet him.
Zhūgě Liàng
Styled: Kǒngmíng
I am a lowly member of the imperial house from Zhuó-county.
For so long have I heard of your name, that echoes like thunder. Twice I came but we couldn't meet.
I left a letter, though I don't know if you've read it.
I am but a rural man of Nányáng.
I don't deserve the honor of being blessed by your presence.
After you, General.
Thank you, sir.
Wait here, brothers.
I have already read your letter, General.
One can perceive your worries for the state and the people.
However, I regret to say that I have but meager ability. You are asking advice from a lesser man.
You were recommended by master Water Mirror
and Xú Yuánzhí. How could theirs be empty praise?
I hope you don't abandon me, unworthy as I am, and offer me your guidance.
Decao and Yuanzhi are both exalted scholars of our age.
I am but a common tiller of soil. How can I discuss matters of state?
Why would you throw away a fine jade to look for a rough stone?
You are too modest.
Worthy men wish to command the talents of this world.
How could one idle away life in these secluded groves?
I hope you can consider the living souls of the Empire and free me of ignorance and folly
Since you insist, I will hear you, General.
The Hàn Empire is collapsing
and treacherous ministers are in power.
I have no power, but I wish to extend justice all over the realm.
However, I am lacking in strategy and my achievement inadequate.
If sir could be so gracious
and help us from this calamity...
We would be most fortunate!
Ever since the treachery of Dong Zhuo,
many champions of our time rose up in arms.
Cáo Cāo's strength couldn't compare with that of Yuan Shao's —
— yet he was the man to defeat Yuan Shao.
Not only was this for proper timing, but he also benefited from others' cunning.
Now, Cáo Cāo has a million men—
—and overturns the Son of Heaven to command over the lords. We cannot fight him for supremacy.
Sun Quan rules Jiangdong, where his family has had ties for three generations.
A prosperous land that's difficult to enter.
He can be used for support,
but must not to be conspired against.
Jing-Province borders the Han- and Mian-Rivers to the north —
—and gives access to the Southern Sea.
In the east, ally with Wu.
In the west, reach the region of Bāshǔ.
Military force is to be used there,
for their lord is unable to keep them.
For Heaven has granted you that land, General.
Does the general not intend to take it?
To the west of Jīng-Province, there is Yì-Province.
The roads are difficult, but the land is rich for a thousand lǐ.  Heaven's storehouse!
It's because of this did the High Forefather accomplish his imperial designs.
Note: Hàn Gāozǔ AKA. Liu Bang
But its lord, Liú Zhang, is dim-witted and weak.
Even though his land is wealthy,
he can't support his people and army.
Therefore, its talents long for an enlightened ruler.
You are a member of the imperial clan, General.
Your noble intent is well-known,
and heroes all over desire a virtuous leader.
If you can conquer Jing- and Yì-Provinces, fortify its natural barriers —
— make peace with western Rong-tribes, calm the southern Yí and Yuè —
— ally with the eastern Wú,
and reform the constitution within!
When the moment is right, send finest generals with the army of Jīng towards Rivers Yuan and Luo —
— while you lead the armies of Yì-Province
and attack from the Qínchuān.
Then, how could the people not welcome your armies with food and drink, General?
If you proceed as I just said, you can accomplish your grand design—
—and the Hàn Dynasty can be restored.
You wish to build your great cause, General—
—then let Cáo Cāo dominate the north
and Sun Quan have the shelter of the south.
While you, general, will have the support of the people.
This is a map of the fifty-four counties of the western regions.
First take Jīng-Province as your home, then seize Yì-Province as your base —
—  to form the legs of a crucible.
Note: Referring to a "Dǐng (鼎)"-ritual vessel, a Zhou-era symbol for power.
After that, you can aim for the Central Plains.
This is the grand strategy I present to you, General.
With just a few words you have opened my eyes, sir!
It's as if I can see the blue skies cleared from the dark clouds.
However...
Liú Biao of Jīng and Liú Zhāng of Yì are both members of the imperial family.
How could I bring myself to overthrow them?
As I have observed, and Liú Biao won't be in this world for long.
Liú Zhang isn't a man of great drives, and after some time, the western regions will be yours.
Without leaving this cottage, sir has already known the land will be split into three!
None throughout the ages can compare!
Though my name be of small repute,
my virtue meagre —
— I hope sir does not resent to offer me help. I will listen most reverently to your advice!
I have long been content tilling the land without any worry for this world.
I cannot accept.
Sir, will you really not leave the mountains and aid us?
I fear I cannot accept.
If sir won't leave their retreat,
what is left anymore for the people?!
what will become of the people?!
To realize the general's dream, I, Zhūgé Liàng, will vow to serve you with utmost loyalty.
Shù fǎ dú shī shū, xiū dé jiān xiū shēn
With his hair tied, learning,
cultivating virtue and character.
Yǎng guān yǔ fǔchá, tāolüè xiōngzhōng cún
He gazes up in the sky and down to his books, stratagems in his mind.
Though he's tilling the land,
forget does he not the troubles of the nation.
Gōnggēng cóng wèi wàng yōu guó,
Who knew such blood boiled deep in the forests?
shéi zhī rèxuè zài shānlín.
Phoenix, oh, phoenix!
High are your dreams!
Fèngxī, fèngxī! Sī gāojǔ
Lament you do for the world long fallen to chaos.
shì luàn shí wēi jiǔ chényín
Phoenix, oh, phoenix!
High are your dreams!
Fèng xī, fèng xī! Sī gāojǔ
Lament you do for the world fallen to chaos.
shì luàn shí wēi jiǔ chényín
Three visits you received in your thatched cottage to discuss at length.
Máolú chéng sāngù, cù xī zòng hénglùn
Bàn shēng yù zhī jǐ, zhé réngǎn xìng shēn
After half a lifetime, you find a kindred spirit. The one who sat still is deeply moved.
In the morrow, you took your sword and followed a worthy ruler.
Míng cháo xié jiàn suí jūn qù,
To soot your fan and headscarf on this odyssey.
yǔshàn guānjīn fù zhēngchén.
Dragon, oh dragon!
Wind and cloud meet at last.
Lóngxī, Lóngxī! Fēng yún huì
Uttering a long cry of relief.
Cháng xiàoyī shēng shū huáijīn
Going to and fro,
I cherish the wish —
Guī qù guī qù lái xī
wǒ sùyuàn yúnián háizuò lǒng mǔ mín
—to spend my last years as a farmer again.
Clear winds, bright moon, embracing me—
Qīngfēng míngyuè rù huáibào,
—as apes and cranes hear me play the qin.
yuán hè tīng wǒ zài fǔqín.
The path marked by Heaven ever-changing, as fate is hard to discern.
Tiāndào chángbiàn yì, yùn shù yǎo nán xún
Victory and defeat depends on guile and sincere vow for undying loyalty.
Chéngbài zài rénmóu, yīnuò jié zhōng kún
This great man of the world shows promise.
Zhàngfū zàishì dāng yǒu wéi,
He will plant the seeds of peace for the common men.
wèi mín bō xià tàipíng chūn.
Going to and fro,
I cherish the wish —
Guī qù guī qù lái xī
wǒ sùyuàn yúnián háizuò lǒng mǔ mín
—to spend my last years as a farmer again.
Going to and fro,
I cherish the wish —
Guī qù guī qù lái xī
wǒsù yuàn yúnián háizuò lǒng mǔ mín
—to spend my last years as a farmer again.
Clear winds, bright moon, embracing me—
Qīngfēng míngyuè rù huáibào,
—as apes and cranes hear me play the qin.
yuán hè tīng wǒ zài fǔqín.
Switch formations.
Yes, sir!
Acquiring your services is akin to a fish that gets water, Strategos.
Note: Zhuge Liang's initial rank was "Strategist-General of the Household" (军师中郎将);
an idiosyncratic title invented by Liu Bei.
My lord.
You are hard at work, Strategos.
After you.
My lord, these fresh recruits still need training. Only then can they fight.
Without training, a hundred men are only as good as one —
— but with proper drilling one man can equal a hundred.
Excellent. You've been working hard planning tactics and training our forces, Strategos.
For your hard-work, I personally weaved this hat as a token of my appreciation.
My lord, don't you have lofty aspirations?
Weaving hats is but a petty diversion.
How can you be so ungrateful?
My elder brother has worked hard day and night.
He made you this hat personally, but this is how you thank him!?
I understand your good intentions, my lord.
However, since I left the mountains I have worked to accomplish your grand design.
Not for a moment have I forgotten your aspirations.
Our current situation is as unstable as a pile of eggs.
I think you too can understand my view, my lord.
I understand your concerns, Strategos.
I also worry about the generals of Cáo Cāo.
Do not fear, my lord.
Please, let us inspect Bowang-Slope.
'Bowang-Slope'?
If Cao's forces were to arrive, they'd come directly to Xinye. What would they do at Bowang Slope?
Clearly, he just wants to enjoy the nature.
My lord.
Before us stands Bowang Slope.
My lord, Bowang Slope has many trees and bushes.
If Cáo Cāo's troops arrive, we will lead them to the gorge
and attack them with fire.
Let us keep surveying the terrain ahead, my lord.
Very well.
After the death of Sun Ce, Sun Quan inherited his brother's territory.
He guarded Jiangdong, while recruiting talented men from all over.
Cáo Cāo, in order to control Jiangdong —
— had ordered Sun Quan to send his son to serve the sovereign, intending to hold him hostage.
Sūn Quán
Styled: Zhòngmóu
Sun Quan refused.
After this, Cáo Cāo had intentions to march south.
Huáng Gài
Styled: Gōngfù
In the spring of thirteenth year of the Jian'an era —
Note: Year 208
— Sun Quan complied with his mother, Dowager Wú's will to avenge Sun Jian.
He marched against Liú Biao's officer, Huáng Zǔ.
He stationed his troops in the county of Cháisāng and seeked to take the lands of Jīng.
Sun Quan of Wú has killed Huang Zu and taken Xiàkǒu.
Now he's camped at Chaisang
and surely covets Jīng-Province.
Meanwhile, Liú Biao is bedridden with illness —
— and his son, Liú Qi, is incompetent and ignorant. He won't accomplish anything of note.
Liú Bèi, however, took refuge under Liú Biao after his defeat in Runan —
— and likely conspires to take over Jīng-Province. Since the time is right —
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
— wouldn't surely he take this opportunity to act?
He's now stationed in a tiny place like Xinye —
Xú Shù
Styled: Yuánzhí
— recruiting troops and accumulating provisions.
Xún Yù
Styled: Wénruò
One can easily see he has wild ambitions of hegemony.
I will march once again before he can spread his wings! There cannot be any delay!
I have recently heard Liú Bèi acquired the services of a strategist named Zhūgě Liàng.
What kind of man is he?
With the composed surname Zhūgě and the name Liàng —
he is of about twenty-six
or twenty-seven years of age.
Xiàhóu Dūn
Styled: Yuánràng
Now a whelp is his strategist?
Seems Liú Bèi has ran out of personnel!
Yuánzhí.
Yes, Chancellor?
Is Zhūgě Liàng an acquaintance of yours?
He is. His style name is Kǒngmíng and people call him 'the Sleeping Dragon'.
How is his ability compared to yours?
How dare I compare myself to Zhūgě Liàng?
I am as dim as the light of a firefly, but Zhūgě Liàng's brilliance is like that of the moon.
Chancellor, Zhūgě Liàng has the talent to take Heaven and Earth and can turn the tide of the war.
Gods and spirits cannot fathom his plans
and he conceals the ambitions of Heaven and Earth.
He is a genius of our age.
Liú Bèi has always held the ambitions of a kūnpéng.
Note: A kūnpéng refers to a legendary roc, a giant bird of prey transformed from a fish.
Now, Zhūgě Liàng is to him like water is to a fish. It's like giving wings to a Tiger.
I'm afraid... I'm afraid none under Heaven can rival him.
Xu Yuanzhi! Don't spout nonsense!
Zhūgě Liàng is as insignificant as a blade of grass.
What's there to fear?
Calm down, General Xiahou. Yuanzhi is right.
Liú Bèi is a hero and now he has Zhūgě Liàng in his service. We must not underestimate him.
Liú Bèi is just a rat! I'll take him alive!
Very well! Remember the army is not a place for jests.
I'll leave a pledge if necessary. I will capture Liú Bèi and Zhūgě Liàng alive.
If I fail, I'll gladly give my head to the Chancellor.
Very well!
I name Xiahou Dun as Field-Marshal.
Yú Jìn, Lǐ Diǎn  and Hán Hào will be his deputy officers.
Gather 100,000 troops and aim straight for Xinye.
Understood!