This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 13
White Gate Tower (Part 2)
Fengxian?
Lǚ Bù
Styled: Fèngxiān
Chancellor.
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Fengxian,
I have led my armies here
not to take Xu Province, but to help you, General. That is all!
I heard you, Fengxian, were going to send
your daughter to Yuan Shu for marriage,
but he declared himself Emperor.
That is the heinous crime of treason!
And you, sir, helped against
Dong Zhuo, earning glory!
Why would you forsake your merits
to bend yourself to a traitor?
If Xiapi falls, your regrets will be too late!
Better to surrender and
help us support the House of Han!
You won't lose your Marquis rank!
Fengxian, consider this!
Chancellor.
Withdraw first, and then
we may talk. How about that?
Rotten traitor!
What type of man are you?
Chén Gōng
Styled: Gōngtái
I know who you are!
A smooth talker!
See my arrow!
Gongtai! Why did you do that?
Chen Gong, I swear I will kill you!
Xiàpī
Gongtai, why do you despise Cao Cao so much?
Cao Cao is rather overstretched right now.
General, you can lead the garrison outside the city,
and me and the remainder will guard it.
If Cao Cao were to attack you,
I will lead an army to attack their rear.
If he attacks the city, General,
you can strike their rear.
Both ways will get them between ox-horns, so to speak.
In ten days, his army will run out of
provisions and would naturally fallback.
That way, you can again be on the offensive.
In one beat, you can rout the Cao army!
According to your words, Gongtai...
My lord!
It's cold. Order men to bring more cotton clothes.
Xiàpī
Hurry! In formation!
It's Chen Gong.
Sire, how could you abandon us and
your men, and leave for that plan?
If something unexpected happens, would I then still be your wife?
Form up!
My lord, please give an order.
General, you've hesitated for three days already.
Though we are trapped,
they haven't broke through.
If we hesitate, thus trapping us,
it will be too late!
General!
Lady Yán
General, you can't go!
Can Gao Shun and Chen Gong really defend Xiapi?
If there is a flaw, it will be too late for regrets!
I'm only going out to cut off Cao Cao's supply lines.
When I was at Chang'an, you abandoned me there.
Fortunately, I was later able to rendezvous with you.
Who would've knew that today,
you'd want to abandon me again!
General!
My lord, hurry! Go!
Rather than leave the city, it would
be more feasible to defend it.
My lord, I have another plan.
I heard their army have limited supplies,
so the supplies from Xudu will arrive, in some time.
General, lead elite soldiers to cut off their lines.
This is a brilliant plan. I beseech you,
General, to make a decision now.
Cao Cao has multiple tricks and has always been good at breaking supply lines.
How could he not defend his own supply lines?
I cannot act rashly now.
We will die without a place to be buried at!
General, why not go out and ask Yuan Shu?
Yuan Shu is in Huainan; if you manage to get to him, propose a marriage alliance.
Xǔ Sì
Wáng Kǎi
Correct! Yuan Shu can send troops to save us.
Unite your families to initiate a pincer attack!
Cao's army will be easy to rout.
Who?
My lord.
Xu Si? Wang Kai?
General!
Has anyone else been here?
The two left the city.
It's been several days.
Why is there no information from them?
General!
Since yesterday, Xu Si and Wang Kai have been returned.
You've recently been of an inconstant mind
and have sighed often.
You drink to remove the fears,
and there is not a word nor reply from you whenever I speak.
General, you must be depressed.
Being your wife is so painful I would not want to live!
It's not that I won't talk... it's really...
it's really that my subordinates won't let me tell you!
What?
A few days ago, Xu Si and Wang Kai
came in and said to me,
"Now Yuan Shu resides in Huainan, his power booming."
"Since we had entered talks of a
marriage alliance previously,"
"and considering our situation now,
why not ask again?"
You!
"This time, Yuan Shu will send reinforcements
our way so that we may do a pincer attack."
"Then Cao Cao will not be difficult to rout!"
Under this did I agree.
But this is too ambitious!
General, you listen to others and
never inform me of their words!
General! Xu Si and Wang Kai have returned
from Shouchun and are here!
General?
Speak now!
Yes.
Below his city, we met Yuan Shu
and presented the letter from you.
Yuan Shu, because you, sir, had killed his envoys,
declined our proposal.
Now that we have came to ask of it again,
he has blamed you, sir, for your many betrayals.
He added that if it weren't for the Cao's army besiegement,
and the crisis of Xiapi,
how could you marry your daughter off?
This time, only when you first send your daughter
will he be willing to relieve us.
But how can I send her?
Our enemies have besieged the city on all sides.
When we went,
hadn't it been for Zhang Liao and Gao Shun,
we wouldn't have broken through Liu Bei's camp!
Otherwise, we would've been
ghosts before Shouchun!
When returning, General Hao Meng broke from the rear
but was captured by
Zhang Fei and given to Cao Cao!
They know our situation,
hence we ought to be ready.
As your lowly servant sees it, unless... unless...
What!
Unless you will escort your daughter yourself,
who else can break out of the siege?
What!
How could you think of this?
I will escort her today, how about it?
Today has a ominous aura; we cannot leave now!
Tomorrow is auspicious,
and you should leave at night.
Fine!
Tomorrow, it's tomorrow!
Lǚ Bù's
daughter
Mother!
The Chancellor's orders. If anyone lets
Lü Bu escape, they shall be killed!
Charge!
Don't cry! Don't cry!
Father!
I never thought we'd fall into such a predicament!
The Administrator of Henei;
Zhang Yang sent troops east
to reinforce Lü Bu, but his subordinate, Yang Chou, killed him.
Zhang Yang may be gone, but we still need to consider Yuan Shao in the north.
Further east are Liu Biao and Zhang Xiu.
Xiapi has held out for a long time.
I could abandon the siege and return to the capital with a truce.
Gentlemen, what do you think?
Chancellor, you absolutely should not do this!
Lü Bu suffered repeated defeats
and his morale has fallen.
An army's will depends on their leader.
When their will has fallen, the army's spirit falls.
As of now, Lü Bu has not recovered;
Chen Gong cannot decide on a plan.
Sir, if you exploit this to intensify
your attack on Xiapi, Lü Bu will be captured.
I have a single plan to break through Xiapi,
able to take on 200,000 soldiers.
Perhaps you mean using
the Yi and Si rivers to inundate Xiapi?
That was my intention.
Flood it.
Report! General, Cao Cao flooded the city!
Report! General! The Southern and Northern
gates have been flooded!
Report!
General, Xiàpī has one gate—
the Eastern gate. It's dry!
All the others are flooded!
I have Red Hare, who can cross waters
as if they were fields.
What do I have to fear?
My lady, cheers.
I was damaged by wine and because of this,
I look so disheveled and haggard.
General!
Starting today,
no more wine!
Men! Pass my orders. Starting today,
anyone who drinks will be beheaded!
Yes!
Hurry! Hurry! That area needs more men!
We need to keep this area secure! Hurry, go.
Gongtai.
Gongtai!
Pass my orders! Starting today,
anyone who drinks will be beheaded!
Hóu Chéng
General!
Why didn't you go to the walls and reinforce them,
rather coming here instead?
General, our fifteen stolen horses have been recovered!
Good.
It is only because of your might that I was able to recover them!
The generals have come to congratulate me
by brewing wine. I wouldn't dare keep it for myself!
My might?
I had just banned alcohol but you gather your cohorts to drink.
Perhaps you are working against me with Cao Cao?
A ban on alcohol?
General!
Men!
Here!
Behead him now!
Yes!
General, lower the blade for a useful man!
Sòng Xiàn
Wèi Xù
Today, I will look at your faces when
I give him a hundred strokes!
General, we are facing a strong foe!
They are employing people as of now!
My lord!
You two know that we are facing a terrible foe, right?!
In that case, I will take off fifty strokes!
He'll be beaten fifty times
so that you two stop talking!
General!
Song Xian, I owe my very life to you...
Lü Bu only cares about his wife and children and treats us like weeds!
Now that enemy army has besieged us with water, we are close to being dead!
Lü Bu is not benevolent nor just.
How about we desert and go elsewhere?
Desert? That would be an act of a coward!
Better to capture Lü Bu and
surrender to Lord Cao!
Capture Lü Bu and take him to Lord Cao?
Lü Bu relies only on his mount, Red Hare!
You two can surrender the city
after capturing that traitor.
I will be the one stealing the horse for Lord Cao.
You take the horse. Wei Xu and I will pretend to chase you down.
We can capture Xiapi today! Charge!
Cao Cao, from dawn, assaulted the city until noon.
Lü Bu's army suffered countless casualties.
Cao's army withdrew not far and
Lü Bu stood resting on the city tower.
What are you... what are you doing?
What are you doing?!
We have captured Lü Bu!
Wicked traitor!
White Gate
Tower
Follow me up.
My lord, please.
Chancellor!
It's too tight!
How can one bind a tiger loosely?
I never belittled you.
Why rebel against me?
You only heed your wife's words and never ours.
How can you say that?
You punish your subordinates at will,
and yet you say that.
Lü Bu,
you are captured now.
What else do you need to say?
My lord, you seem to have become thinner recently...
Fengxian, had I not bound you,
then how could I rest assured?
Gāo Shùn
Do you have any words?
Hang him, then behead him.
Go!
Gongtai, have you been well since we last met?
When you left my service,
did you ever expect this event?
I left your service because of your crooked ways.
My 'crooked ways'?
Can you explain why you served Lü Bu alone?
Lü Bu, despite his lack of wisdom,
does not resemble you in such deceit and treachery.
You claim to be full of wisdom and slyness,
but just how did you fall into such a predicament?
All I regret is that the man didn't heed my words.
Had he listened, we would not
have been captives then.
Gongtai, that...
So then,
Gongtai, what do you think ought to happen today?
Today, there is death for me, and that is all!
Sir, naturally you would prefer death,
but what will happen to your mother, wife, and children?
I heard that those who rule with regard
to filial piety do not harm one's family.
One who practices benevolence
cannot cut off the sacrifices at one's tomb.
My family are all in your hands, and that is all.
Gongtai!
I'm captured! Punish me so I may die without any concerns.
Gongtai?
Gongtai!
I abandoned my magistrate post
to follow you, sir, and achieve great deeds.
I'd rather let myself betray the world
than let the world betray me.
Escort Gongtai's family to Xudu so that they may be looked after.
Anyone who delays will be... beheaded.
Sir, you are the guest of honor; I am a prisoner.
Why not talk to save us both?
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
My lord.
My lord, you only worry about me, that is all,
but now, I am willing to serve you, my lord.
Sire, you take the lead; I will assist you.
Why worry about the unruly world then?
Lord Xuande, how do you feel about this?
Sire, did you not see what befell
Ding Yuan and Dong Zhuo?
What...
Did you not see what befell
Ding Yuan and Dong Zhuo?
Guards.
Here!
Hang him until he is dead.
After that, cut the head off.
Liu Bei! You traitorous bastard!
You are the most untrustworthy person in the world!
Liu Bei! Did you forget how I saved you when
shooting that arrow through my halberd?!
An arrow through my halberd-
Lü Bu!
Zhāng Liáo
Styled: Wényuǎn
You bum! Death is but death! Why be afraid?
This fellow looks familar...
We met each other at Puyang City.
How could you forget?
So you remember as well...
It's only a pity!
What pity?
It's only a pity that the fire that day
wasn't big enough to roast you to death.
My lord.
My lord, don't strike him down.
What a loyal man he is.
My lord, let him live to do justice.
I have long known that Wenyuan is very loyal man.
I will plead for him with my life.
How wouldn't I know Wenyuan was just as described?
I was merely jesting, that is all.
In the 3rd year of the Jian'an era,
the winter of 198 CE,
Cao Cao finally fulfilled his wish
by wiping out the trouble within his heart, Lü Bu,
and receiving Zhang Liao's surrender.
The General of Chariots and Cavalry,
Che Zhou, governed Xu Province.
Ever since, Cao Cao's power has grown
stronger, and his prestige has amassed.