This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 10
Shooting an arrow through a halberd
Sūn Cè fought dozens of
small and large battles. Eventually,
the 6 commanderies and 81 counties within Jiāngdōng were pacified.
Meanwhile, Cáo Cāo welcomed Emperor Xiàn of Hàn
and moved the capital to Xǔchāng.
He appointed himself Grand General and Marquis of Wǔpíng,
monopolizing authority.
Detaining the Emperor, he could send decrees to warlords,
giving him an advantage.
Then, Liú Bèi had garrisoned his troops at Xúzhōu and oversees their matters.
Lǚ Bù, recently defeated,
has joined them.
Liú Bèi had him settle at Xiǎopèi.
If they were to collaborate
and invade me together,
Cáo Cāo,
Styled - Mèngdé
they will surely threaten my position.
Gentlemen, what plans do you have?
Xǔ Chǔ,
Styled - Zhòngkāng
I'll lead 50,000 elite soldiers,
lop both their heads off,
and offer them to you!
Xún Yù,
Styled- Wénruò
General Xǔ is really valiant!
Still, this is a bad idea.
We just established a new capital recently;
we cannot be rash and use force.
I have a plan.
Without using a single man, we will end up in a more favorable position.
Wénruò, please explain.
Although Liú Bèi governs Xúzhōu now,
he hasn't been appointed through an edict.
My Lord, you can petition the Emperor
to appoint Liú Bèi as Governor of Xúzhōu.
Then, just secretly send Liú Bèi a message
instructing him to kill Lǚ Bù for justice.
If he succeeds,
then Liú Bèi no longer has Lǚ Bù to scheme with,
and thus our plans will work out.
If he doesn't succeed,
then Lǚ Bù will surely retaliate and kill Liú Bèi!
This is the 'two tigers competing for food' stratagem.
Brilliant plan!
Tommorow, I will memorialize
the Son of Heaven.
Lord Xuándé!
I heard that you have received an appointment from the imperial court!
Lǚ Bù,
Styled - Fèngxiān
I, Fèngxiān, have come to pay his respects!
I wouldn't dare. I wouldn't dare. Please.
Third Brother!
You can't cause mischief! Leave!
Liú Bèi,
Styled - Xuándé
Elder Brother, you...
Yìdé, what did I do to you
that makes you want to kill me?
Cáo Cāo said you are a wicked man,
and told my Elder Brother to kill you!
Lord Xuándé, could it be true that you received that message?
Well...
Please, come with me.
Please.
Xuándé!
That traitor wants to sow discord;
he wants us to be at odds!
Have no worries, brother.
I vowed to never commit an act of injustice.
Virtuous brother!
Wénruò, your 'two tigers competing
for food' stratagem failed.
I have another plan called
'driving the tiger to devour the wolf'.
Oh, how does this one work?
My Lord, you may secretly send an envoy to Yuán Shù with a message.
You only need to tell him that
Liú Bèi petitioned the imperial court,
wanting to annex the
southern commanderies.
Once Yuán Gōnglù hears of this,
he will surely be enraged and attack Liú Bèi.
My Lord, you need to then forge an edict
ordering Liú Bèi to attack Yuán Shù.
This way, once both Yuán and Liú
start attacking each other,
Lǚ Bù will start planning sedition.
That is the plan of
'driving the tiger to devour the wolf.'
Great
Lǚ Bù on one side; Yuán Shù on the other.
This time, I will observe
how Liú Bèi reacts.
Prepare the soldiers and set a date to march against Yuán Shù.
Sūn Qián,
Styled- Gōngyòu
You need to task someone
to guard the city first.
Zhāng Fēi,
Styled - Yìdé
I'll guard!
Third Brother, you won't be
able to defend this city.
Firstly, after drinking,
you will become impetuous.
Secondly, you will abuse the officials.
When handling affairs
you won't take advice.
I can't rest assured.
Regardless, please let Yuánlóng assist you.
Chén Dēng,
Styled - Yuánlóng
Please, my Lord, rest assured.
Prepare 30,000 troops
to march for Nányáng.
We leave tomorrow.
Yes!
Liú Bèi?
He is merely just a mat-weaver
and sandal maker.
Now he dares lay claim to a major commandery as if he were one of the noble lords.
Yuán Shù,
Styled- Gōnglù
I was going to attack him,
yet he plotted against me.
How I despise him!
Jì Líng!
Jì Líng
Here!
Dispatch 100,000 troops to Xúzhōu.
Teach that bumpkin Liú Bèi...
that there is no turning back!
Yes!
First ordered to kill Lǚ Bù,
now ordered to attack Yuán Shù!
This Cáo Cāo fellow...
He let my Elder Brother be Governor of Xúzhōu,
but causes trouble for him!
Before my Elder Brother left, he instructed me to drink less wine.
He fears I will mess up matters.
Today, I hold this banquet for you fellows to take an oath.
Tonight, everyone will get
drunk just this one time.
Tomorrow, starting with myself,
everyone must quit drinking,
to guard the city well!
I have something to say first.
Tonight, you men better drink!
Cáo Bào
General Zhāng, you may drink, but you can't be so sulky.
Right!
We were told to kill Lǚ Bù, so let's kill Lǚ Bù!
We were told to fight Yuán Shù,
so let's fight Yuán Shù!
Maybe it would be better
to beat up that Cáo Āmán!
Note: It was very disrespectful for one to call others by their baby name if they were now an adult.
Then I wouldn't be sulky anymore.
And he wouldn't be leading my
Elder Brother by the nose anymore!
Come on, drink it.
General, I don't drink.
You don't drink?
I never drink alcohol —
I have a natural aversion to it.
I hope you put this at rest.
A natural aversion?
A natural aversion!
You are a man of war,
how can you not drink wine?
how can you not drink wine!
I want you to drink just this cup.
I really can't drink!
Only one cup!
That's what I'm talking about!
Come, drink!
General, I really can't drink anymore!
Rubbish! You just drunk one,
but now you refuse
to have another one.
This time, I really can't
drink anymore, I mean it!
One more! Just one more cup!
You dare disobey my orders?
The punishment is 100 strokes!
General Zhāng, before Lord Xuándé left,
what did he warn you about?
Get out of here!
You are a civil official,
so you take care of civil matters!
Leave me alone!
What are you all looking at?
What did I just say! Take him away!
Beat him!
General Zhāng?
Lord Yìdé, if you saw my son-in-law's face,
you would pardon me!
Your son-in-law?
Who is he?
He's... Lǚ Bù.
I did not mean to have you really beaten,
but you think bringing up
Lǚ Bù will scare me?
Now I want to beat you!
Beat him!
Lord Yìdé, you can't beat me! Lord Yìdé, you can't beat me!
General Zhāng!
If it weren't for your wicked son-in-law,
my Elder Brother would'nt
have had so much trouble!
Beat him! Beat him... as if you were beating Lǚ Bù... beat him!
Large-eyed brute! He's
gone too far this time!
Chén Gōng,
Styled - Gōngtái
General, we better go at
once and aid Master Cáo!
Gōngtái! What do you think?
Originally, Xiǎopèi was only a place to occupy temporarily.
Now that Liú Bèi has left for Huáinán,
you should seize Xúzhōu while you can.
If you fail to seize it, it will be
too late for regrets.
Good!
Reply to my father-in-law!
Tell him that tonight I will seize Xúzhōu and let him coordinate within!
Yes!
This time, I want to see how
that large-eyed brute will
explain his loss to Liú Bèi.
Jì Líng can retreat to the mouth of the Huáiyīn ad won't dare fight us after that.
We're locked in a stalemate.
Third Brother?
My Third Brother!
Elder Brother!
Third Brother.
Why aren't you defending Xúzhōu? Why have you come here?
Elder Brother... Xúzhōu...
What happened?
What happened to Xúzhōu?
I lost Xúzhōu!
What?
You...! You...!
Elder Brother, because you told me to follow the decree against my will,
the more I thought about it, the grumpier I got.
Without realizing it, I got drunk.
I beat up Lǚ Bù's father-in-law, Cáo Bào,
and he and Lǚ Bù
coordinated from within.
I...
Elder Brother, just punish me according to military law!
Get up!
Third Brother, what about
our sisters-in-law?
They were in the city...
What!
You! Third Brother! Third Brother!
What did you promise when you wanted to defend the city?
What did Elder Brother warn you about?
Now the city was lost and
with it our sisters-in-laws!
How is this good!
Third Brother!
As the ancient saying goes:
Brothers are like limbs;
wives are like clothes.
Torn clothes can be sewed up,
but if you have severed limbs,
can you continue on?
We three swore an oath
in the Peach Garden.
Even though we weren't
born on the same day,
Guān Yǔ,
Styled - Yúncháng
we only ask to die on the same day.
Elder Brother,
Although you lost the city
and my family today,
how could I find peace if I let my Younger Brother die early?
Besides,
Xúzhōu wasn't mine anyways.
When I got it, I wasn't glad.
Now that I have lost it, I won't be upset.
Although my family remains within the city,
Lǚ Bù won't harm them.
We can still negotiate for their return.
Virtuous brother, you made a mistake,
but is it one deserving of death?
Elder Brother!
Not long afterwards, Liú Bèi's camp
was raided by Yuán Shù,
losing most of his army.
After leaving Xūyí, Liú Bèi wandered vagrant
with no home to return to.
At this time, Chén Gōng offered a plan to Lǚ Bù:
Let Liú Bèi return and reside in Xiǎopèi to guard Lǚ Bù left and right.
That way they could make
Liú Bèi their vanguard in the future.
They would conquer Yuán Shù, then Yuán Shào,
sweeping through the realm with ease.
Lǚ Bù was worried that
Liú Bèi would be suspicious,
so he first sent someone to return Ladies Gān and Mí back to Liú Bèi.
He was very relieved.
Liú Bèi, with his brothers,
led his men back to Xúzhōu.
Xúzhōu
Elder Brother, I will escort the sisters-in-law back to Xiǎopèi!
Alright.
Help them settle down first.
Virtuous brother!
General.
I'm most grateful to you for
protecting my family.
You needn't mention it, brother!
Hey. Where's your little sibling?
Third Brother didn't want to come here,
so he took our two sisters-in-law to help them settle down in Xiǎopèi.
Lord Xuándé,
it's not that I wanted to take over Xúzhōu—
It's alright!
It's only that your little brother got drunk
and would hurt someone.
I feared he would delay important matters, so I rushed to defend the city.
Now that you've returned,
you deserve to have it back.
It's okay, it's okay.
I've long intended to give Xúzhōu to you.
Now is the right time I did it.
Better that it's you.
No.
I'm content to live in Xiǎopèi.
Well...
Fine. I'll govern the province for you now.
Please.
Gentlemen.
Sūn Cè borrowed my troops for his expedition;
and now, he already has the entirety of Jiāngdōng.
He didn't even think to repay my generosity,
but demands I must return the Jade Seal.
This is very detestable!
What plans should I make to deal with him?
My Lord, Sūn Cè has the
natural barrier of the Yángzǐ River;
his soldiers are experienced and supplied.
Due to this situation,
it is hard to find a suitable plan.
Hm? What advice do you have then?
We have to eliminate Liú Bèi first,
taking revenge for
attacking us yesterday without reason.
Once we deal with Liú Bèi,
we can attack Sūn Cè; it won't be too late.
Liú Bèi?
Jì Líng defeated him just now. How could he fight back?
Although Liú Bèi has been defeated,
he and Lǚ Bù have reconciled.
In addition, Lǚ Bù looms over Xúzhōu. He'll certainly bring trouble in the end.
My Lord, please consider these three reasons.
I will first deal with Liú Bèi.
What brilliant plans do you have?
My Lord, you may present Lǚ Bù with gifts of gold, silk, and provisions.
This way, he'll have a change of heart,
dissuading him from deploying his troops and allowing Liú Bèi to be captured.
My Lord, first get rid of Liú Bèi,
then act against Lǚ Bù afterwards.
Now this will make taking Xúzhōu a really easy task?
Not bad... if we first take Xúzhōu and then plot to take Jiāngdōng,
Then is it not that the Jade Seal will be...?
Good.
Good!
Hán Yìn.
Here.
I order you to send 200,000 carts of millet to Lǚ Bù.
Then I will write to him,
telling him not to help Liú Bèi.
Jì Líng!
Here!
I appoint you as Grand General.
Léi Bó, Chén Lán!
Here!
You two are to serve as deputy generals!
Lead 100,000 troops and march the next day towards Xiǎopèi!
Yes!
Please.
General, please go back.
Please, please, please.
General Lǚ, no need to see me out.
Please make a reply to Yuán Shù.
I am most grateful
towards him for the grain.
I won't help Liú Bèi.
Alright, I'm leaving.
Please.
Xiǎopèi only has about 5,000 troops.
How can we resist
Yuán Shù's 100,000 troops?
How is Yuán Shù so terrifying?
Just send out your little brother out to fight a few bouts with that Jì Líng!
After that we can talk!
Brother Zhāng, don't be rash.
Xiǎopèi's low supplies and few soldiers
can't resist the enemy.
I think you, my Lord, should write a plea for help to Lǚ Bù.
How is he going to agree?
Gōngyòu's advice is on point.
I'll write a letter.
Yuán Shù sent me lots of grain with a letter
telling me not to help Liú Bèi.
But Liú Bèi sent a plea for help to me
requesting reinforcements.
Gōngtái.
General, what are you going to do?
Liú Bèi is of no threat whilst in Xiǎopèi.
But if...
if Yuán Shù overcomes Liú Bèi
and comes to an understanding
with the other lords,
we won't be able to ensure the safety of Xúzhōu.
What you're worried about is true.
But if you dispatch troops to save Liú Bèi,
you can't account for it before Yuán Shù.
What a dilemma!
I have an idea!
I have a plan to keep both of them from complaining about me.
Welcome Xuándé!
Please!
I wouldn't dare turn down your invitation!
Please.
Good.
Please?
Today, I've asked you, sir, to come here
to relieve the danger
of you being besieged.
When you achieve your ambitions some day,
please remember me.
Well let's —
General Jì Líng has arrived!
Jì Líng?
General, wha...
Xuándé, don't be alarmed.
I've invited both of you
here for a discussion.
Don't be suspicious, just be calm.
General Lǚ has promised
not to help Liú Bèi.
Why did he dispatch his troops?
Isn't his the intention to help Liú—
General, could it be that
you want to kill me?
Not at all!
Is it that you want to kill Liú Bèi?
Then... what's going on?
Liú Bèi is like a brother to me.
Now you are besieging him, so I have come to the rescue.
Then you'd better kill me!
I've never been a man of war,
but I've always been a mediator.
I want to meditate peace between you two.
Excuse me, General, but may I ask how?
I have a way—it will
be settled by Heaven!
You'll soon understand!
Come, take a seat!
General Lǚ, what are you intending to do?
Come, come, come!
Let me introduce you two to each other.
I've opposed violence for my entire life,
but the entire world thinks I enjoy fighting!
This is a really big misunderstanding.
Today, I have prepared a banquet for you.
This is a good banquet,
and it's definitely not a Hóngmén banquet!
Note: A Hóngmén banquet is a banquet that's really an assassination.
I want to mediate peace between the Liú and Yuán clans.
Look at me in the eyes,
and please stop this war for my sake!
You two each withdraw your troops and go home.
Well?
That's nonsense!
I received my Lord's order to raise 100,000 well-seasoned soldiers
to capture Liú Bèi!
You sure speak big for a dirty lout!
You have 100,000 troops. So what?
Killing you is child's play!
You dare to threaten my Elder Brother?
Third Brother...
sheathe your sword.
Let's see what General Lǚ has to say first.
After that, there will be time
to go back and fight.
I invited you two to
come here to reconcile!
How could I let you fight?
Reconcile?
It's easier said than done!
Jì Líng, you're just an insolent fool!
Do you really think I'm afraid of you?
You dare go out to compete
with me for 300 bouts?
You bet!
Let's go!
Bring my halberd!
I told you two not to fight!
Now accept Heaven's will!
Good!
The gate is 150 paces away from us:
If I shoot my arrow through the center of the halberd-head,
you both shall withdraw your troops!
If I miss...
You may return to your camps and prepare to kill each other.
Whoever disobeys, I'll send my troops to the other party,
and fight to the death with the offender!
Are you going to shoot...?
The center branch of the halberd-head!
Alright. I'll comply with you.
I only hope you won't break your word.
Bring the bow!
It is Heaven's will!
Heaven bids you to withdraw troops!
Come!
Serve wine!
It's reconciling wine! Cheers!
General, I dare not disobey your words,
but if I were to withdraw,
will My Lord believe this event?
How hard is that? I'll just write a letter to him;
you just simply withdraw.
I, Liú Bèi, am most grateful to you, General.
Without me, you'd be in danger!
You fool!
I can't believe you fell for Lǚ Bù's trap!
Lǚ Bù received lots of grain from me.
Instead, this farce of a child
was made to suck up to Liú Bèi!
I'll personally lead a grand army to conquer Liú Bèi and Lǚ Bù!
My Lord, don't!
That Lǚ Bù is one of the
most valiant among men;
he also has the domain of Xúzhōu!
If Lǚ Bù allies with
Liú Bèi from end to end,
it'll be hard to beat them both!
But we can't let them off easily!
My Lord!
I have an idea.
Speak!
The other day, you, sir,
sent me some provisions.
Now today, you came
to give me betrothal gifts.
I wonder why?
General, my Lord has heard that you have a daughter,
and that she is of a similar age to his own son.
My Lord has admired you for a long time and would like a to propose a marriage.
He wants to form a lifelong alliance,
and has sent me here to be the matchmaker.
What do you think about it?
Sir, please go to the guest room to rest.
Let me counsel with my advisers — then we'll talk.
Thank you, General.
Hán Yìn takes his leave.
You must be really bold.
Do you think we're all fools in Xúzhōu?
I wouldn't dare!
Who proposed this lousy trick to Your Lord?
By allying Yuán Shù with Fèngxiān via marriage,
the real purpose is nothing more than to take Liú Xuándé's head, is it?
Gōngtái-
How could a simple trick
ever get past you, Gōngtái?
I ask you keep it secret, Gōngtái.
Xuándé is an ambitious
hero of this generation,
But his feathers have not fully spread yet.
Gōngtái, do you want
to grow a tiger at Xiǎopèi?
Don't worry, sir. I won't let it leak out.
I'm only afraid that delaying action
will make the scheme obvious to others.
Gōngtái whom are
you referring to by 'others'?
What's that for? I implore you,
Gōngtái, do tell me.
I'll go to Fèngxiān
and persuade him to wed his daughter at once. How about it?
If this is so, then Lord Yuán will be most grateful to your foresight and virtue!
You just wait for good news.
I've heard that you have already agreed to join your family with the Yuán's.
Oh? You've heard about it?
What do you think?
It's good!
But I wonder, when is the big day?
The date is yet to be discussed.
Back then, during the time between the betrothal and wedding,
there are set rules of the duration.
What rules?
For the Son of Heaven, a year. For the noble lords, half a year.
For ministers, one season, and for commoners, a month.
Yuán Shù has the god-given Jade Seal in his possession...
Sooner or later, he'll declare himself Emperor.
Hey! Then do we follow the rules for the Son of Heaven?
That won't do.
Then do we follow the rules for the warlords?
Then... do we follow the rules for the ministers?
That won't do either.
Don't tell me... that we have to follow the rules for the commoners?
Not at all!
Gōngtái, what are you implying?
Many warlords are currently contending for hegemony.
If you unite with Yuán Shù by marriage,
are there not any people that are jealous of you?
If we select an auspicious day too far off,
then they will take advantage of our wait and lay an ambush on the wedding day.
How would that be good?
So, our plan for the present is that,
although you should've declined but have already consented,
you ought to surprise those unaware warlords
and send your daughter to Shòuchūn.
You should first rent her a house there,
then select an auspicious day for the wedding.
This way, you can be safe with no risk at all.
Gōngtái, you're absolutely right.
I'll make the preparations right away!