This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 19
Reunion in an Old City
Sister-in-law, please board the ship!
Please.
Crossing the Yellow River is crossing into Héběi's borders.
I will be able to see my elder brother.
Who couldn't but only reflect in longing.
Bidding farewell to Xǔchāng,
hanging my seal and locking that gold.
Cutting down the warriors of the pass, in order to look for my elder brother.
To see my elder brother's face, I, Guān Yúnchǎng, would die for it a myriad times without regrets!
Yúnchǎng, slow down!
Sūn Qián
Styled: Gōngyòu
General Guān!
Gōngyòu!
General!
General Guān!
Gōngyòu!
Gōngyòu! Where were you after we were defeated?
I wandered around Rǔnán!
Gōngyòu!
General!
Ever since I fled from Xú Province, I wandered Rǔnán.
I luckily met Liú Pì, who gave me shelter.
He sent to Héběi to ally with Yuán Shào,
and invite Xuándé together to defeat Cáo (Cāo).
But Yuán Shào's strategists resent each other and fight for influence.
Yuán Shào himself is suspicious and indecisive.
The Imperial Uncle and I decided to find a way to escape.
Now he has already left to Rǔnán.
I was afraid you would be harmed by Yuán Shào upon arrival.
Thus, I was sent to meet you.
Tis fortunate I met you.
General Guān, you can hurry to
Rǔnán to meet with our lord.
The road has been long and arduous, to think it has come to this.
Mistresses, is everything alright?
Sisters-in-law, don't be sad.
The imperial uncle is at Rǔnán.
In a few days, you can meet him again.
If you, sir, had not escorted us through the passes,
the two of us would never see the imperial uncle ever again.
Guān Yǔ, halt!
Who are they?!
Stop Guan Yu!
Mister Sūn.
Guard the chariot. I will deal with this myself.
Wait for me, I will be back.
Go!
Xiàhóu Dūn
Styled: Yuánràng
If you come for me, it would be breaking the Chancellor's promsie.
The Chancellor did not send out a written word,
yet you trespass
and kill our warriors along the way.
This cannot be tolerated!
Today, I'm here to capture you!
Bring you back to the Chancellor in chains!
The Chancellor made it clear that going forward, no matter what happens or who dies,
I answer to no one!
Yet those gate-guards were arbitrary
and wanted me stopped despite my reasoning.
I had to resort to violence in order to pass.
Had it been any other officer, there'd be no quarrel.
But Qín Qí was my subordinate, and my friend Cài Yáng's nephew.
How can I back down?!
General, you cannot fight with Yúnchǎng!
The Chancellor admires General Guān's virtue, so he was stopped by the gate-passes,
so he commanded me to relay the order to everyone.
Guān Yǔ killed those gate-officers to trespass!
Does the Chancellor know that?!
Not yet...
If so, I will arrest Guān Yǔ and take him back to the Chancellor for questioning!
Do not challenge me, knave!
Today, we will decide who is the champion!
Die!
General, stop!
But I received the Chancellor's order to arrest Guān Yǔ!
No, the Chancellor was worried and had me to pass this letter!
He ordered that the passes were not to hinder General Guān!
Does the Chancellor know of the killings?
Not yet!
Then if he does not...
We cannot let him go!
Get him!
Sir, now you have disobeyed the Chancellor's orders multiple times.
Is it because I killed Qín Qí?
Are you are here to resolve this grievance?
And what of it!?
If so, I will not hesitate killing
the Chancellor's trusted officer.
It will be thus.
Yúnchǎng, stop this!
By the Chancellor's orders! He heard of Yúnchǎng's battles, and feared the passes would still halt him,
Zhāng Liáo
Styled: Wényuǎn
so he sent me throughout the gate-passes to grant him passage!
Qín Qí is Cài Yáng's nephew, he entrusted him to me.
Now that Guān Yǔ killed him, how could I ever rest?
General Cài will have to resolve it himself,
but by the Chancellor's generosity, Yúnchǎng has passage. We cannot disobey that order!
Someday, we shall meet again on the battlefield!
Yúnchǎng, where are you going now?
I don't know where my elder brother is.
If you don't know where Xuándé is,
would you like to join the Chancellor again?
How would that make sense?
Wényuǎn,
Along the way, I committed a many misdeeds.
When you go back, please tell the Chancellor I ask for his forgiveness.
Yúnchǎng.
Yúnchǎng!
Attack!
Stop!
Leave your horses and weapons behind!
Who are you wretches to have the gall to stop me!
How amusing! Now leave your horses!
So, just a bunch of petty horse-thieves.
Shut up! Men, kill him!
Die!
Dismount! Leave your weapons behind!
(Péi) Yuánshào, stop!
We are making a huge mistake!
What are you-
Zhōu Cāng pays his respects to General Guān!
General Guān!
Where are you going?
This man had reported that there was someone riding a fast steed.
We stayed over at his family's house and he invited us to steal such a steed.
We never knew it was yours...
The hero, Guān Yúnchǎng!
We are fortunate to meet with you!
General Guān!
We have never met before, how did you know of me?
Back then general, the Imperial Uncle,
and Zhāng Yìdé beat that county inspector at Ānxǐ.
The court distributed wanted posters everywhere!
Ever since, we have never forgotten your integrity!
I have always been eager to see you, and here we are!
Gentlemen, you may all stand up.
Thank you, General Guān!
Not you!
I have travelled a thousand lǐ, escorting my
sisters-in-laws to find my elder brother,
all on this horse!
Who do you think you are, having the gall to plot against me!
Halt!
For his family's sake, spare his life.
Get out!
Come back!
Return to where you belong!
Do not fool around with petty crime henceforth.
Take care of your family.
Get out!
Thank you, General!
General!
I have long admired your virtue!
Zhōu Cāng
Now that I am blessed to see you, my life has purpose!
I am willing to follow you everywhere!
I will lead your carriage and your horse willingly, and I am content with death!
General!
Sir, please rise.
General Guān, please mount your horse!
'Mount your horse'?
Hurry up! Hurry up!
Sir, may I ask what is the land behind you?
Ten lǐ before me is Gǔchéng.
Hasten our march! We will rest once we arrive at Gǔchéng!
Are you officials, if I may ask?
Is there an issue?
A few days ago, there was a mighty man descending from the mountains.
He entered the city, asking for food.
The county magistrate refused.
That man got so furious he seized the seal.
He seized the city and exiled the magistrate.
That man now recruits soldiers and horses and has been storing provisions in the city.
He now has three to five thousand soldiers, no one dares to fight him.
Sir, do you know this man's name?
It is Zhāng Fēi.
Zhāng Fēi?
Sisters-in-law!
We found Yìdé!
Where is he?
He is ahead in Gǔchéng!
Go!
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
What weapon you want?
Anything will do, but preferably something like the Green Dragon-Crescent Blade,
just like what General Guān uses.
Forgive me, sir.
I'm being forgetful.
Yesterday they did remind me,
only sir can refer to General Guān.
No one else can talk about him.
How could I forget.
I- Please forgive me.
Yide?
Gōngyòu!
It is Yìdé! Yìdé!
Mr. Sūn!
Mr. Sūn, any news of my Elder Brother?
Of our Imperial Uncle, we can discuss later in detail
Now Yúnchǎng is escorting your
two sisters-in-law to Gǔchéng!
Yìdé, are you not happy to welcome him?
What?
Give me my weapon!
Yìdé!
Yìdé?
It's Yìdé that's picking us up!
Sisters-in-law!
My third brother is coming to welcome us!
Sisters-in-law! Yìdé is here!
Third Brother!
Traitor, face my spear!
Third Brother,
I'm Guān Yǔ!
I know you are Guān Yǔ, but
today, it is Guān Yǔ that will die!
Third Brother!
Have you forgotten our Oath of the Peach Garden?
You have have no shame! How dare you meet with me face to face?!
How have I no shame?!
You betrayed my elder brother, you surrendered to Cáo Cāo,
and even accepted a marquis title,
and now you've come to deceive me!
We'll fight to the death!
Third Brother, it's complicated. It's hard to explain right now.
You can ask our sisters-in-law here yourself!
Brother-in-law.
Why do you do this, brother-in-law?
Wait there sisters-in-law. I will kill this traitor first.
Then I shall escort you back in the city.
Third brother-in-law! He didn't know where you and Imperial Uncle were,
he had to reside at Cáo's camp.
But now that imperial uncle is in Runan,
he escorted us all the way over all obstacles.
Don't blame him, Third brother-in-law.
Don't be fooled
A loyal man would rather die than surrender!
What kind of man would serve two?!
Brother
Why do you accuse me so?
Yìdé!
Yúnchǎng came back for you.
Now you lie to me too?!
How can he come for me?
He clearly came to capture me.
If I were to capture you, I would bring an army.
What is that, if not an army?!
Do you still dare to argue?
Watch me.
I will show you.
Bring the drum.
Third Brother!
-Second Brother!
-Third brother!
Brother!
My Brother!
Second Brother
My good brother!
I missed you, my Brother!
Third Brother
Brother!
General Guān is still as strong as ever.
No need, no need.
Please.
Everyday, General Zhāng misses the imperial uncle and you.
He often wakes up screaming your names.
You met today and yet he almost killed you!
That is no lie.
Usually General Zhāng doesn't allow us to speak of General Guān.
If we do, general would get violently angry.
Yìdé is very clear-cut, he detests evil and unjust.
Admirable!
If you had gone on each other's throats today, would Second Brother-in-Law still say so?
Lady Mí
Sisters-in-Law! Second-Brother!
Look who's here!
Mr. Mi.
Mí Zhú
Styled: Zi Zhòng
My brother.
Today we've reunited, the one only missing is Elder Brother.
Tomorrow, I will go to look for him in Runan.
When we came here, we heard my lord, seeing Liu Pì and Gōng Dū were low on manpower,
has gone to negotiate with Yuán Shào.
-Zhou Cang
-Yes, sir.
How many serve under Pei Yuanshao?
About four or five hundred.
I will take a shortcut to look for Elder Brother.
You go gather some men in Mount Wòniú, and return through the main road.
Roger.
This old city is our safe haven. We can't abandon it.
I will look for Elder Brother with Mr. Sun.
Brother, you stay here and guard the city.
Yes.
Do not worry, brother.
Come back as soon as possible.
Over there is Hebei.
Tread lightly, general.
Only take rest for a short while,
wait for me to meet with Imperial Uncle.
Gongyou, please be quick.
Understood.
My lord.
My Lord, if you are so eager to see Yúnchǎng,
why won't you see Yuán Shào tomorrow?
Tell him you will go to Jīng-Province to
persuade Liú Biǎo in allying against Cáo Cāo,
Yuán Shào agreed. My lord, you can seize this opportunity to escape.
Its a good plan, but I wonder if
you, Lord Jiǎn, can accompany me.
My Lord, no need to be worried!
I, Jiǎn Yōng, will find a way to escape.
Another prolonged and painful night.
Liú Jǐngshēng has the nine commanderies of the Jīng-Province. We can join together against Cáo Cāo.
I already sent someone for such purpose.
That useless Liú Biǎo refused alliance!
We share the same family ties.
If I were sent, I would have
no trouble convincing him.
If Liú Biǎo and I unite together...
But he did defeat Liú Pì several times...
Lord Xuándé, you can go negotiate with him.
If so, I shall go immediately.
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
I heard recently that Yúnchǎng has left Cáo Cāo and intends to come to Héběi.
I will kill him, to avenge Yán Liáng and Wén Chǒu!
Sire once said you wanted Yúncháng by your side, so I sent him a letter. Why do you want to kill him?
Besides, Yán Liáng and Wén Chǒu are but two deers, while Yúncháng is a tiger.
Two deers for a tiger, what is there to hate?
I'm speaking in jest. In reality, I do like Yúncháng.
Sir Xuande can call someone to get him here immediately.
Sire, I, Liu Bei shall have
Sun Qian to call Yúncháng back.
-Farewell.
-Good.
Once that man leaves, he'll never return.
Guō Tú
Styled: Gōngzé
General Guān!
General Guān, my father asked me to bring water.
General, you stood here for too long!
Please put on this robe!
General, look!
It's him! It's him! It's my elder brother!
Second Brother!
Elder Brother!
-Elder Brother
-Second Brother!
-Brother
-My Brother!
Brother.
Second Brother.
Elder Brother, we've been apart far too long.
Píng'er, come! Come meet with your uncle.
Guān Píng
Who is he?
Elder brother, this is my son Guān Píng.
I adopted him in Guanding village.
This one greet you, my Uncle.
Uncle.
Good.
General Guan!
General Guan! Zhou Cang greets you!
You were contact Pei Yuanshao. Why are you here?
General, before I reached Mount Woniu,
There was a warrior on horseback, he engaged Pei Yuanshao.
He killed Pei Yuanshao in an instant, and took over the mountain.
When I came to call,
only these few dared to come out.
The rest were too afraid to leave.
I challenged that warrior,
but lost to him, injured by his spear three times.
Who is this man? What does he look like
He is mighty, but I don't know his name.
So, there's someone this powerful.
Lead the way, I will meet with him.
Yes, sir!
Come out, you brigand! Today will be your last!
General, that's him!
Are you sir Zǐlóng?
Sir magister!
It is Zilong!
-Zilong!
-Magister!
Zhào Yún
Styled: Zǐlóng
Zilong, why are you here?
Ever since I bid magister farewell,
Gongsun Zan became callous,
and led everyone go down with him.
Yuán Shào called on me many times,
but I refused to serve him.
Only when I heard you were at Yuán Shào's side,
had I want to come, but I didn't want to meet with Yuán Shào.
That's why I was scattered with the wind.
Yet when I was passing by,
that Pei Yuanshao came down to rob my horse, I killed him in self-defense, and took refuge.
I am overjoyed to see the magister again!
To meet again today, it's truly a miracle!
I had wandered across
all directions, looking for a worthy lord.
But none were as worthy as you, magister. To meet again, is truly a great honor.
Through thick and thin,
I shall follow you to the end.
Yide has come to welcome us.
Days have been like years! Today, we will reunite!
Third Brother!
Elder Brother!
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Chūnfēngdéyì zhīyīn,
A chance encounter makes us friends forever.
táohuā yě hánxiào yìng jì tái.
Peach blossoms bloom before the altar.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Bǎoguó ān bāng zhì kāngkǎi,
Defend the country and be magnanimous to the people,
jiàngōng lìyè zhǎnxióng cái.
strengthen the country through our talents and deeds.
Zhǎnxióng cái
Our talents and deeds.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Zhōng gān yì dǎn,
Remain loyal and always brave,
huànnàn xiāng suí shì bù fēnkāi.
never parting despite hardships and suffering.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Shēngsǐ bù gǎi,
Life or death, never give up,
tiāndì rì yuè zhuàng wǒ qínghuái.
Heaven and Earth, let my resolve
be as powerful as Sun and Moon.