This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 25
Liu Bei Seeks the Virtuous
Please.
Sir, why have you come?
I was passing through when a child led me to visit your esteemed presence.
I feel honored.
Sīmǎ Huī
Styled: Décāo)
Sire, you shouldn't keep secrets.
You're here today in order to escape.
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
To be honest with you, Liu Biao had me attend a meeting in Xiāngyáng —
— but Cai Mao tried to harm me, so I fled them and came here.
I gathered that from your facial expression.
I have heard of your great reputation, sir.
Why has it to this day you have no foundations of your own?
Fate are ever-changing. That is why I am here.
Wrong.
Wrong!
The reason why you haven't yet accomplished your great undertaking —
— is because there are no virtuous sage men around to assist you.
I may not be able  —
But with me are ministers Sūn Qián, Mí Zhú, and
Jiǎn Yōng, and generals Yúncháng, Yìdé, and Zǐlóng.
All loyal and supportive,
how could you not count them as sage men?
Sir, why are you laughing?
Guan Yu, Zhang Fei, Zhao Yun are warriors rivaling of ten-thousand men.
But its pitiable that they aren't made more use of.
Sun Qian, Jian Yong,
and Mi Zhu are inexpert literati —
— Not men of grand strategies and statesmanship!
Teacher, your words are most correct.
I have searched for such able men before —
— but haven't had the chance to meet a man of such talent.
Xuande, is it not like how Confucius once said:
"Within a township of ten families,
you will find one who is venerable and virtuous."
Why claim there are no men of talent?
Forgive my ignorance on this matter. I'd like to ask your advice.
The great heroes and prodigies of today are already here!
Sir Xuande must go inquire them.
I wish to know who these prodigies are.
Come.
Please.
'Sleeping Dragon' and 'Fledgling Phoenix'
With either by your side, peace can be brought.
Please explain sir, who are these
Sleeping Dragon andFledgling Phoenix?
Well...
Good, good.
It's getting late now.
General, feel free to stay overnight.
There will be time to talk again tomorrow.
Sir...
Please, please.
The reason why you haven't yet accomplished your great undertaking —
— is because there are no virtuous sage men around to assist you.
Sleeping Dragon and Fledgling Phoenix...
With even one by your side, peace can be brought.
Zhao Yun unsuccessfully searched for Liu Bei outside Xiāngyáng.
When he saw water prints from the east of the Tán-Creek to the west —
— he figured Liu Bei came back to Xinye, and returned there.
However, even after he returned to Xinye, he couldn't find Liu Bei.
Zhao Yun felt very worried  —
— so he searched the entire western bank of the Tán-Creek.
At Shuijing Mountain, he met Liu Bei, and the two headed back for Xinye.
Along the way, they found a man seeking to serve them.
...there is a wise man on the mountain, hoping to find a lord.
The lord seeks wise advisors,
but still he has no clue!
"The lord seeks wise advisers..."
"... But still he has no clue."
Zilong, could that man be either
Sleeping Dragon or Fledging Phoenix?
Come with me.
Yes, sir.
May I ask where you came from?
From all around the mountains!
May I ask for your name?
I am from Yǐngshàng.
Of the family Shàn, by the name of Fú
I heard you are recruiting men of talent for your cause.
Because you listened to my melody,
you have earned my respect.
I thank you, sir, for not refusing me.
You have my gratitude.
I wouldn't dare!
Sir, let us discuss this at a hut.
Shàn Fú
(AKA. Xú Shù
Styled, Yuánzhí)
That horse must be 'Dilu'!
Although this horse can run a 1,000 li,
it will bring misfortune to its rider.
My lord, do not ride it.
This horse galloped across the Tán-Creek!
It saved me!
How can it bring misfotune?
This horse will curse its rider.
I have a way to avoid this problem.
Do speak.
Sire, if you have someone in mind you detest,
you should give this horse to them.
Let the curse take effect, and then reclaim it.
No more problems!
I happened to hear your melody,
and thought it was out of the ordinary.
Looking at you, you seemed to be a man of talent.
I hoped you would help me achieve my ambitions.
Yet instead of showing me the way,
you talk of causing petty harm.
Sir, you may need to find another lord.
I have long heard of your benevolent reputation.
Today I'm shown it was not empty talk!
I, Shan Fu, am willing to follow you to the end!
How would I call myself benevolent!
I only wish to seek your advice.
My lord, don't be too humble.
The people of Xinye have sung this.
"Xinye's Lord, Uncle Liu,
blessed is the land, where he would stand."
Because of your benevolence,
the people placed great faith in you.
I want to appoint you as our Army-Strategist,
for you to train them to achieve great things.
My lord!
Since the 5th year of the Jian'an era.
I raised a righteous army to destroy each menace of the world!
I defeated Yuan Shao and retook four provinces!
I have pacified the Wuhuan-tribes and appeased Liaodong!
Now, with the north pacified, I will again march my army!
Note: Jīng-Xiāng (荆襄) aka. Jing-Province and Xiangyang.
I will first take the lands of Jīng-Xiāng,
then conquer Eastern Wú!
Liu Bei had tried earlier to take the capital of Xǔ (Xǔchāng).
We must kill him while his wings have
not developed to eliminate a future problem!
Generals, heed my orders!
Cáo Rén.
Here!
Lǐ Diǎn.
Here.
Lü Kuàng.
Here!
Lü Xiáng.
The four of you will advance!
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Lead 30,000 troops to garrison at
Fánchéng, and scout Liu Biao's strength.
Yes sir!
Disperse.
We should speed up preparations to garrison Fancheng.
General Cao.
Liu Bei has garrisoned at Xinye,
building up his armies and supplies.
This suggests he will take Xǔdū.
He is getting too bold.
We must eliminate him early.
Lü Kuàng
Lü Xiáng
Since we brothers joined the Chancellor, we haven't had great achievements —
— yet still receive the Chancellor's patronage.
Now that we're going to Fancheng, we ask of 5,000 elite soldiers —
—  to seize Liu Bei's head and
gift it to the Chancellor.
Good! I will let you two
lead the elite troops towards Xinye.
Cáo Rén
Styled: Zǐxiào
Liu Bei will be first to fall!
Yes!
Elder Brother! Strategist!
Generals.
How could that Lü Kuang
and Lü Xiang be a match against us?
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Zilong and I cut them down in two rounds!
Great! You may sit.
Thank you, Elder Brother!
Sir, your plan was ingenious!
Cao Cao wants Lü Kuang and
Lü Xiang to intrude upon our Xinye —
— but with only a single plan from our Strategist,
he has now lost two of his warrior-generals!
However, how can Cao Cao be willing to concede at this point?
Xinye has just a few soldiers.
How can we counter the enemy?
No need to worry, my lord-
Report! A large army led by Cao Ren and
Li Dian is coming towards Xinye!
Because we defeated Lü Kuang and Lü Xiang —
— a furious Cao Ren led his entire army over here.
Fancheng must be empty then!
We must use this chance to take it over!
Guan Yu.
Here.
Zhang Fei.
Here!
Both of you will lead thousand soldiers to meet the enemy at Fancheng.
Two generals just need to follow my plan.
Yes, sir!
Sir, with their departure,
how can we defend ourselves?
We will guard Xinye.
Zhao Yun.
Here.
Zilong, you will accompany us and await our command.
Yes!
Cáo Rén
Styled: Zǐxiào
Great!
Li Dian is defeated! Signal the men to finish him off!
Attack!
Heed my orders!
Change formation!
Hurry!
Go!
Wait!
Sir, why are you halting our attack?
My lord, see them?
That is the Golden Locks of Eight Gates Formation.
Zilong rushed into it!
Die!
Zilong!
How are you, Zilong?
When I rushed into their formation, a cloud of smoke rose.
I couldn't find that Li Dian!
The Cao army changed formation, encasing me in it!
With much effort, I broke out,
and my other troops didn't make it.
By the look of it, that formation is hard to break through.
The Golden Locks of Eight Gates Formation has eight regiments and gates.
They are tightly linked together without even a gap.
If our troops rushed into them,
you will fight a different soldier each time.
The formation has the soldiers intersect with each other.
The formation never stops turning.
They can hit you, but you cannot hit them back.
If a soldier joins them, it will grow the cycle.
No matter how brave your soldiers are,
they'll eventually lose.
That is the strength of this formation.
In that case, is there no plan that can defeat it?
Although they are grouped neatly —
— they lack a Supreme Ultimate,
their center has no commander.
General, enter through the Southeast corner.
If you attack the Western Gate, they will rout.
Zilong.
Do as he says.
Have your men maintain their flanks.
Yes sir!
Go!
Pass the order!
We have broken through them!
Pursue them!
Sir, you are extraordinary!
My lord, you flatter me!
You should order our troops not to
pursue them, but to remain at camp.
Okay!
How could he break through our formation?
We will raid Liu Bei's camp tonight
while he's complacent from victory.
We will succeed!
General Cao.
There must be sage men helping Liu Bei now.
Now that our army is at this point,
we must defend Fancheng.
We will fall back if we don't succeed tonight.
Don't! Liu Bei must have prepared for that!
Armies aren't run by paranoia!
Advance.
Death!
We've been outmaneuvered!
Retreat!
Hurry, hurry!
Cross the river!
Find a ferry!
Cao Ren, halt! I've been waiting for you!
Run!
Open the gates! Cao Ren's army has returned!
Cao Ren's army has returned! Open the gates!
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
Cao Ren, you boor! We already captured Fancheng!
Run! Run!
Come, come! Let us drink!
Strategist, thank you! Thank you, elder brother!
Please, drink!
Drink!
Ever since this gentleman has joined us,
we've been victorious.
I always knew if I were to achieve my undertaking —
— I would have to have sage, talented men like him by my side.
Correct, correct, correct!
Sir, you have my gratitude.
My lord, my lord!
My lord, you flatter me!
My lord, you graced me with your patronage.
I am merely repaying that.
I dare not receive such respect!
With this gentleman's assistance, we will persevere! Soon our great cause can be realized!
Another round!
Come, come, come!
We wish Your Lordship great fortune!
Chancellor!
Chancellor, we lost Fancheng!
You may punish us!
Your pride led you to ignore warnings.
Thus you were defeated!
However, because of your past achievements, I shall spare you.
We thank you for your mercy!
Yet not too long ago, Liu Bei was handily defeated at Rǔnán under my watch.
Now you get routed whenever you attack Xinye.
Even the Golden Locks
of Eight Gates Formation has failed.
Liu Bei must have received a great talent to his ranks, planning his next maneuvers.
Chancellor is correct.
I have heard that Liu Bei has gained a judicious advisor called Shan Fu.
He is the one who broke our formation.
Shan Fu? What is he like?
Chéng Yù
Styled, Zhòngdé
Chancellor, Shan Fu is a fake name.
He is actually a man from Yingshang,
of the family Xú, by the name of Shù, styled Yuánzhí.
When he was young, he practiced swordsmanship
He is a forthright personality, and likes to fight against injustice.
Near the end of the Zhōngpíng-calendar, he killed a corrupt official to avenge a friend.
Note: Zhōngpíng(中平) = 184-189 CE, last calendar era of Emperor Líng of Hàn
However, he had no choice but to go into hiding.
When he was arrested,
he was asked for his name, but did not reply.
The officials tied him to a cart
and drummed in the streets to learn about his name.
However, because of his heroic deeds, no one identified him.
The office could only put him in jail.
Later however, there was 'someone' who freed him
Xu Shu then changed his name,
and has since he devoted himself to learning.
He visited famous teachers and
became enriched with knowledge.
He often meets with people like Sima Hui about the current state of the realm.
How does Xu Shu's talent compare to yours?
Ten times as much.
What a pity! What a pity!
Another talented man falls under Liu Bei's palms.
Now that his wings are fully developed, how can I not be concerned?
Although Xu Shu serves under Liu Bei —
— if you want him under your command, it can be done.
What are you suggesting, sir?
Xu Shu is a filial man.
When he lost his father, only his mother stayed in the household.
When his brother Xu Kang passed away, their mother had no one to support her.
Chancellor, you should invite her over to Xudu  —
— and have her summon her son with a message.
Xu Shu will certainly come!
Good.
Send someone to Yingchuan right away,
and bring Xu Shu's mother here.
Mother of Xu Shu
Why did you make me come to Xudu?
Ma'am.
I heard that your son, Xu Yuanzhi, is a prodigy of our time.
However, he is assisting that rebel Liu Bei
in undermining the Imperial Court from Xinye.
Is it not pitiful that such a
beautiful jade fell into the mud?
I asked you to come here in order for you to return him back to Xudu.
I can petition the Emperor to grant you a hefty reward.
Ma'am, please.
What kind of man is Liu Bei?
A lesser man from Zhuo Commandery who claims to be the Emperor's uncle.
Treacherous to the core.
As they say; A crook in gentleman's clothing.
Why are you lying to me?
I know that Liu Xuande is a descendant of the Prince Jìng of Zhōngshān —
— and of Emperor Jǐng of Hàn's lineage.
He treats the virtuous with the utmost respect and has built up a righteous reputation.
He is a hero of this age!
My son is blessed to have such sagacious lord to serve.
You are the Chancellor of the Hàn in name only, because you are its traitor!
You lie about Liu Xuande being a rebel to have my son turn away from the light into darkness!
Have you no shame?!
Out with her!
Traitor!
Behead her!
Hypocrite!
No! Stop the execution!
Xu Shu's mother has angered you to have herself executed —
— for if you kill her, it will only worsen your reputation and instead make her a martyr.
By killing her, Xu Shu will either commit suicide or he will devote himself to Liu Bei to avenge her.
Better to let her live, so that Xu Shu would be split between two.
Even if he stays with Liu Bei, he won't be as dedicated.
Let Xu Shu's mother remain here, for I have yet another plan to make Xu Shu come.
True. I shall send Xu Shu's mother somewhere else.
Ma'am!
Ma'am, how have you been lately?
Mister Cheng, you brought me something again.
After you.
When Yuanzhi and I studied together, we were like brothers.
Thus ma'am, you are like a mother to me.
However, now that Yuanzhi is not here for you,
I will be for you in his stead.
Mister Cheng, you are a kind man.
Yet, you have submitted to Cao Cao. How-
Ma'am, you needn't say more.
Fates are unkind, it is how it is.
When I get the chance, I will send you back home.
Good, good!
Ma'am.
I have something to do, so I'm afraid I cannot stay.
Farewell.
Take care.
Ma'am,
Mister Cheng left you another letter.
Cheng Yu really is a scholarly gentleman.
I already have his letter, so I should reply.
Fetch me the pen and inkstone.
Yes.
My lord, someone from Xudu is here.
He was asking where Shan Fu was, he had something to tell him.
Enter.
I am a servant of Ma'am Xu!
I have here a letter by her own hand!
Leave us.
Sir, what is it that has you worried?
My lord, I...
Sir, say what it is. Don't be so sad.
My lord,
My real name is Xú Shù, styled Yuánzhí, from Yingchuan.
When I went into hiding,
I changed my name to Shan Fu.
I heard that Liu Jingsheng was
seeking advisers, so I visited him.
In discussing matters, I came to learn that he was useless.
Therefore, I left a letter of resignation.
Overnight, I stayed with Master Sima Water-Mirror.
Master criticized me for not recognizing
a sagacious lord, so he recommended you to me.
I was lucky to have your favor and use of my talents.
But for this, now Cao Cao targets me.
My lord, my mother is now imprisoned in Xudu, under Cao Cao's torment.
My mother's letter tells thus. I have no choice!
It isn't that I do not wish to serve you —
— but my mother suffers in chains!
I must leave for her.
Sir.
Love between mother and child is the most innate of all. Yuanzhi, you shouldn't consider me before her.
After you meet with your mother,
it will not be too late to come back.
My lord...
Yuanzhi, no need to leave just yet!
I implore you to stay with me just this night!
Tomorrow, I will bid you farewell.
My lord, I-!
Yuanzhi!
Fine.
Xu Shu takes his leave!
Farewell.
My lord!
Yuanzhi is a rare genius in the world.
However, he saw the ins and outs of our army in Xinye.
If he goes to Cao Cao, his knowledge will be used.
That would bear ill toward us.
My lord, you should persist. Do not let him leave.
Cao Cao will see Yuanzhi did not join him, so he'll kill his mother.
When Yuanzhi hears of this,
he will certainly desire vengeance!
No!
To kill a mother
to keep the son, is atrocity!
Forcing him to stay —
— to sever the bond of
mother and son, is depravity!
I would rather die than become vile!