This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 16
Guān Yǔ's Three Terms
Zhāng Fēi captured Cáo Cāo's General, Liú Dài, at their camp.
However, Liú Bèi feared Cáo Cāo would return,
so he released Liú Dài and Wáng Zhōng back to Xǔchang.
Furthermore, he ordered Guān Yǔ to protect his wives and to remain at Xiàpī.
Sūn Qián and the others guarded Xú Province
while Zhāng Fēi guarded Xiǎopèi.
They thus formed an ox-horn defense against Cáo Cāo.
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Dǒng Chéng's servant?
Let him in!
This one is Qín Qìngtóng.
Chancellor, I and Dǒng Chéng's concubine were talking in the dark.
Dǒng Chéng saw us, suspected us of an affair, and had me beaten.
Qín Qìngtóng
Even wanted to kill me!
That's why I ran away from the mansion!
Chancellor.
Chancellor, Wáng Zǐfú, Wú Zǐlán, Zhǒng Jí, Wú Shuò, and Mǎ Téng
had a secret meeting in the mansion.
They plan to murder you, sire!
Dǒng Chéng had some silk to write characters, but did not know what to use as the pen.
Yesterday, Jí Píng and the others bit their fingers to seal their oath with blood.
I had seen it!
I saw them, but couldn't see what they were writing!
Jí Píng
Chancellor! Chancellor! They had ill intentions!
What if you lie to fulfill your grudge?
I wouldn't dare! I wouldn't dare!
You said they bit their fingers for an oath?
Which finger did Jí Píng bite then?
The index finger.
The right index finger!
Chancellor, I'm telling the truth! Please see for yourself!
Thank you, Chancellor!
Why is this medicine so difficult to decoct?
It's ready.
Chancellor, this medicine shall remove your ailment in one serving.
'Remove my ailment'?
Sir, you are erudite, therefore must know the etiquette!
I think you should know that
when the lord needs medicine,
their vassal must taste it first,
when the father needs medicine, their son must taste it first.
You happen to be one of my aides.
Why did you not taste it first?
Medicine is meant for treatment. Why have others taste it?
Gentlemen! This banquet is for you, we end only when drunk.
Wáng Zǐfú
Today, I invited all the important ministers here.
How come Dǒng Chéng isn't here? State Uncle Dǒng?
He hasn't arrived yet!
I heard he fell ill recently and couldn't come because of it.
And I heard you, Zǐfú, are a heavy drinker.
Come! I want to have a drinking contest!
With your prowess, I cannot possibly beat you, my lord.
Since you refuse merriment,
I'd like to show an amusement that'd make Zǐfú and the rest of you sober.
Zǐfú, are you sober?
Dǒng Chéng
Apologies for being unwelcoming.
Last night, why didn't you come to the banquet?
I was still sick, I dared not.
Perhaps a sickness for our nation.
I heard that the State Uncle was ill.
As such, I bring to you special medicine to treat thy illness.
This man has incriminated Wáng Zǐfú
and four others. They now imprisoned.
There is but one person not yet found and arrested.
Jí Píng?
Who is it that ordered you to poison me?
It's Heaven's will to kill you!
Chancellor, he can't take any more beatings.
Jí Píng, why is your right index finger wounded?
I bit that finger as oath,
to kill the traitor of the nation!
And now I will have your fingers cut off.
We'll see if you can make any more oaths.
I still have teeth to bite the traitor,
and I still have a tongue to curse that traitor!
Cut his tongue!
Yes!
Chancellor!
State Uncle, please tell me
where is... the imperial palace?
I wish... to see it one last time... Before death!
I was unable to eliminate the traitor!
Thus is Heaven's fate!
Grand Physician!
State Uncle, perhaps you recognize this man?
How could I not know?
Shameless drudge! Lecher! Craven deserter!
I should behead you here!
He was the first to leak the plot with his testimony. Who dares hurt him?
Chancellor, how could you heed the words of a serf!
Have you found it?
Vermin... You would dare?!
Your Majesty!
Your Majesty, the Chancellor has-
Dǒng Chéng intended to rebel. Was Your Majesty aware?
Dǒng Zhuō is dead.
Not Dǒng Zhuō... Dǒng Chéng!
We... don't know.
Did you forget that blood edict?
Your Majesty!
Take her out. Kill her.
Emperor
Xiàn of Hàn
Concubine Dǒng is with child of five-months! We beg Chancellor to spare her.
And leave a traitorous seed to germinate for vengeance?!
Guards, take her away!
If she refuses to die herself, hang her.
Yes!
I order Cáo Hóng to lead 3,000 soldiers as
the Imperial Guards for the palace.
Henceforth, if any relatives of the Emperor enters the palace without my permission, kill them!
Chancellor, we have Dǒng Chéng and over 700 people under arrest! What shall we do with them?
Kill them all.
Dǒng Chéng and the others may be dead,
but Liú Bèi and Mǎ Téng are also included.
They must be removed!
Mǎ Téng is guarding Xīliáng, not to be trifled with
We should present him an award to lure him into the capital,
then eliminate him!
Liú Bèi has only recently raised his troops, there's still unease.
If you were to march east with a regiment, they will be crushed in one battle!
Excellent! Send order to all troops,
I hereby raise a force of 20,000 to attack Xú Province from five directions...
and kill Liú Bèi.
Fadeth has the winter, cometh has the spring.
Gone hither are ice and snow.
A great time for battle.
Gōngyòu,
Go to Yuán Shào to convey my greetings.
Tell him to send reinforcments, and return.
Sūn Qián
Styled: Gōngyòu
Yes!
If anything goes wrong, we would have a backup.
Sir, dividing your troops to guard Xiàpī and Xiǎopèi,
while this forms an ox-horn defense,
but with the distance between them, if something were to happen...
You needn't say more.
Sir, Cáo Cāo is cunning and nefarious.
With a chance of a raid, you must be very careful.
Gōngyòu, you needn't worry too much.
Take good care.
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
My Lord?
With Cáo Cāo's attack against Liú Xuándé, Xǔchāng is undefended.
Tián Fēng
Styled: Yuánhào
We should exploit this by moving our troops in,
in the name of rescuing His Majesty, as well as the masses.
This would also solve Liú Bèi's crisis.
This is our chance.
Please, my Lord, make a decision.
I too know this is most opportune,
yet my heart is very confused.
Raising troops might do no good.
We can't miss this opportunity!
I could die!
My Lord, why say such?
I have five sons.
Only the youngest one I hold dear!
I don't want to him to die from scabies!
If he is about to die, my...
my mind will be troubled! Troubled so!
My Lord!
We will discuss military affairs later.
When you return back to Xuándé, explain the matter thoroughly.
I will come to you when I'm feeling better.
I will help you.
It would be easier if Second Brother were here.
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Don't worry, Elder Brother!
The enemy is coming from afar, so they will be exhausted!
They won't be prepared if you raid their camp!
Their defeat is guaranteed!
I have always regarded you as a warrior.
Back then, you managed to capture Liú Dài with clever planning.
And your tactic now is textbook!
Good! I shall leave to make preparations!
Select elite troops to raid the camp!
Alright! Wait!
Tonight, we will raid the camp together.
Yes!
Sire, Cáo Cāo's attack on Xú Province isn't the same as last time!
This matter is urgent. Sir, hurry back to Xú Province!
Yes! I shall take my leave.
Master Sūn!
Sir, return to Xú Province.
There, send someone to hurry over to Xiàpī and inform Yúnchǎng!
This matter is urgent, I will go to Xiàpī myself.
Tell Yúnchǎng that the enemy is approaching and that he must be careful.
Men, halt!
How could the flagpole be broken by wind out of nowhere?
Gentlemen, what do you think?
What does it bode?
Chancellor, why halt our march?
A great wind broke the flagpole.
The Chancellor asks what it could mean.
Where did the wind come from?
From the south-east!
What color was the flag?
It was the Chancellor's standard! The flag was red!
Guō Jiā
Styled: Fèngxiào
Liú Bèi will raid us today.
Those were my exact thoughts.
Order all units to standby!
Divide troops into nine! Leave one to build an empty camp! The others shall ambush from all eight sides.
Yes!
The Heavens smile upon me.
Advance!
Death!
Uh oh! We fell into that traitor Cáo's plan!
Retreat! Retreat!
Elder Brother!
Third Brother!
Guān Yǔ is protecting Liú Bèi's family. He'll die guarding Xiàpī.
If you don't obtain him now, I fear Yuán Shào may.
Wényuǎn, I have long admired
Yúnchǎng's prowess.
I wish to have him for my purposes.
It would be better to pressure him into submission.
Yúnchǎng is fiercely loyal.
Yúnchǎng and I are acquaintances. I will persuade him.
However...
Zhāng Liáo
Styled: Wényuǎn
Chancellor,
Yúnchǎng has strength of ten-thousand men,
he can only be swayed by cunning.
We should send back Liú Bèi's surrendered soldiers back to Xiàpī, and claim that they deserted.
Lay ambush within the city,
and lure Yúnchǎng out to fight us.
I will pretend defeat to lead him somewhere else,
have elite units cut off all escape routes.
Then I will ask for his surrender, and end this matter.
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúnchǎng
General, how can the sky be red today?
Is it the beacon from Xiàpī?
Yúnchǎng?
General Guān, do you really want to fight to the death?
A warrior without weapon.
Do you plan to mock me?
Alright, then let me tell you of last night's battle.
The Chancellor was already prepared. He had ambushes on all eight sides.
He has this mountain besieged as of now.
Yúnchǎng, trying to force your way
to Xiàpī simply isn't possible.
Chancellor Cáo has already broken into the city.
Please think this over, Yúnchǎng.
Wényuǎn, do you intend me to surrender?
No.
Back then, you saved me.
How could I not repay that?
Then will you break me out of this siege?
I cannot.
If you won't help me, then why are you here?
Yúnchǎng,
There is no news of sir Xuándé's survival. Sir Yìdé as well!
This time when Chancellor broke
into the city, we left citizens unharmed.
The Chancellor sent someone to watch over sir Xuándé's family.
That is all I want to say.
Then you do wish me to surrender.
Now I am at my end, as good as dead.
Go back whence you came,
and we will battle to the last.
Yúnchǎng!
To answer with such, do you wish ridicule upon yourself?
I will die with honor!
Why would I be ridiculed?
Sir, if you die in battle,
you will have committed three sins.
Explain yourself.
Prior, you and sir Liú formed a bond for greater good.
vowing to share life and death.
Now with sir Liú's defeat
you wish to fight to the death.
Yet if your master would return,
there would be no one to aid him.
Would that not be betrayal to your oath?
That is your first sin.
Sir Liú has entrusted his family to you.
If you die now, his wives would be without support!
How could that not betray his trust in you?
That is your second sin!
You abilities are without peer, and your learning vast.
Yet you don't consider aiding sir Liú to restore the Hàn Empire, but recklessly tread on fire.
That is a fool's bravery! How is that virtuous?
That is your third sin!
These are your three sins. I am sorry to tell you.
You say there are three sins,
then what do you wish of me?
Lord Cáo has us surrounded on all sides.
If you don't surrender, you will die.
To die would be for naught.
Better to surrender to Lord Cáo.
There, you could wait for news of your master, then return to him.
You would protect the two mistresses,
and secondly, you would not betray your oath.
Third, you could exercise aid for all.
With these three reasons, please reconsider!
For your three reasons, I answer with three terms.
If Lord Cáo is able to heed it, I shall cast off my armor.
If he won't accept it, I would rather die in battle with my three sins!
The Chancellor is bounteous. How could he refuse?
He will listen to your three conditions.
First, me and the Imperial Uncle made an oath to restore the Hàn Empire.
I cede only to the Emperor, not to Cáo Cāo.
Second, my sisters-in-laws' residence shall be supported with their husband's imperial salary.
Everyone, regardless of rank, is not allowed to enter.
Third, once I find out
the Imperial Uncle's whereabouts,
be the distance a thousand or tenfold,
I will leave sir Cáo to search for him.
If one of these three is refused, I will never surrender!
I expect you, Wényuǎn, to report this now!
He would leave once he finds out where Liú Bèi is?
Then why even bother keeping Guān Yúnchǎng?
Chancellor, you don't need to worry.
Yúncháng relation to Liú Bèi is only of kindness.
But if Chancellor were to show more favor to Yúncháng, to win him over,
why worry of Yúncháng's stay then?
Chancellor, is it not for Yúncháng's loyalty that you admire him of?
He is an honorable man who will repay his dues.
You are correct, Wényuǎn.
Good! I accept his three conditions!
Yes!
Wait.
All troops surrounding the mountain are to retreat 3,000 lǐ.
Allow Yúnchǎng to enter the city
and meet with two mistresses first.
Yes sir!
Second Brother.
Please forgive me for my absence.
I left the city to fight,
but was besieged at the mountains.
Cáo Cāo sent Zhāng Liáo to persuade my surrender. I accepted for three conditions.
First, I concede to the Hàn Empire, not to Cáo Cāo.
Secondly, he is to support the two of you.
Your residence cannot be entered by others.
Third, once I discover my elder brother's whereabouts,
I will leave Cáo Cāo to find him, no matter the distance
I could not ask of your thoughts, please forgive me.
Second Brother, do you know where the Imperial Uncle is?
I don't know...
Yesterday, when the Cáo army
entered the city, we would've died.
Yet no one had intruded us,
not one soldier dared to enter.
Now that you've sealed your agreement, why discuss it with us?
I only fear that in the future, that Cáo Cāo won't allow you to search for the imperial uncle.
Don't worry, sisters-in-law.
I made sure to have my say in it.
In that case, you can make the decisions.
You don't need to discuss them with us.
Please, Second Brother, be on your guard.
Sisters-in-laws, please come in and rest!
This defeated warrior is grateful
for the Chancellor's mercy.
I have long admired your loyalty and integrity.
To meet with you today is my greatest fortune.
Chancellor, Wényuǎn received my three terms.
Chancellor, I hope you won't violate your promise.
I made my promise.
How could I dare violate it?
If I know the imperial uncle's location,
I will search for him by hook or by crook.
I'm afraid I might not bid you farewell then.
Please accept my discourtesy.
Where Xuándé is at is where I will send you, sir.
I only fear he may have already
died within my army's arrival.
Sir, fear not, for I will search everywhere for him.
Thank you, Chancellor!