This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 2
The Crisis of Ten Attendants
Ginseng soup.
As I see it, the emperor will
only last for another two days.
What shall we do?
The emperor favors Liú Xié,
naturally he'd like for him to succeed.
What about Liú Biàn?
Do you think Empress Hé and Hé Jìn
will just leave it at that?
Duàn Guī
Currently, our first plan is
to deal with Hé Jìn. When he dies, Empress Hé-
What can she do?
Everything she has she owes to us.
Who's there?
Empress Dowager
Dǒng
Divine spirits hear me.
Bless his majesty with a speedy recovery.
I'm willing to trade the years I have left
for the emperor to have a few more.
Please bless his majesty, divine spirits.
Liú Xié
Grandmother.
No... Empress Dowager, don't worry.
I'll definitely be a good emperor.
Please bless his majesty, divine spirits.
Empress Hé
Liú Biàn
My respects to Empress Dowager Dǒng.
My respects to Empress Hé!
Rise.
My grandson?
His Majesty?
His Majesty!
Jiàn Shuò
Alright.
Has Hé Jìn reached the palace?
He's probably still on the road.
Kill all who leaks the news.
Yes.
Generalissimo.
Generalissimo, this way please.
Generalissimo, don't enter the palace.
His Majesty summoned me, how could I not go?
His Majesty has passed away!
The Ten Attendants are keeping it a secret.
I think, sir, they intend to assassinate you.
Is it true?
Let's go!
Zhāng Ràng
Who leaked the news?
It's all over!
Jiǎn Shuò, make sure to step up security!
I'll personally see to it!
Hé Jìn still wants to enter the palace.
Why do you think that is?
It's only to force Liú Biàn onto the imperial throne.
Today will be a momentous day! We must all speak as one!
Those rotten eunuchs!
I will exterminate them all!
Sire, please calm.
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
The eunuchs' power has been growing since the reigns of Emperors Chōng and Zhì.
Their influence spreads all across the court.
Their power didn't accumulate overnight,
nor can it be taken down overnight.
If we don't keep this a secret,
we'll be the ones eliminated.
Hé Jìn
Styled: Suìgāo
Please, Generalissimo, reconsider.
You're just a subordinate. What would you know of imperial court affairs?
The late emperor favored Jiǎn Shuò.
Jiǎn Shuò and Empress Dowager Dǒng have a close relationship.
Only by putting blame on Jiǎn Shuò,
can we still save our lives.
Correct! Correct! Blame it all on Jiǎn Shuò!
Second, we need hurry over to Empress Hé,
grovel before her, and beg for our lives.
She's the only one who
has the power to save us now.
Generalissimo,
you are to hurry over to the palace!
Return ahead of me.
Yes.
Sir, the imperial guardsmen are
under the command of Jiǎn Shuò.
I'm worried they've already set an ambush.
We should first install the rightful emperor, then wipe out the eunuchs.
Mèngdé, your words quite suit me.
Who dares assist me and eliminate them?
Give me 5,000 elite troops, to enter the palace.
Coronate the rightful emperor, then kill the eunuchs and restore peace to the realm!
With Běnchū's help, I can rest assured!
Good!
Summon all the ministers to gather at the palace.
Your Majesty!
Sir, ambushes outside the court have been cleared.
We dare not venture further inside the palace.
Why don't we eliminate
the eunuchs and purge the court?
Restore peace to the realm!
Generalissimo, stick to the plan.
Crown the emperor first,
then purge the eunuchs afterwards!
Mèngdé is correct,
the nation can't go on without its leaders!
We should crown the new emperor right now!
This minister requests the Crown Prince to ascend the throne immediately.
Your minister, Hé Jìn, congratulates
the Crown Prince on his ascension to the throne!
Long live!
Long live His Majesty!
Elder brother,
you can't trust those high officials.
I understand court affairs better than you do.
The plot to murder you
was orchestrated by Jiǎn Shuò alone.
Zhāng Ràng and the others had nothing to do with it.
Empress Dowager, you...!
Why do you favor Zhāng Ràng and his ilk?
Generalissimo,
think about it.
We come from a poor background.
If it weren't for Zhāng Ràng and his
faction, could we be where we are today?
Enjoying wealth and prestige?
Empress Dowager, you're right.
But...
where's this Jiǎn Shuò now?
You all may come out now.
Generalissimo, spare our lives!
Generalissimo, it was Jiǎn Shuò who
collaborated with Grand-Empress Dowager Dǒng!
The plot against you, Generalissimo, had nothing to do with us!
That villain Jiǎn Shuò has been killed.
We present you his head.
Please! Generalissimo for the sake
of our past friendship, spare us!
From now on, we'll wait for the
Generalissimo's orders before acting.
We swear our loyalty! We would never consider betraying you!
Jiǎn Shuò has already been punished for his crimes.
Why should you believe the words of others?
They are truly innocent.
For the sake of the Empress Dowager,
you will be spared this once!
But listen closely!
There won't be a next time!
If you plot to kill me again, I won't be as merciful!
Thank you, Generalissimo! We wouldn't dare!
Jiǎn Shuò has been eliminated for his plot against me.
Generalissimo, Zhāng Ràng
simply shifted the blame to another.
Do you really want to let
the Ten Attendants get away with it?
I want Jiǎn Shuò's entire family put to death! Exterminate them all!
As for the rest of the eunuchs...
there's no need to be cruel.
If we don't remove the eunuchs now, there will be trouble.
My decision is final! This talk is over!
Dismissed.
Grand-Empress Dowager,
don't hurt your hands.
You all served as the servants of the late majesty.
The late emperor favored and raised you up.
Why are you all mute now?
Empress Dowager, the late Emperor's bones are barely even cold yet.
They wouldn't dare to harm
the Grand-Empress Dowager.
You're still the Grand-Empress Dowager.
That Empress Dowager Hé, although it was her son who became Emperor,
she still has to show respect
to the Grand-Empress Dowager,
regardless of His Majesty's passing.
But if the Grand-Empress Dowager
wished to say something,
you could demote some officials,
even Hé Jìn and Empress Hé.
Who'd dare to disobey you?
That's right.
The Grand-Empress Dowager
is still the Grand-Empress Dowager.
That Hé Jìn just established Biàn as the emperor himself.
He was only one step ahead of us.
Grand-Empress Dowager, don't give in.
Why not take your own way?
What do you mean by 'take your own way?'
Empress Dowager Hé has Prince Biàn;
Grand-Empress Dowager, don't you have Prince Xié?
Empress Dowager Hé has her elder brother Hé Jìn;
Grand-Empress Dowager, don't you have your own maternal relatives?
In my opinion, it's better to act sooner rather than later.
Tomorrow morning, before the Imperial Court,
the Grand-Empress Dowager may confer the title Prince of Chénliú upon Prince Xié
and appoint her nephew Dǒng Chòng
the General of Flying Cavalry,
in order to check their power.
Good,
I'll hold court from behind the curtain.
Note: Women weren't allowed to attend the court. However, it was an open secret that many Empresses did so from 'behind the curtain'.
Generalissimo,
what's the problem?
This morning, without Generalissimo's presence,
The Grand-Empress Dowager suddenly appeared in court to listen to the proceedings.
There was an imperial decree conferring the title Price of Chénliú on Prince Xié.
and promoting Dǒng Chòng to General of Flying Cavalry.
Emphasis was also given for the Ten Attendants
to manage the affairs of state.
Is this true?!
If this isn't the work of the Ten Attendants,
then it's the Grand-Empress Dowager causing trouble.
Wait, I'll go to the palace to investigate.
Elder brother, I don't think this matter has anything to do with the Ten Attendants.
I didn't hear anything about it.
Think about it, brother.
Biàn succeeded the throne, how could the Grand-Empress Dowager not be angry?
You're the Generalissimo,
in control of all military forces.
How can she not be jealous?
I figure her intentions are
nothing more than to make a move against our clan.
Yes, definitely.
That day, Zhāng Ràng and the eunuchs swore allegiance to me.
They were spared and wouldn't dare act against me again.
The Grand-Empress Dowager is weak and isolated.
It's natural for her to try and
gain the support of the Ten Attendants.
How about we use this opportunity to
persuade Grand-Empress Dowager Dǒng
to stay out of court affairs.
All right.
We're family, talk frankly.
There is no need to be formal.
Mother Empress, you and I are women.
It's not appropriate to be interfering with court affairs.
In the past when Empress Lǚ held power she interfered with court affairs.
Note: Empress Lǚ dominated early Hàn politics for 15 years through brutality and the use of puppet emperors.
Finally, more than a thousand of her family members were executed; her clan exterminated.
Now you and I should just live
peacefully inside the palace,
and let the veteran ministers discuss court affairs.
It's what is best for the empire.
I sincerely hope you will listen
carefully to your daughter-in-law.
You dare attempt to lecture me?
Without my recommendation,
could you even be here today?
Would your son have become the Emperor?
Have you forgotten all this?
Your daughter-in-law wouldn't dare to.
I only wanted to remind you.
Remind me?
I'm quite aware.
First you were jealous of Beauty Wáng
and had her poisoned.
Note: Beauty Wáng was a favored concubine of the late Emperor and the mother of Liú Xié.
Do you want to kill me now as well?
If you dare keep speaking this nonsense,
I'll have Dǒng Zhòng kill you and your brother.
I tried to advise you reasonably.
Empress-Mother, why are you so unreasonable?
You?
You dare to speak about being unreasonable?
Ridiculous, truly ridiculous.
You!
Empress-Mother, better watch your words.
True, I came from a poor background.
However, Empress-Mother,
you used to be only a concubine.
If it wasn't for your son
succeeding Emperor Xiàohuán,
could you become the national mother?
Given our current roles,
perhaps it's best to not mention our past.
What's wrong with being a concubine?
This concubine is a hundred times better than you.
Maybe before, but not anymore.
What's so different between then and now?
Is it that you want to kill me?
I wouldn't dare to kill Empress Mother!
I'm only capable of daring to kill pigs.
You.
Outrageous!
I wouldn't dare!
If a junior slighted an elder
wouldn't that be a major offense?
Do you think the Emperor is going to punish me?
You can't use the Emperor to threaten me.
I'm not afraid.
Well then, Grand-Empress Dowager,
what are you afraid of?
Grand-Empress Dowager Dǒng
having been a concubine,
is unfit to reside in the palace.
With the death of the late emperor,
there is less reason for her to stay.
She is to return to her hometown
and leave for Héjiān effectively immediately.
The Grand-Empress Dowager is not used to your crude meals!
Get rid of it!
Bring it over!
The Generalissimo has sent this imperial wine to honor the Grand-Empress Dowager.
Please drink and enjoy, Grand-Empress Dowager.
Grand-Empress Dowager! The wine is poisoned!
Grand-Empress Dowager!
Please, Grand-Empress Dowager, drink the wine.
The Grand-Empress Dowager
has been poisoned by Hé Jìn.
Hé Jìn, that pig butcher!
How dare he murder the state mother!
Arrogant miscreant!
If wasn't for us, he wouldn't be where he is today.
The mountains that backed us have collapsed.
How should we act from this?
We can only see the wind and steer the helm,
or we could join up with Hé Jìn.
Either way... nonsense!
Although Hé Jìn may not have grand ambitions,
which of the high officials
backing him doesn't hates us?
If not for them,
would Hé Jìn dare enthrone the new
emperor during the late one's funeral?
Now today, he poisoned the Grand-Empress Dowager.
If we don't act now, we'll be endangered!
Only by removing Hé Jìn first,
can the others be brought into line.
All our power lies inside the palace.
We must keep control over the
Emperor or the Empress Dowager.
Then...
we can do as we please.
Around the Empress Dowager,
we need to be very careful.
So long as we can handle the three royals,
Hé Jìn will fall easily as turning over the palm of hand.
Why shouldn't I want to kill the eunuchs?
The Empress Dowager says
the eunuchs are capable administrators,
that their mandate was established since the prior reign and shouldn't be disregarded.
And since we're still in mourning for the late Emperor.
It's disrespectful to the shrine of the forefathers to kill veteran servants.
What can I do now?
Indecision will cause trouble.
Generalissimo, I, Běnchū, and all the other generals are all ready for your commands.
Zhāng Ràng is spreading rumors.
Why don't we use this excuse to execute them.
We shouldn't waste this opportunity.
The Empress Dowager would never go along.
Generalissimo, you may summon some frontier troops to enter the capital.
Use them to exterminate the eunuchs, and ignore the Empress Dowager!
Excellent plan!
Really excellent plan!
Call the Registrar; Chén Lín!
Gentlemen,
I went and told my brother to spare your lives.
Are you still afraid I can't keep your old lives safe?
The Empress Dowager humours us!
With you protecting us,
Whom can compare with you?
It's true, it's true.
Cáo Cāo pays his respects to the Generalissimo.
Generalissimo,
it's an easy matter to remove the eunuchs.
A warden is equal to the task, why summon a frontier army?
A warden is enough?
A warden is enough!
All of the issues come from the ringleaders. No need to exterminate everyone.
If we want to kill everyone,
the plot will leak out, and we'll certainly fail.
Oh... I get it now!
Mèngdé is related to the eunuchs.
It's only natural for him to be soft on them.
Note: Cáo Cāo's father, Cáo Sōng was adopted by the eunuch Cáo Téng.
You!
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
The one who ruins the nation, be none other than Hé Jìn!
Dīng Yuán
Styled: Jiànyáng
Dǒng Zhuó is on the table to remove the eunuchs?
Who doesn't know his relation with the Ten Attendants?
During the Yellow Turban Rebellion,
he was defeated and suffered heavy casualties.
If it weren't for the Ten Attendants' favor,
how could he have replaced Director Lú?
Fortunately, Huángfǔ Sōng testified to your merits, Director Lú.
Otherwise, Zigān, how could you be here today?
So...
Dǒng Zhuó is coming with 200,000 armored troops.
The eunuchs are about to be swept away as easily as turning over the palm of hand.
Generalissimo, Dǒng Zhuó is a rabid wolf.
Zhèng Tài
Let him in the capital, and he will eat people.
You're too suspicious!
He can't possibly be able to do such a thing!
Generalissimo,
Lú Zhí
Styled: Zǐgān
I know Dǒng Zhuó.
He may seems kind
but is cruel as can be.
Once in the capital,
he will bring disaster.
Better to stop him from
entering the capital to avoid chaos.
These are all just pedantic opinions!
There is no discussion.
The order has been given.
We can no longer bear this office.
Farewell.
Abandon your post and flee!
Dǒng Zhuó
Styled: Zhòngyǐng
Empress Dowager!
The Generalissimo has ordered
frontier armies to enter the capital!
He plans to kill us! Please save our lives,
Empress Dowager, we beg you!
Rise.
All rise.
What's the big deal?
You all head over to the Generalissimo's
residence and admit your crimes.
I'll go and speak well on your behalf again.
Empress Dowager...
we servants wouldn't dare go to the
Generalissimo's house!
If we go over to his residence to admit our crimes,
we'll be crushed into dust!
Please, Empress Dowager! Summon the Generalissimo to enter the palace
so we can be before you when we admit our crimes to him!
Empress Dowager!
If the Generalissimo still won't forgive us,
we'd rather die before our Empress Dowager!
We don't want to die outside.
Empress Dowager!
Alright, alright.
I'll do as you say.
Summon the Generalissimo to enter the palace.
Yes, Empress Dowager.
Pass the order!
Summon the Generalissimo
to enter the palace!
Generalissimo, don't enter the palace.
Why not?
Empress Dowager's edict must be
Zhāng Ràng and Duàn Guī's trap.
General you mustn't go inside,
there will surely be trouble.
Ridiculous, my very own sister summoned me.
What can go wrong?
Generalissimo, the order for
frontier troops must have leaked out.
We are exposed!
How can we still enter the palace?
To meet the Empress Dowager, you must first
summon all the eunuchs out of the palace.
An act of lesser men! I hold the power of the realm.
What could the Ten Attendants dare do to me?
Generalissimo,
if you insist on going, we will come with you.
Just in case.
Alright,
don't worry.
Quick, quick!
The Empress Dowager summons only the Generalissimo, no one else.
I hold the supreme power of the realm.
What would Zhāng Ràng, Duàn Guī,
and the others dare do to me?
Generalissimo,
please board your carriage!
Generalissimo?!
The eunuchs have murdered a high official!
Follow me! We will enter the palace!
Exterminate the eunuchs!
Empress Dowager, it's an emergency, quickly follow your ministers to escape the palace!
No, I'm not going anywhere!
Hurry!
No, what are you doing?
Hurry up! Hurry up!
I'm not going anywhere,
let go of me! Someone, help me!
Quick, this way, this way!
Hurry, hurry!
Empress Dowager
Empress Dowager?
Please, Empress Dowager.
We await your orders.
Biàn-er?
Biàn-er!
My son!
What?
Search and find the Emperor and the Prince of Chénliú!
Your Majesty!
Mǐn Gòng
Quickly, stand up.
Who's coming?
This minister, the Marquis of Áoxiāng and the Overseer of Xīliáng; Dǒng Zhuó has arrived.
Wáng Yǔn
Styled: Zǐshī
You are Dǒng Zhuó?
This minister is Dǒng Zhuó.
Back when the Yellow Turbans rebelled, you were defeated and suffered heavy casualties.
Are you aware of your guilt?
This minister confesses.
The new regime is still young
and you came just in time for the rescue,
doing us a great service.
Lǐ Rú
From now on, you have to make up your previous actions by doing good deeds.
Lǐ Sù
I obey.
This minister will do everything
he can to assist the Imperial Court.
Escort us to the palace.