This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 6
The Chain-Link Stratagem
Sūn Jiān
Styled: "Wéntái"
Report! We've found a person in a well!
My lord, they have found someone!
Go take a look!
Yes!
Pull it out.
My lord?
Huáng Gài
Styled: "Gōngfù"
Heavens! My Lord, congratulations!
Chéng Pǔ
Styled: "Démóu"
That's the Heirloom Seal of the Realm!
The Heirloom Seal?
My lord!
Of old, Biàn Hé, at the foot of Mount Jīngshān,
saw a phoenix perching on a stone.
He presented the stone to King Wén of Chǔ,
he ordered it to be cracked open, finding a piece of jade.
It would be known as the Jade of Hé!
Later, Qín Shǐ Huáng ordered his artisans to carve a seal from the jade,
and Lǐ Sī engraved those eight characters on it.
Once, Qín Shǐ Huáng was patrolling Dòngtíng lake, and a violent storm erupted.
The ship was about to sink so he threw the jade into the lake. The storm receded.
Eight years later, when Shǐ Huáng was inspecting Huáyīn,
a passerby presented him with the same seal.
Thus, the Jade Seal was returned to Qín.
The next year, Qín Shǐ Huáng passed away.
Eventually, his grandson, Ziyīng, would relinquish the jade Seal to Gāozǔ of Hàn.
Thereafter, it has been known as the Heirloom Seal.
My lord, we can't stay here! We must hurry back to Jiāngdōng! Plan our next move!
That is exactly what I think.
Tomorrow, I will report sick, then leave.
Yes!
Yuán Shào
Styled: "Běnchū"
I've caught a slight ailment, so I need to return to Chǎngshā.
I've come to bid farewell.
What illness? Could it be the illness of the Jade Seal!?
Why do you speak thus?
We have risen against a traitor to rid the empire of a menace!
The Seal belongs to the royal family.
Sir, since you have it,
you ought to return to me!
After eliminating Dong Zhuo, will I return it.
Yet you hide it and wish to scurry away!
What is the meaning of this?
That... how could the Heirloom Seal be within my possession?
Where is the thing in the
well near Jiànzhāng hall?
I don't have it! Why interrogate me so?
Return it now, or you will suffer!
Oh, high heavens!
If I indeed have the Seal and am hiding it for myself,
may I meet a painful end, struck by arrows!
Since Wéntái has made such an oath,
perhaps he doesn't have the Seal after all.
When you salvaged it, was this fellow present?
You dare deceive us!
Report! Sir, Cao Cao led his army to pursue Dong Zhuo.
He was ambushed and routed! He's now returning!
He didn't listen to me.
No wonder he's lost.
Prepare a banquet behind the tent to solace Mèngdé!
Gentlemen!
Cheers!
Cáo Cāo
Styled: "Mèngdé"
Mengde.
Mengde, don't be upset.
Victory and defeat are all part of war.
I fought for great justice to rid the empire of a traitor.
From eighteen directions came armies fighting for justice.
My heart was grateful...!
Utmost grateful...
I was to have Bénchū rally the the people in Hénèi,
lead them to Mèngjīn and Suānzǎo, guard Chénggāo,
seize granaries, and obstruct Huányuán, the great valley. Secure the station.
Gōnglù! You were to lead the men of Nányáng,
garrison Dānxī, and enter Wǔ pass so we could attack from three directions.
Thus, a high ground.
Not to fight, but to threaten.
Showing the realm our strength,
the people would rebel, and thus pacify the land!
Yet, you hesitate and refuse to follow.
and we lost the world's hope in us...
For shame... For shame!
Gōngsūn Zàn
Styled: "Bóguī"
For shame!
The coalition has righteous warriors
willing to destroy a powerful group of enemies.
In the beginning, they met at Méngjīn, willing to free the capital from evil.
But their forces were uncoordinated,
they hesitated and moved like geese, leaderless.
Out of selfish interests,
they were willing to kill each other.
The one in Huáinán is so prideful,
and the one in the north carved a seal.
Note: Referring to Yuán Shù and Yuán Shào.
Yuán Shù would declare himself Emperor,
Yuán Shào would attempt to make Liú Yú emperor.
From the armor of the soldiers, lice are born, with tens of thousands of people dead.
Bones rest in the wild,
where no birds sing within a thousand lǐ.
Out of a hundred who live here, only one survives.
That mere thought splits my heart with empathy.
Gentlemen? Ministers?
Dǒng Zhuō
Styled: "Zhòngyǐng"
Those eighteen renegades are now in utter shambles, fragmented and split up.
They've already begun to eat each other.
Now, General Sūn Jiān has been killed by the hands of Liú Biǎo!
Qiáo Mào was killed by Liú Dài!
Hán Fù lost the Jì Province and fled to Zhāng Miǎo for shelter.
And as for Yuan Shao and Gongsun Zan?
All willing to submit to me!
Gentlemen, you are all veteran ministers of the dynasty.
As long as you remain loyal,
Your old friend here can promise you prestige, rank, and wealth!
Thanks, Grand Preceptor, for your great virtue!
Bring them in!
Come!
Put them all to death!
Come, everyone!
Ever since I moved the capital and led you all here, I never got to feast with you all!
Today, I shall be your host!
Gentlemen? Cheers!
Father?
So that's how it is...!
Gentlemen, no worries!
Wáng Yǔn
Styled: "Zishī"
Zhāng Wēn conspired with Yuan Shu!
They planned to harm me!
Yuan Shu snuck a letter for him, but by accident, my son, Fengxian,
discovered it, and so he was executed.
Why, brother Benchu?
You wench!
Diāochán
Look at you, wailing and
sighing late at night.
Perhaps you have an affair?
Yes, I had an affair!
If I may speak with honesty.
Explain!
Diaochan has received your generosity for sixteen years,
teaching me to sing and dance.
Treating me with great kindness!
Even if I were crushed into dust,
it wouldn't be enough to repay a thousandth part of your kindness!
Today, I saw you an anxious, instead of joy.
I figure, there must be a great state affair worrying you,
but I dare not ask too much.
Today, I noticed that you broke down and refused to eat, nervous at all times.
I hate myself for not being
able to ease my lord's worries,
so I have been sighing
at the moon instead
I didn't want you to notice, my lord.
My lord, if you ever have a use for me,
I will not back down, even after 10,000 deaths.
Who would've thought the fate of
the great Han rests within your hands!
Follow me!
My lord, you don't need to!
This is more than I will ever deserve!
My lord, if you ever have a use for me,
I will not back down, even after 10,000 deaths!
Right now, the people are in great peril.
Both the Emperor and his ministers are in jeopardy!
But it's not as if you cannot help them.
The traitorous Dong Zhuo wants to usurp the throne!
All officials of the court are unable to oppose him.
Now Dong Zhuo has an adopted son by the name of Lü Bu.
His valiance is extraordinary!
I have observed that both Dong Zhuo and Lü Bu are lecherous.
I wish to employ a Chain-Link Stratagem.
First of all, I will let Lü Bu marry you,
and at the same time, present you to Dong Zhuo!
If you can go in between them, you can strain the relationship between father and son!
Eventually, it will provoke Lü Bu to murder the traitor, and end a great evil!
With that, restore the land once more!
Would you do it?
I already said it. Just give the order.
I won't leave, even if it means death!
My lord, just do what you must, I know what to do!
If this discussion gets out, our family will be exterminated!
My lord, don't grieve!
If I can't repay your great kindness,
may I bleed to death by 10,000 knives!
I am most grateful!
Lǚ Bù
Styled: "Fèngxiān"
General!
it seems you're in a good mood by yourself here!
Minister, its not often I see you in the hunting grounds!
Did you catch any game?
Oh no, no game.
After I settled here, I often go out
with my family to admire the nature.
I wonder if you, sir, would like to join us?
Thank you, sir, but the Grand Preceptor has orders for me. I dare not tardy.
Please do so, sir!
Please do come visit me later on!
Thank you, sir!
Hurry up!
I did not expect you to come!
Please excuse me for my discourtesy!
Forgive me! Forgive me!
Sir, it's alright, it's alright!
This way.
Please.
Please take the seat of honor, sir.
I wouldn't dare!
Sir, you are a grand minister,
I am just an officer! How could I accept?
You should take it, sir.
Sir, you must be mistaken.
Within the realm today, many people claim to be heroes,
but only you, general, are worthy enough!
I am not honoring you because of your rank, but because of your abilities!
But you, sir, refuse to claim the seat.
Could it be that you look down on me?
No way! But if so, please allow me.
Please.
I shall offer a cup for the Grand Preceptor, and for you as well!
Alright.
For the Grand Preceptor's longevity!
For the General's health! Cheers!
Cheers!
Cheers.
General? General!
Sir.
Haven't you seen General Lü before?
Sir, who is this lady?
My humble daughter, Diaochan.
I pay my respects, General.
No need! No need!
General, there's no need to be formal.
You've shown us charity, and so I view you as part of my family.
Thus, I told my daughter to come here so that she may see you.
My child, would you serve
a cup for the General?
General?
Yes, I'll drink.
General, even in my chamber,
I've long heard of your reputation.
Your name echoes like thunder.
Because I look up to you, sir, I have made this cap
to express my admiration, just for you.
It is just a token of my respect.
I hope you do not laugh at it.
My lady, not only are you clever and deft,
but you are also very beautiful and pure! Your speech is elegant as well!
My lady, you may sit.
The General is a good friend.
My child, do take a seat.
Please.
General,
I wish to give you my
daughter as a concubine.
I wonder if you will accept
or refuse my offer.
Since that is the case,
I am at your complete service,
so that I may repay you, sir!
If so, we must set a date
for an auspicious day
to bring my daughter
to your residence.
Exalted father-in-law, I shall accept your generous gift!
No need to be so formal!
General. General!
In the future, my family
will rely on you, sir!
Sir, you are flattering me!
It's night already.
I intended for you to stay the night,
but then Zhongying will grow suspicious.
It's midnight already.
I'll thank you another day.
I drank too much tonight, so I am not well.
I beg your pardon. I'll let my daughter accompany you, general.
Do as you please, sir!
Court dismissed!
Father!
Fèngxiān!
I need you to go Méiwù to escort munitions.
I also need you to lead some troops to be garrisoned, just in case!
Father, please ease yourself!
I will surely return within three days!
If I may dare, sir, can I ask you visit my humble abode for a banquet!
How would you, sir, feel about it?
If the exalted minister wants me to go, how could I refuse.
You flatter me! I am unworthy
of the Grand Preceptor's grace!
So you really have come!
I present my humble respects!
Sir, please!
Note: Duke Wen of Zhou helped found the Zhou dynasty, considered the forefather of Confucian virtues.
Sir, your majestic virtue towers over
Yī Yǐn and the Duke of Zhōu!
For you to have visited my humble abode gives me enough fortune to last three lives!
Sir, after you.
Grand Preceptor,
please drink a cup.
I wish the Grand Preceptor a prosperous life!
Your virtue is enough to overflow the four seas!
Heh, cheers!
Cheers!
From a young age, I have studied astronomy.
Lately, I observed an odd phenomenon at night,
and knew the days of the Hàn reign were waning.
Sir, your virtue echoes throughout the world,
Note: Shùn, Yáo and Yǔ are the mythical rulers of the era of Three Sovereigns and Five Emperors.
like Shùn succeeding Yáo and Yǔ succeeding Shùn
to finish their great cause, meet the hopes of the world!
Sir, you can't disobey the will of heaven and the people!
How could I dare do so?
Of old, those with principles fought those without it,
those without virtue submitted to those with it. Sir, if you take over the realm,
it would be in concert with the will of the world!
If the Mandate of Heaven is indeed mine,
then you, gracious minister, are a founder of a new dynasty!
I am most grateful for your support, sir!
I will never forget your great generosity, even in old age!
Good! Very good!
May I entertain you this once?
I have a dancer in my house. Would you be interested?
Very good, very good...
Who is this woman?
A singer, Diaochan.
Excellent... she's excellent!
Her dancing is perfect, and she is even more perfect!
Serve a cup to the Preceptor!
Yes.
How young are you?
I am only sixteen years of age.
You're truly a deity amongst fairies!
I wish to present this woman to you, sir!
I didn't know whether you agree or not.
Sir, since you've shown me so much kindness,
what can I do to repay you?
Sir, what are you saying?
For her to be presented to you, sir, is a blessing!
You flatter me!
Gracious minister, gifting this lovely beauty to me
shows your great virtue indeed! I am very grateful!
You flatter me!
If I were to respect you, this is the least I could do.
Ready my chariot!
Let's return home!
I'll send my daughter to your house.
No need to escort further, my good sir.
Do return.
Take care, Grand Preceptor.
I was looking for you!
You dare to trick me?
General, this is no place to talk. We'll talk inside.