This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 7
Fèngyí Pavilion
General.
General!
Ducal Minister,
you were about to betroth Diāochán to me.
Why did you send her to the Grand Preceptor?
General! Please, calm down! Calm down!
General, you misunderstand.
Please?
Someone told me...
that you sent Diāochán in a carriage
to the Premier's mansion as a gift!
Wáng Yǔn
Styled: Zishī
You probably don't know this, but...
Yesterday, in court,
the Grand Preceptor told me,
"I'll come to your household tomorrow,
I have something to discuss."
So I prepared a small feast for him.
While he was drinking, he said,
"I heard you have a daughter named Diāochán"
"that you betrothed to my son, Fèngxiān."
Lǚ Bù
Styled: Fèngxiān
"I was afraid it was undecided,"
"so I'm here to confirm and meet her as well."
I dare not let him down.
So I led Diāochán to greet the Grand Preceptor,
and he said, "Today is a good day!"
"Allow me to take this girl to marry Fèngxiān."
Imagine, General,
the Grand Preceptor came to pick her up in person.
How could I dare refuse him?
So I had to send my daughter over.
So that's how it was...
I'm sorry to have troubled you, sir.
I owe you my humblest apology.
General, you didn't know,
what's there to apologize for?
Where's the Grand Preceptor?
The Grand Preceptor is sleeping with his new bride.
He hasn't got up yet.
Which new bride?
A girl named Diāochán.
Diāochán?
Diāochán
Come here, darling!
Fèngxiān, my son! What's going on?
No... nothing!
Dǒng Zhuō
Styled: Zhòngyǐng
Get out of here.
You dare to desire my mistress?!
Get out of here!
Get out of here! You are forbidden to enter!
Who's present?
The Grand Preceptor sent this servant to come.
He said the Marquis of Wēn from
now on can enter his mansion
as if it was your own home,
no need to be formal.
That senile lech!
He dares to mock me!
General, why aren't you in court
with the Grand Preceptor?
It's not safe to talk here.
You may first go to
Fèngyí Pavillion and wait for me.
General!
General, though I am not
Ducal Minister Wáng's natural daughter,
he treats me like I am.
I fell for you at first sight, my general.
So he betrothed me to you.
I hoped I could depend on you all my life,
but the lecherous Grand Preceptor deflowered me.
I didn't kill myself there only
because I wanted to say farewell to you,
I will have to live with this humiliation.
Luckily today, I was able
to see you General.
My wish has been fulfilled.
My body has been defiled.
I cannot be with you any longer.
I only wish you see me one last time, general!
I've long known your heart!
I only regret not being together.
I can't be your wife in this life.
We'll have to meet in the next.
If I cannot marry you in this life,
then I am no hero!
For me, a day here is like a year.
I force a smile before him and weep behind him.
Please take pity, General! Save me!
Has Fèngxiān been here?
He went to the inner hall.
Today, I've come unannounced,
fearing the old lech will see me.
I...
I have to leave now!
General!
General, if you are so afraid of that old lech,
then I will never get out of here!
Give me time, I'll think of something.
Where's Diāochán at?
She's in the garden admiring the flowers.
When I was in my boudoir,
I heard of your great name
like thunder piercing the ears.
I thought you were the greatest hero of this era,
but instead, even you
are controlled by others.
Grand Preceptor!
What are you doing here?
I've.. I've came to your mansion
when I learnt that you were furious
and went straight to the
back garden to look for Lǚ Bù.
I came and saw Lǚ Bù escaping. He was shouting, "The Grand Preceptor wants to kill me!"
I've rushed here to mediate peace
but accidentally bumped into you!
Please forgive me!
That bastard whelp! He has the guts to have an affair with my mistress?
I'll kill him!
Calm down! Grand Preceptor,
calm down! That won't do!
Lǐ Rú
Note: King Zhuāng of Chǔ was one of the Five Hegemons of the Spring and Autumn period.
Sir, of old, King Zhuāng of Chǔ hosted a feast with his retainers one night.
When the candle was out, Jiǎng Xióng took advantage to flirt with the queen,
but the queen ripped the tassel from his hat
and asked King Zhuāng of Chǔ to light the candle to reveal the offender,
but King Zhuāng of Chǔ ordered all the retainers to remove their tassels
so the lights wouldn't indicate the offender.
After King Zhuāng of Chǔ was surrounded by Qín troops,
Jiǎng Xióng risked his life to save him.
At present, Diāochán is merely just a woman
and Lǚ Bù is your most trusted and fierce general.
Grand Preceptor, if you can seize this opportunity
and give Diāochán to Lǚ Bù,
Lǚ Bù will remember this kindness and will definitely repay you with his life.
Consider the advantages.
I hope that sir understands this.
Slut!
You dare have an affair with Lǚ Bù?
Grand Preceptor!
Grand Preceptor, I was only admiring
the flowers in the garden,
when Lǚ Bù suddenly came.
I wanted to avoid him,
but he said, "I am the Grand Preceptor's son.
Why must you avoid me?"
With these words, he forced me to Fèngyí Pavilion with his halberd.
I knew he had no good intentions
and I was afraid he'd assail me and disgrace you,
so I intended to drown myself in the lotus pond.
But he held me from behind.
I was between life and death
when you came and saved my life.
So that's how it was.
Thank you for your forgiveness!
What if I were to send you to Lǚ Bù?
How does it sound?
I would rather die than be disgraced!
I was only joking!
It must be Lǐ Rú's idea!
He has a profound friendship with Lǚ Bù
so he set up this plan regardless of your honor, and my life.
How could I have the heart to give you up!
Although you love me dearly,
I'm afraid we cannot stay here for long,
or Lǚ Bù will certainly hurt us.
Méiwù(郿坞) was Dong Zhuo's real-life fortified manor, located 250 lǐ from Chang'an.
Tomorrow, we'll live together in my Méiwù-manor!
You can enjoy a joyful life there,
carefree and without worries!
Many thanks, Grand Preceptor!
Grand Preceptor, today is a good day.
You can send Diāochán to Fèngxiān now.
But Lǚ Bù and I are father and son!
It's improper!
I'll ignore his crimes, nevermind them.
You can go reassure him.
Grand Preceptor, you can't be fooled by that woman!
Are you willing to give your concubine to Lǚ Bù or not? Huh?
Do not talk about Diāochán ever again!
Anyone who speaks of this again will be executed!
Yes...!
All of us will die in the hands of that woman!
General! General!
The other day I caught a cold, so I couldn't come out.
That's why I haven't seen you for a long time, General.
Today, the Grand Preceptor rode to Méiwù-manor,
I had to see him off despite my illness.
Why didn't you go with him?
May I ask why you are sighing, General?
Because of your daughter!
After all this time, the Grand Preceptor
still hasn't sent my daughter?
That lech has kept her for himself.
I don't believe it!
Where do I even start!?
Then we discuss this in my humble abode. Let's go!
I never imagined that the Grand Preceptor
could do something this barbaric!
He has not only defiled my daughter,
but took your wife as a concubine, General!
It will be the ridicule of the whole nation!
They are not laughing at
the Grand Preceptor, but at us!
It matters not whether I am
ridiculed as senile or incompetent,
but you're the peerless hero of the realm!
How could you bear such a humiliation and shame?
Apologies for letting these
words slip, please forgive me!
I will kill that senile wretch! Avenge my disgrace!
General, General!
Don't get into trouble!
A real man should stand up
between Heaven and Earth!
How could I submit to him any longer!
If you are a great general,
how could the Grand Preceptor restrain you?
I will butcher that bastard!
General!
Yet I have a father and son bond,
I fear what later generations will say about this.
General, your surname is Lǚ,
but his surname is Dǒng.
Consider this:
At Fèngyí Pavillion, when he threw your halberd at you...
where was the bond then?
Sir, if not for your words, I would be amiss
General, if you can revive the Imperial House of Hàn,
you'll be known as a loyal officer,
and your name will be
immortalized in history!
General, if you aid Dǒng Zhuó...
you'll be known as a traitor,
and go down in history as a byword of infamy!
Pros and cons, advantages and disadvantages.
To be pure or impure, to be loyal or disloyal.
General, please consider this!
Sir, your words have cleared my mind!
I am determined!
Do not doubt me sir!
It's just...
it's just...
it's just that if our plan fails, we will be in trouble!
I swear to revive the Hàn state by killing the national traitor!
If I ever betray my word,
then doom me for all of eternity!
General!
If the House of Hàn doesn't fall, it's thanks to you, General.
Please accept my respects!
Sir,
Does the Excellency of the Masses have any plans to eliminate the traitor?
I'll tell you it when the time has come.
Dǒng Zhuō is far away in Méiwù-manor.
We could send an eloquent man to Méiwù asking him to come to court to discuss matters,
but who to send?
Lǐ Sù was originally one of Dǒng Zhuó's supporters.
He once enticed Lǚ Bù to kill Dīng Yuán
but Dǒng Zhuó did not promote him afterwards.
He harbors a grudge due to this.
If we send Lǐ Sù,
that traitor won't be suspicious.
Please, sires.
Lǐ Sù
Exalted sir,
Please sit.
Please.
Brother Sù, back then, you induced me to kill Dīng Jiànyáng and turn to Dǒng Zhuó.
Now this lech abuses the Emperor
and oppresses the people.
His sins are innumerable and all of us share resentment!
Now the Ducal Minister asks you, Brother Sù,
send an imperial edict to Méiwù biding Dǒng Zhuō to enter the court.
I will pretend to be subservient while the warriors wait within the gates.
By killing this traitor, we would help the Hàn Empire and we'll be known as loyal ministers.
What is your honorable opinion?
Thank you, exalted Excellency of the Masses!
Thank you, General!
I have long wanted to kill that traitor Dǒng!
I only regret I wasn't able to find any allies.
Now we have been
bestowed an opportunity by heaven!
My mind is set!
General, please go straight to Méiwù-manor.
My dear concubine, I dreamt
of a dragon covering my body last night.
Sure enough, good news came today when
the Son of Heaven sent for me to enter the court
and abdicate the throne to me!
Excellency of the Masses Wáng
has already built an abdication platform for me.
They're just waiting for me to accept the throne!
After I become the Son of Heaven,
you will be my favored concubine!
Thank you for your great favor, my lord!
Beautiful girl, you just wait here.
I'll come to take you to the palace soon!
The carriage's wheel broke
and the horse escaped its reins,
what omens do they bode?
My lord, it bodes you will ascend the throne,
abandon the old for the new.
These omens mean you will ride in the Emperor's jade carriage on a golden saddle!
Heavens really blessed me!
The grass spreads a thousand lǐ, how green it is!
Within ten days divine, it won't be alive!
Does that song bode well or ill fortunes?
It bodes the Liú clan will be gone and Dǒng clan will thrive!
Stop singing! Stop singing!
Go play over there!
What's wrong with singing?
Do you know what the song means?
'Thousand lǐ grass' refers to the word 'Dǒng',
'Ten days divine' refers to the word 'Zhuó',
It means that Dǒng Zhuó won't live!
You want to die?!
Heaven blesses us.
My respects, Father!
It's alright! It's alright!
Congratulations, Father!
After I accept the Emperor's abdication,
you will be in charge of all the military forces throughout the world.
Thank you, father!
Why aren't Wáng Yǔn and Lǐ Rú here?
Wáng Yǔn is on the abdication platform waiting for you,
Lǐ Rú caught an illness, so he could not come.
Your son respectfully invites you, father,
to ascend the platform.
Go.
Please.
The traitor scum has arrived!
Summon the warriors!
Where is my son Fèngxiān?
Here is the imperial order! Kill the treacherous vassal Dǒng Zhuó! The rest will be pardoned!
Fèngxiān, my son! Why are you doing this?
Old bastard! We cannot coexist together!
Kill him!
'Traitor Dǒng'
Cheers!
Who says that Méiwù is in the depths of Spring
shuō shénme méiwù chūn shēn
and doesn't know the Will of Heaven and the People,
quán bù xiǎo tiānyì rénxīn
the Abdication Platform has become the gallows,
shòuchántái fǎn chéng liǎo duàntóutái
Where can one find the imperial dream?
dìwáng mèng hé chù xún
away from riches and prestige and people
yuǎnlíle fùguì fán xiāo de
bidding farewell to the struggle between beasts.
Gàobiéle lóngzhēng hǔdòu mén
Forsaking the delicate years of youth,
gūfùle jǐnxiù niánhuá
letting slip away blooming maidenhood
Cuòguòle dòukòu qīngchūn
To repay the Minister's great kindness,
wèi bàodá sītú dàyì shēn ēn
Gave up this body as delicate as a flower and refined as jade.
pīn shě zhè rúhuā sì yù shēn
From now on, you'll never see your daughter's shadow again,
cóng jīnhòu zài bu jiàn ěr de shēnyǐng
and never hear your daughter's voice again,
yě zàibu wén ěr de shēngyīn
Diāochán has drifted away with the cool breeze,
Diāochán yǐ suízhe nà qīngfēng qù
become as like the clouds,
huà zuòle yīpiàn bái yún
Diāochán has drifted away with the cool breeze,
Diāochán yǐ suízhe nà qīngfēng qù
become as like the clouds,
huà zuòle yīpiàn bái yún
yuǎnlíle fùguì fán xiāo de
Away from riches and prestige and people
bidding farewell to the struggle between beasts.
Gàobiéle lóngzhēng hǔdòu mén
Forsaking the delicate years of youth,
gūfùle jǐnxiù niánhuá
letting slip away blooming maidenhood
Cuòguòle dòukòu qīngchūn
To repay the Minister's great kindness,
wèi bàodá sītú dàyì shēn ēn
Gave up this body as delicate as a flower and refined as jade.
pīn shě zhè rúhuā sì yù shēn
From now on, you'll never see your daughter's shadow again,
cóng jīnhòu zài bu jiàn ěr de shēnyǐng
and never hear your daughter's voice again,
yě zàibu wén ěr de shēngyīn
Diāochán has drifted away with the cool breeze,
Diāochán yǐ suízhe nà qīngfēng qù
become as like the clouds,
huà zuòle yīpiàn bái yún
Diāochán has drifted away with the cool breeze,
Diāochán yǐ suízhe nà qīngfēng qù
become as like the clouds,
huà zuòle yīpiàn bái yún
Diāochán has drifted away with the cool breeze,
Diāochán yǐ suízhe nà qīngfēng qù
become as like the clouds.
huà zuòle yīpiàn bái yún