This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 21
The Battle of Guāndù (Part 1)
In the fourth year of Emperor Xiàn's reign of Jiàn'ān,
200 A.D.
Sūn Cè of Eastern Wú died,
and his younger brother, Sūn Quán, succeeded him.
He improved relations with Cáo Cāo
and rejected Yuán Shào's
proposal for an Anti-Cao front.
That August of the next year,
August 201 A.D.
Yuan Shao raised a force of
700,000 to attack Cáo Cāo.
This was the historically famous battle of Guāndù.
Sun Quan may reject my offer,
but what can he do to stop me?
With such a mighty host like this,
who in the world could resist?
Report! Sir, Cáo Cāo has
raised 7,000 men in response.
He has camped at Guāndù, and
already sent his vanguard towards us.
Cáo Āhmán truly overestimates himself!
With only 70,000 petty men, he stands to
defeat our mighty army of 700,000?
Is he not striking a stone with only an egg?
Have the three armies hasten their march!
I will finish this in one battle!
My lord, you cannot be so impetuous!
My army is powerful! Why are you talking like this?
My lord, we are more numerous,
but our morale cannot match theirs! They hold that advantage,
but they have few supplies compared to us!
We should remain here with our abundant supplies.
If we just wait, they will disperse without even a fight.
Should we charge forth? That is what Cáo Cāo wants!
My lord, you need to reconsider this.
Tián Fēng has already hurt our morale and is to be executed!
Our mighty army is about to march, and you
wish to replicate him?! This is most frustrating!
If you fail to take frank advice,
you will be at a disadvantage!
Men, take him away, and behead this disturber!
Jǔ Shòu
沮授
Yes!
Order the three armies out!
If you fail to take frank advice,
you will lose!
My lord, stop this! My lord!
To kill our own before a battle will damage our morale!
Instead imprison him for now, and pass judgment later.
My lord, please heed General Zhāng!
You can pass judgement after we've won.
Put Ju Shou away somewhere.
After I defeat Cáo Cāo, I'll sentence him and Tian Feng together!
Yes!
My lord, if you fail to take frank advice,
you will be at a disadvantage! My lord!
All forces, accelerate your advance! Divide the 700,000 force
into the east and west camps to block off the enemy troops.
Sire, please listen or all will be lost!
Sire, if you fail to listen, you will lose!
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Guō Jiā
Styled: Fèngxiào
Chancellor, why are you still watching?
Yuan Shao came eagerly,
and was supposed to go on the offensive,
but he's using shields as the front-line now.
His intention is to defend.
Yuan Shao is able to defend, but you cannot.
Our men are elite, equal to ten of his.
We must defeat them and shatter their morale.
If we stall, our supplies will run out, and the worst will come.
Chancellor, if you are to use your force of 70,000 to withstand a force of 700,000,
you must act decisively. The slightest hesitation will unnerve our army!
Yuan Shao, before the Emperor,
I petitioned for you to be a Generalissimo,
so why are you rebelling now?
You claim Chancellorship, yet act in treachery!
It would be a sin not to rebel against you!
I am under Imperial order to defeat you!
And I have Their  blessing to destroy you!
Sound the drums!
Release!
Exterminate the traitors!
My lord, Cáo Cāo has fallen back to his camp in Guāndù.
He fled to Guāndù?
Guāndù is the choke-point to Xǔchāng (Xǔdū).
Cáo Cāo seeks to grab my army's very throat with this move
and stop us from advancing to Xǔchāng.
How clever.
Have the three armies to press onward to Guāndù.
Order the troops to harass them.
Do not give Cáo Cāo any breathing room.
If we capture Guāndù, Xǔdū can also be taken.
My lord, I believe we can split 10,000 men to blockade Guāndù.
Have your troops siege them, build dirt towers,
and then to fire into the camps.
Shěn Pèi
Styled: Zhèng Nán
If we constantly harass them thus, and Cáo Cāo retreats in response,
we can seize this choke-point, and Xǔchāng will be within our grasp!
An excellent strategy. Give his order.
All regiments, choose elite troops
and quickly construct dirt towers to trap Cáo Cāo at Guāndù!
Some say Cáo Cāo is a great commander,
but we'll make sure he is unable to advance or retreat.
Yes, sir!
Xún Yōu
Styled: Gōng Dá
Come!
Hurry!
Eat, eat, eat!
Patrol captain, look!
Charge!
Chancellor.
Has Wénruò sent us anything?
Liú Yè
Styled: Ziyáng
The battle at Guāndù has been a stalemate for over a month.
Though both sides have wins and losses,
Yuan Shao has more soldiers and provisions.
If this continues, our army will eventually collapse.
Right now, I've left Xǔdū empty.
If Yuan Shao splits some of his troops to attack Xǔdū,
how then can we resist him?
Since we are at a major disadvantage,
What if I were to leave early...
and prepare my military a proper attack in the future?
I have said much, so why do you say nothing, sir?
Chancellor, I came to suggest the plans for the 'Thunder Mangonel'.
I just didn't want you to...
What?
I just didn't want you to retreat our armies.
Chancellor, think about it. We have 70,000 soldiers
that managed to resist a force of 700,000
at Guāndù for over a month.
Chancellor, you do not have the advantage, but you were never dislodged.
Doesn't this show how paltry Yuan Shao's progress is?
Chancellor!
I have returned from Xǔdū (Xǔchāng), carrying a letter from Xún Yù!
"Yuan Shao knows you have held together at Guāndù"
"and wants to make a last stand"
"Sire has to match with less against more,
"If you cannot do this, weakness will be exploited."
"This moment will decide the fate of all."
"Though (Yuan) Shao's army is grand, he can't use it."
"With your divine-like stratagem, what is there to concern?"
"Our army may be small, but the borders are drawn.
"Grip tightly on the choke-point so they cannot advance."
"The tide will begin to turn, changing in haste."
"To strike at this critical moment is a chance utmost vital."
"The borders are drawn"...
"Grip tightly on the choke-point so they cannot advance"...
"Tide will begin to turn and disarray will happen..."
"To strike at this critical moment is a chance utmost vital."
Indeed, we have no time to lose!
Chancellor, what did sir Xun Yu write for us?
Fortify Guāndù.
Grip tightly on the choke-point so they cannot advance!
But with the conditions before us...
We have already reached an impasse at Guāndù for several months.
As was said, "the tide will begin to turn".
If we persevere, and seize every available opportunity,
then it is just as sir Xun Yu summarized, there will be "changing in haste."
For now, the critical task is to stabilize the military and raise our morale.
Oh right, Zǐyáng had just provided us with a plan.
Sir Zǐyáng?
"Thunder Mangonel Schematic"
Come up!
Put your back to it, let that bastard taste some steel!
But he's two-three hundred feet away!
Chancellor, your orders.
Lǐ Diǎn
Styled: Mànchéng
Release!
Advance!
Who is outside?
Chancellor!
My lord.
We invited ourselves in.
Why are you two covered in dirt?
Chancellor, we managed to spot the enemy digging a hole behind the mountain.
They couldn't beat us openly,
and so now they try with stealth.
The hole was a tunnel dug to sneak in our camp.
Fear not, for Master Liú Yè ordered the camp to surround the hole.
This had the enemy waste their resources on the tunnel.
Chancellor, our provisions are about to run out.
I was just about to write to Wenruo about this matter.
Have him quickly amass grain and transport it here overnight to relieve the troops!
Chancellor, General Xú Huǎng wants to see you.
Chancellor!
Gōngmíng, what is it?
Chancellor, my subordinate, Shǐ Huàn, went on patrol, and captured a spy for the Yuan army.
Xú Huǎng
Styled: Gōngmíng
After interrogation, we found out Yuan Shao ordered General Hán Měng to deliver food.
Han Meng is but a fool!
If we send out a few thousand
light cavalry and intercept him,
we'll sever their supply line and disrupt their army.
Good. Gōngmíng, you can lead your personal forces out first,
I'll order Zhāng Liáo and Xǔ Chǔ to reinforce you shortly after.
Once you seize Yuan Shao's food, if he orders soldiers to rescue it,
put your troops in two spots,
and crush him in a pincer attack!
I will prepare immediately! I take my leave.
Hurry up! We must arrive at the main camp before daybreak!
Who's the officer before us?
Oh, it's just Generals Zhāng and Gāo.
If you'd arrived just a bit earlier,
how could the food have been seized?
If not for the seizure of the food and the report of the defeated,
how could our lord have us rescue you?
Alright, now quiet! While Xu Huang is still close by, let's kill him.
Very good!
General, look!
You two, stabilize the formation! I'll meet him!
Damn it! We've been surrounded!
You had your supplies seized,
yet you still have no shame to see me?
Men!
Here!
Take him, and behead him!
Yes!
My lord!
My lord, our supplies was just seized, so our morale is shaken.
Wouldn't killing our own officer worsen it?
My lord.
My lord, General Han has fought fiercely for us before,
This is Cáo Cāo's doing.
Spare him, and let him redeem himself.
Please, my lord, spare him.
I will show mercy on you.
Get out of my sight, now!
Thank you my lord!
Now that our supplies have been stolen,
do any of you know how to respond?
My lord, all our grain is stored at Wūcháo.
We must send forces there to prevent any unforeseen events.
I have already planned that out. You'll go to Yèdū to supervise the supply lines.
Ensure the supply line is maintained so our armies will not lack grain.
Yes, I obey!
Chúnyú Qióng?
Here!
Wūcháo is our main granary, therefore we'll need heavy forces to protect it.
You will lead the forces towards Wūcháo. Make sure to defend it carefully.
Do not fail me.
Chúnyú Qióng
Styled: Zhòngjiān
Yes!
My lord!
What is it?
Jǔ Shòu wants to talk to you about an urgent matter!
No!
Jǔ Shòu says it's a critical military matter!
I don't care how critical it is!
Yes!
Sir, you're in shackles and stocks, no longer a strategist by our lord's side.
Please, tell me what happened quickly, and I will reward you.
I'm only a simple soldier. How could I take such a gift?
If you wish to listen, I'll just talk.
General Han Meng was escorting our grain, when he was intercepted en route, and lost the grain.
Our lord has sent Master Shěn to Yèdū to supervise the supply line.
He also sent Chunyu Qiong to defend Wūcháo.
Sir, what is wrong? Sir?
You need to tell our lord that a calamity is coming!
My lord, I have something to say, and I hope you let me say it.
There's nothing happening today, so I can humor you.
How can you say there's nothing happening? Disaster's about to strike!
My lord, I have followed you for many years.
And now, on the verge of disaster,
I beg you to just listen to me!
It's because you've served me for years that you get to see me at all.
Rise quickly and say what's on your mind.
Yes.
My lord,
in matters of war, the supplies are important.
Do I need you to remind me?
But my lord, though it's such a critical matter, you've barely given thought to it!
How so?
Han Meng's provisions have been stolen,
and Wūcháo is in grave danger!
I already sent Chunyu Qiong to guard it, heavily.
My lord, the problem is exactly that!
You are still in prison.
Military matters are none of your concern!
It is common knowledge to prioritize supplies in war!
I've dispatched troops to defend it a long time ago!
My lord, that Chúnyú Qióng loves alcohol like his own life.
He drinks so much that he has no thoughts and no plans.
The whole day, he looks haggard!
With such a dolt, the most incompetent among all,
how could you entrust such a great responsibility to him, my lord!
Men...
Yes?
Take this brazen fool and throw him in prison!
Move!
Add more shackles to him!
Sire! Sire
Nobody release him without my explicit orders!
Yes sir!
I risked death to warn you of an eminent disaster!
You must come to your senses!
Sire!
Move!
I want his guard put to death!
Have somebody else replace him!
Yes!
Who is that? Where are you taking him?
Xǔ Yōu
Styled: Zǐyuǎn
To answer, Master Xǔ,
the patrols have captured this suspicious person just now.
He claims to be a merchant,
but we've found a secret letter from Cáo Cāo to Xǔchāng on him,
so we're taking him to the main camp to report to our lord.
An enemy spy?
Where's the letter? Let me see!
Such a military matter will be reported by me to our lord personally!
In this battle, we must obliterate Cáo Cāo at Guāndù.
So?
My lord! My lord! Great news, such great news!
What great news would have you, sir, so elated?
It's indeed great news!
We'll destroy Cáo Cāo in one battle!
Please, Mister Xu, tell me more!
My lord, we take our leave!
Sit.
Mister Xu, please explain.
My lord, Cáo Cāo has maintained his army at Guāndù to oppose us for a long time.
With this, Xǔchāng is unguarded!
If we divide our army to raid Xǔchāng at night,
then Xǔchāng can be captured, and Cáo Cāo can, too!
Master Xu, how do you know they are running out of supplies?
A patrol captured one of his spies.
This is a letter from Cáo Cāo to Xǔchāng, urging for supplies.
Pass it.
Cáo Cāo is full of dastardly schemes.
Perhaps this letter is a trap.
My lord,
if we do not take Xǔchāng right now,
it will harm us in the future.
While Cáo Cāo is indeed devious, this letter cannot be discredited.
My lord, you cannot waste this opportunity!
I swear my life on this!
How can you be sure that this isn't one of Cáo Cāo's tricks?
Mister Xu, how do you know
Cáo Cāo's thoughts in such a way?
My lord...
Speak!
In important matters, how could I dare fool around?
Cáo Cāo's letter was very clear!
With his supplies running low, his army's about to collapse!
Guāndù can no longer be maintained. How could this be false?
My lord!
My lord, Master Shen Pei has a letter for you from Yè Commandery.
Read it.
Yes!
"As ordered, I have supervised the provisions for the Yè army in Háncāo."
"They are prepared and will arrive soon, assuaging your worries."
"My lord, there is another issue. When Xǔ Yōu..."
Continue
Yes!
"When Xǔ Yōu served in Jì Province,
he plundered people's property."
"Furthermore, he had his nephews embezzle taxes and food."
"Thus, I already arrested them."
My lord, these are Shen Pei's libels.
My lord, do not trust his words at all!
You are one devious idiot!
How could you face yourself
after presenting your plan to me!
I'm well aware that you and Cáo Cāo are old friends.
Is it not that you were bribed by him?
You tried to deceive me in dividing my troops to get me defeated!
I... I...
Mister Xu, what is this!?
Shen Pei is slandering me! Shen Pei is slandering me!
I should have beheaded you.
And now I have the authority to do so!
Guards?
Here!
Drag him out! Drag him out!
Yes!
You cannot let him see me again!
Shen Pei is slandering me...
Getting offended over honest advice, these petty men don't deserve it!
Yuan Shao refuses to accept loyal words, for that Cáo Cāo will defeat him.
Then why not surrender to Cáo Cāo?
Damn animals, there's not enough for us yet you waste all your food.
If you weren't our lord's horse...
Halt!
Please report to the Chancellor. The patrols found this gentleman.
He says he needs to talk with the Chancellor.
The Chancellor was busy all night planning with his generals.
He just went to sleep. Report to him after he wakes.
This fellow says it's an urgent
matter, and it can't be delayed!
Did I stutter?
The Chancellor is asleep. Who'd dare awaken him?
Mengde!
Who's shouting!?
Xǔ Yōu of Nányáng has come!
Good. Very good!
Sir, you are the Chancellor while I am commoner. You don't have to be polite.
No, no, no! Come, come, come!
We're just friends, so why mention our ranks?
Come! Come! Hurry up! Hurry up!
Come!
After you!