This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Romance of the Three Kingdoms
Gǔngǔn chángjiāng dōng shì shuǐ
The rolling Long River flows eastward,
Lànghuā táo jǐn yīngxióng
flowers wash away like past heroes.
Shìfēi chéngbài zhuǎn tóu kōng
Their rights and wrongs, victories and defeats,
all fade into nothing.
Qīngshān yījiù zài
Yet the verdant hills stand as they did before,
Jǐ dù xīyáng hóng
beneath countless rosy sunsets.
Bái fà yú qiáo jiāng zhǔ shàng
White-haired fisherman and
lumberjacks on the banks,
Guàn kàn qiūyuè chūnfēng
familiarized with the
autumn moons and the spring breezes.
Yī hú zhuó jiǔ xǐ xiāngféng
With a turbid bottle of wine, they merrily assemble.
Gǔjīn duōshǎo shì
The countless tales of present and past
Jiē fù xiào tán zhōng
all in their jests.
Yī hú zhuó jiǔ xǐ xiāngféng
With a turbid bottle of wine, they merrily assemble.
Gǔjīn duōshǎo shì
The countless tales of present and past
Jiē fù xiào tán zhōng
all in their jests.
Act 1
Deer-Hunt of Lords
Episode 1
Oath of the Peach Garden
As ancient adage dictates:
The world under heaven,
Long divided, must unite.
Long united, must divide.
Note: 771 BC – 476 BC
In the times of Spring and Autumn,
five hegemons strove for supremacy.
Note: 475 BC – 221 BC
In the times of Warring States,
seven kingdoms clashed.
After five centuries of strife, they were quelled and united under Qín.
After the Qín fell,
two rival nations arose: Chǔ and Hàn.
Thus all were once again
united under the Hàn.
In the 2nd year of Zhānghe
of the Eastern Hàn dynasty,
Note: 88 AD
the ten-year-old Emperor Hé of Hàn
ascended the throne.
With the help of eunuchs, he was able
to depose Empress Dowager Dòu
along with her elder brother,
Generalissimo Dòu Xiàn.
Eunuchs became a part of government function,
thus their domination marked the
beginning of the end for the Hàn.
Long live!
Long live His Majesty!
Emperor Hé of Hàn
Long live!
Long live His Majesty!
Over the next few decades,
contentions rose as the eunuchs amassed more power.
Emperor Shāng of Hàn
Emperor Shāng of Hàn,
Emperor Ān
Emperor Ān,
Emperor Shùn
Emperor Shùn,
Emperor Chōng
Emperor Chōng,
Emperor Zhì
Emperor Zhì,
Emperor Huán
Emperor Huán and Emperor Líng.
Emperors' deposition became constant
and the court's power withered away.
With this, local gentry became despots, extorting the people
and annexing land as natural
disasters ravaged the country.
The common people were on a knife's edge,
living in torment by desolation and starvation.
The Old Heaven is dead!
Zhāng Jiǎo
The Yellow Heaven shall rise!
On the year of Jiǎzǐ,
All shall prosper!
Driven to the brink, the people could only rebel.
The Yellow Turban Rebellion
Countless starving people rose high their flags, for one last, desperate push against fate.
Finally in the first month of
the seventh year of Guānghé,
Note: January 184 AD
the Yellow Turban Rebellion broke out.
They burned local government buildings,
murdered officials, and occupied cities.
War quickly broke out throughout the empire.
Within ten days,
news of the rebellion had spread.
The empire was hurled into chaos.
Hé Jìn
Styled: Suìgāo
Your Majesty, the Yellow Turbans are powerful and the Imperial Army is weak.
Permit the provinces to raise their own troops for defense.
Emperor Líng
I-I'll leave it to you,
Generalissimo!
Appoint generals to levy troops
to suppress the rebels.
Make it so.
Thank you, Your Majesty!
Administrator Liú Yān of Yōu Province
hereby announces to the public:
"The Yellow Turbans have rebelled against His Majesty."
"They are now invading
the lands of Yōu Province,"
"causing harm and
corrupting the common people."
"Local guardsmen are ill-prepared and inadequate to defend the province."
"With Heavens' mandate, His Majesty hath decreed:"
"Recruit strong and loyal
men from all four corners"
"to reinforce the army
and protect the people."
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
You are a man, aren't you?
The nation is in turmoil and all you do is sigh!
The market is open!
Butcher Zhāng?
Butcher Zhāng!
Hey, coming, coming.
Sir, I'm sorry. I'm afraid you
won't be able to eat meat today.
You’re here, aren’t you?
Cut me some meat.
How can I sell the meat
if my boss isn't here?
I don't care.
You sell meat, I'll buy the meat.
I have the money, just give it!
Go find Butcher Zhāng!
I dare not disturb him,
you go find him yourself.
What's so difficult about slaughtering a pig?
Get your boss!
Brother, this is your business.
Why be afraid?
Just sell the meat.
Well, you sell it then.
I can't do it.
You see.
The meat is in the well,
but I can't get it out.
I can't get it out.
Why not just move the millstone aside?
Move it?
Go ahead, move the millstone then.
I'll let you know my boss
promised earlier that
whoever can move this millstone, can keep the meat inside.
Go on!
Move it and the meat is yours!
Isn't your boss going to lose his money?
Well, if you can't move the millstone, then quit running your mouth!
It's the boss' business if there's money made or lost.
Step back!
Yeah! Good work, my friend! Move it!
Where do you want it?
Uh, put it back in place!
Hold up!
Sir... powerful sir,
what will you do?
Cut the meat into small pieces.
Distribute it to everyone.
Distribute?
The meat belongs to me now.
Just do it.
Sure! I'll get right on it!
Come one, everyone, get you some meat.
Everyone, this meat is on me. Take a piece, please.
Go, go. Get me a piece, take it.
You were here to buy meat
so you must pay.
If others can take
some,why can't I?
I-I can't take it anymore!
Pass me money, pass me money!
I'll pay! Sir, here's your payment!
Where is he? Where?
Over here, right here.
That's him.
He's there, good!
Fresh green beans,
want to buy some?
What green beans?
This is clearly flour!
I sell fine products at a fair price.
It's nothing but flour!
Are you buying or milling?
If you're not buying, stop messing with them.
You get mad over a couple of beans!
Didn't you give away all my pork?
So you've come for a fight?
You're the one I want to hit!
If I want to make a name for myself,
wouldn't these two men be good companions?
He's really extraordinary.
This guy’s also a real man.
You two heroes have excellent martial arts.
It's admirable, really admirable!
That's too much.
Hey, I heard you lifted the millstone,
so I came here to see you myself,
that's what I was about.
Oh? I thought you came
demanding money for the pork.
That little piece of pork?
Not worth mentioning.
Come on!
Why don’t you two come to my place for a drink?
It's about to rain.
Let's take shelter at your place.
Please!
I'm Zhāng Fēi styled Yìdé!
I love making friends with heroes from all over.
Today, I'm lucky to meet two new heroes!
It really puts me in a good mood.
After you?
Come, come! After you!
Come on, bring wine!
I'm Guān Yǔ, styled Yúnchǎng,
from Jiěliáng of Hédōng,
Note: Style names are given upon reaching adulthood. They're used as a form of respect between
people of the same generation.
I'm Liú Bèi, styled Xuándé.
You first.
We three met by chance but feel familiar straight away.
After you!
After you.
Sit. Sit. Have a seat.
I've noticed you two are no ordinary men.
Currently the Yellow Turbans are running rampant.
The realm is in chaos.
It's the time for heroes to rise.
I wonder if you two heroes have a plan?
One day, back in Jiěliáng,
I couldn't tolerate a local despot oppressing the locals,
so in a fit of anger, I killed him.
I was forced to roam the jiānghú. It's been five or six years since the killing.
Note: The martial arts sub-culture that exist
on the fringes of society.
I have many skills.
I want to put them to use,
but in all my travels, I've found no opportunity to serve the country.
What's wrong with killing?
I hate that I haven't killed
all the villains in the world!
I saw the recruitment notice
at the city gate today.
I intend to enlist in the army, to test my sword and meet destiny on the battlefield.
Even if I die on the battlefield,
I will die as a true and valiant man.
Yeah!
That's what a man ought to do.
I'll enlist with you.
What do you say?
Will you enlist with us?
What’s with the long sigh?
Are you implying that men
shouldn't help their country?
Right now, it is a time of chaos,
heroes emerge in troubled times.
For heroes such as you two,
it is the time to show your valor.
But why must you subject
yourselves to serve others?
Don't you see?
These times will create heroes,
and those heroes will influence the times.
Now the Yellow Turbans are in rebellion
and the world has responded.
The court has ordered provinces to raise troops
because they are weak,
with leaderless, feeble troops.
Also, the eunuchs continue to interfere.
Because of these things,
there is bound to be
another rebellion against tyranny.
When the Yellow Turban Rebellion is crushed,
the heroes of the times
will surely rise up as well.
Which hero will be the one
to hold power under heaven then?
No one knows for sure!
Hearing your speech is worth more
than ten years of books!
It's admirable, really admirable!
I’m just a pig butcher.
I don't know what's
happening in the world.
You just tell me what I should do.
Why are you so hesitant?
There is a man who was
originally a scion of the Hàn dynasty.
His ancestor, Prince Jìng of Zhōngshān, was the 7th son of Emperor Xiàojǐng.
When his ancestor,
the Marquis of Zhuōlù,
failed to pay his annual
tribute to his ancestors,
he was stripped of his rank.
A branch of his family
headed out to the countryside
and settled down in Lóusāng Village.
Lóusāng Village? I know of it!
There's a thousand-year-old
mulberry tree there!
The tree is tall and crowned.
Hence the name, Lóusāng Village.
Note: Lóusāng literally means 'giant mulberry'
I also heard people saying
the mulberry tree shelters a nobleman!
Yes, I'm familiar with this saying.
However, for the last ten generations
the descendants of this family
have been impoverished.
There's nothing but bare walls.
As an imperial scion,
why doesn't he restore
his family's honor and rank?
He began wandering at age 15, seeking teachers and making friends.
He often thought of serving the state
and championing the people,
but now he's 28 and has achieved nothing.
In the end, all his
aspirations will be spent in vain,
a heart full of tears.
Who are you talking about?
To tell you the truth...
It's the man before you.
Why didn't you say it earlier?
That nobleman is right before me?
Brother Liú you say it,
and old Zhāng will do it!
Say it!
I want to recruit local champions
and punish villains,
only I don't have the resources.
What's the problem?
I have the money.
I'm willing to do something for the people.
Are you serious?
I always speak the truth!
Alright!
Please!
A single thread cannot make a rope.
A single tree doesn't make a forest.
I'm weak and can't do it alone.
If you don't give up,
I would gladly follow you!
You two are like charcoal during a snowstorm!
It's too generous of you two.
Liú Bèi pays his respects.
What's that for?
Brother Liú,
you don't have to do that!
Wanting to achieve great deeds,
I've wandered about half my life
searching for like-minded
people, until today.
After washing away the sand,
I've finally discovered gold!
Destiny has brought us together.
I'm prepared to swear an oath of brotherhood
with you two, sharing life and death.
How do you two feel about that?
I've also thought of this!
So long as we three share heart
and mind, clay can be changed to gold.
Together,You have me with you,
we'll accomplish great deeds.
Although I'm just a fighter,
I understand honor and loyalty.
As the adage goes,
"a good bird chooses a good tree to perch on,"
"and a good man chooses
a worthy lord to serve."
My life's wish is fulfilled.
From now on, my life is tied to yours.
My flesh is your flesh.
I'm fully committed!
Same with me!
I swear to go through thick and thin with you!
I'll be your companion through life or death.
Same with me!
If my words are false,
may heaven strike me down.
Same with me!
Elder Brother!
Second Brother!
Third Brother!
Though not born on the same day,
same month or same year.
We seek to die on the same date,
same month and same year.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Chūnfēngdéyì zhīyīn,
A chance encounter that makes us oathsworn.
táohuā yě hánxiào yìng jì tái.
Peach blossoms bloom before the altar.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Bǎoguó ān bāng zhì kāngkǎi,
Defend the nation to bring peace and magnanimity,
jiànguó lìyè zhǎnxióng cái.
Build a grand cause through our talents and deeds.
Zhǎnxióng cái
Our talents and deeds.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Zhōng gān yì dǎn,
Remain loyal and always brave,
huànnàn xiāng suí shì bù fēnkāi.
never parting despite hardships and suffering.
Zhè yī bài
We swear this oath.
Shēngsǐ bù gǎi,
Life or death, never give up,
tiāndì rì yuè zhuàng wǒ qínghuái.
Heaven and Earth, let my resolve
be as strong as the Sun and Moon.
Cháng máo zài shǒu!
Long spears in hand!
Dāojiàn shēng huī!
Swords so brilliant!
Kàn wǒ dìxiōng!
Look my brothers!
Yíngzhe fēngyān dà bù lái.
The battlefield calls us, heed the call.
Cháng máo zài shǒu!
Long spears in hand!
Dāojiàn shēng huī!
Swords so brilliant!
Kàn wǒ dìxiōng!
Look my brothers!
Yíngzhe fēngyān dà bù lái.
The battlefield calls us, heed the call.
Cháng máo zài shǒu.
Long spears in hand!
Dāojiàn shēng huī!
Swords so brilliant.
Kàn wǒ dìxiōng!
Look my brothers!
Yíngzhe fēngyān dà bù lái!
The battlefield calls us, heed the call!
Sūn Jiān
Styled: Wéntái
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Dǒng Zhuó
Styled: Zhòngyǐng
Where are you running, rebel!?
Thank you, heroes, for saving me!
I'll remember it for the rest of my life.
May I ask what positions
you three currently hold?
We are commoners.
Commoners?
Elder brother, you can't just...?
So annoying!
Third Brother, don't bother Elder Brother.
You achieved so much,
yet were rewarded with a
lowly magistrate post in Ānxǐ county.
That Sūn Jiān just curried favor
with the higher-ups and was made a major.
What for?
That stinking imperial court,
it deserves its rebellions!
Third Brother, watch your tongue.
He's a commander of
the imperial court, don't be rash.
And what about that Dǒng Zhuó! He did nothing, yet received a good magistrate position!
By connecting with wealthy men
and bribing the Ten Attendants,
Note: The Ten Attendants are the faction of eunuchs that control the Imperial Court.
That day on the battlefield,
remember what he was like?
Trying to flee like a coward!
If it wasn't for us...
If it was up to me,
I'd kill him myself!
Elder Brother, say something!
The County Inspector
Are you the new magistrate of this county?
Yes.
What's your name?
Liú Bèi.
Ah, Liú Bèi?
What's your background?
I'm descended from Emperor Xiàojǐng
through Prince Jìng of Zhōngshān.
So you're a scion of the Hàn dynasty?
Yes.
Pardon me for lacking manners, my good sir.
That's not necessary.
Since you're an imperial clansman,
please do sit down, good sir. Let's talk.
Thank you.
Liú Bèi,
since you're an imperial scion, may I ask
why are you holding such a
lowly post as a county magistrate?
Regardless of my post,
I'll do my best to help the court.
Who recommended you to take this post, sir?
I started recruiting within Zhuō commandery to suppress the Yellow Turbans.
I have been in more than thirty battles.
For my humble merits,
I was rewarded with this post.
You've got to find a big tree
to lean on in the court,
then you can lie low in the shade.
Then again, it's fairly easy being a lowly official.
It's harder for those higher on the ladder.
Whenever you want to do
something, you need to pay up.
I'm an honest official, I've never committed any offense against the people.
Not the slightest offense?
Really?
I dare not deceive you.
Since you're so confident
Magistrate Liú, I'd still like to check into it.
Elder Brother, how was it?
Did the Inspector trouble you, Elder Brother?
It's alright.
That's good.
He didn't ask for a bribe?
Not outright, but he was hinting at it.
But I turned a deaf ear to him.
I could never exploit or mistreat the people. How could I afford to bribe him?
Even if you had money, don't give it to him!
We'll see what he'll do next.
Magistrate Liú,
you're wanted by the Inspector.
What? The Inspector again?
Damned bureaucrat, merely a bully
leaning on the powerful. Don't go!
The Inspector must be plotting something.
Best be careful.
You're right, the Inspector
must be harboring evil intentions.
I'll go anyway.
Yúnchǎng, Third Brother,
you two wait for me at home.
After you.
What's your name?
Liú Bèi.
What's your background?
I'm descended from Emperor Xiàojǐng through Prince Jìng of Zhōngshān.
Outrageous!
You dare pretend to be an imperial scion?
I wouldn't dare pretend!
You dare answer back?
How did you get this post,
how much did you pay in bribes?
Hurry up! Tell the truth!
I started recruiting in Zhuō county to suppress the Yellow Turbans.
I've been in more than thirty battles. For my humble merits, I was rewarded with this post.
How dare you lie about your feats!
I lied about nothing!
It's my duty to clean up
corrupt officials like you!
Then do investigate!
Leave now. If I find any wrongdoing, you'll be sorry!
I take my leave!
This Liú Bèi is so stubborn.
Inspector, as the saying goes,
"a thief bites down to the bone."
Note: This saying means that bad or wronged people will be vindictive.
The Inspector announces
a a hearing in three days.
During these three days, anyone
who is dissatisfied with the magistrate,
has experienced injustice, corruption, or has any evidence of crimes done against the people
will be the first to be heard.
The Inspector will protect you.
You don't have to be afraid.
Hey, do you hear me?
Take revenge for the injustices done to you.
Good sir,
since Magistrate Liú took office,
he's committed no misdeeds.
He loves the common people.
He has done no misdeeds.
Yeah, he's done nothing wrong.
Did he privately threaten you?
Nothing like that, absolutely not.
Ignorant peasants!
Elder Brother, the Inspector is
deliberately trying to frame you.
Let me go beat him and run him
out of Ānxǐ county. It'll be easy.
Third brother, don't be so reckless.
Damn!
Can't beat him, can't even curse him!
I can't stand it!
Third Brother!
Where are you going?
I can't stand it here!
I'm going for a walk.
Third Brother,
don't be reckless.
Damn!
Elder Brother,
I'm going outside the city to ride my horse.
Alright,
but only outside the city.
Understood.
Magistrate Liú, please.
Master Zhāng, the Inspector has been
intimidating us to turn against Lord Liú.
Master Zhāng, we went to petition on behalf of Lord Liú,
but the Inspector wouldn't let us in
and he even beat us.
Elder Brother!
You bureaucrat cur, where's my Elder Brother!?
You bureaucrat cur!
Go!
Save me! Save me!
You cur! I should beat you to death!
Third Brother, stop!
Lord Xuándé, save me!
Killing this scumbag would be a good deed!
Third Brother!
Inspector, my Elder Brother
has been nothing but dutiful!
He's honest and cares for
the people like his own children!
Why do you try to harm him?
You only know how to steal money and ask for bribes!
Clearly it's you who's the corrupt one!
My Elder Brother is innocent.
Where would he have the money for bribes?
You sell positions and
confiscate property on false charges.
You deserve this punishment!
Lord Xuándé, sirs, sirs,
spare my life! Spare me!
Elder Brother, you've achieved so much on the battlefield,
yet only got to be a county magistrate.
And now, you get slandered by this Inspector.
This place is a thorn bush,
not fit for a phoenix to perch on.
Better to kill him, resign this post,
then head out for a new opportunity!
Forgive me! I'll never do it again!
Those above forced me into it!
Subordinates follow their superiors!
Inspector! You tried to frame the honest
and you tried to harm the people.
You deserve to be put down like a dog,
but I will spare you this once.
Thank you for your favor, Lord Xuándé!
My post...
Note: Stamp seals represent government positions, and were required for decisions to be legal.
you may keep it.
Lord Liú, please don't go!
To avoid prosecution,
Liú Bèi and his two brothers
became captains under Liú Yu.
After Gōngsūn Zàn mentioned Liú's previous achievements,
he was promoted to major for the Píngyuán county magistrate.
There he gradually regrouped his old forces.