This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 4
Mèngdé presents a blade
Wáng Yǔn
Styled: Zishī
Yuán Shào heard at Bóhǎi that
Dǒng Zhuó was abusing his authority,
so he wrote a confidential letter to Wáng Yǔn,
plotting to assassinate Dǒng Zhuó.
Gentlemen, please take your seats. Do so.
Today is my birthday.
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
All of you...
are old ministers who
served the Imperial Court.
I... I...
Your Excellency, why are you crying on your birthday?
Yes!
The truth is,
today is actually not my birthday.
Eh?
I only wanted to have a meeting with you all,
because I feared
Dǒng Zhuó would get suspicious.
so I made this excuse, that's all.
Oh... so that was the real intention...
Dǒng Zhuó insults His Majesty, abuses his power,
and endangered the nation's spirits many times.
Who would have thought
that the empire founded by Emperor Gāozǔ,
who defeated Qín and Chǔ,
which shelters us as of now
would fall at the hands of Dǒng Zhuó?
Mèngdé, why are you laughing?
All you grand ministers do is
wail from dusk to dawn and dawn to dusk, heh.
You think crying can kill Dǒng Zhuó?
Cáo Mèngdé!
Your ancestors too enjoyed the Hàn Empire's favor!
But you don't think of serving the nation...
Instead you are laughing at us!
What is your reason!?
I don't laugh at anything else
but at you folks, for not coming up
with a single plan to kill Dǒng Zhuó.
What do you propose?
Although I am untalented,
I am willing to cut off Dǒng Zhuó's head
and hang it on the capital city's gate
to appease the realm!
Mèngdé, what is your plan?
Come; follow me.
Please look.
Běnchū's writing in this
letter is very passionate.
But...
But what?
he is hiding far away at Bóhǎi.
It is easy for him to order people to do what he dares not.
What do you suggest?
I can get rid of Dǒng Zhuó without a single soldier.
Sir, I heard that you have
the Seven Star dagger in your possession.
It moves like the wind
and cuts iron like hair.
Its blade is peerless.
Are you going to follow Wǔ Fú's example and kill the traitor?
Won't do. Won't do.
You must learn from the past!
Why are you laughing?
Assassinating the tyrant is easier said than done.
That traitor has armored
bodyguards wherever he goes to.
He also has that lackey, Lǚ Bù,
who never leaves his side.
Impossible.
Impossible!
Sir, your concerns are not necessarily wrong,
but not necessarily right either.
Why so?
Dǒng Zhuó is blunt yet boorish.
Before, Wǔ Fú's assassination failed and he lost his life.
Dǒng Zhuó killed him as an example to others
and no one else dared to try what Wǔ Fú did.
But things are different now.
While it has failed in the past, this time it may not.
That being said, it's still difficult.
It goes without saying
that the traitor's heart is distrustful.
But who is he distrustful of?
Without a doubt it is his enemies.
Note: Yào Lí was an assassin of Wú hired to kill Prince Qìngjì of Wú during the Spring and Autumn period.
In the past, Yào Lí assassinated Qìngjì.
Even 10,000 people could
not match up to Qìngjì's bravery,
yet Yào Lí was handicapped.
How was he able to succeed?
Because Qìngjì trusted Yào Lí.
Right right right!
His confidant assassinated him.
It is very hard to defend
yourself against your confidant!
I have been serving Dǒng Zhuó recently,
and I have gained his trust.
He consults me on all matters, big or small.
I have become so close with Dǒng Zhuó
that I can enter and leave his residence freely.
If I have the Seven Star dagger,
I can wait for a chance to assassinate the bastard.
Success is guaranteed!
Mèngdé, you are a devoted official.
The Empire is very fortunate to have you!
Please accept my respects.
By the gods of Heaven and Earth,
your servant, the Colonel
of Valiant Cavalry; Cáo Cāo,
will assassinate the evil traitor Dǒng Zhuó
to appease the Imperial Court, the state,
the world, and the people.
I will go through fire and water, risk life and limb, and stop at nothing!
Brother Rú, where are you going?
Mèngdé, the Premier of State is in the small pavilion.
You may enter.
Thanks.
Who is it?
It's me.
Oh, it's you.
Why is it so quiet today in the Premier's mansion?
The Premier is resting at the pavilion in the garden.
The servants are having this day off.
If you wish to see him,
you will have to find the way yourself.
Ah, then please have some rest.
Where are you going?
You are still running.
Salutations, Premier.
Dǒng Zhuó
Styled: Zhòngyǐng
Mèngdé,
why are you late today?
My horse is frail and it couldn't endure the travel. That's why I'm late.
Well why didn't you tell me sooner?
How can an officer not have a good horse?
Fèngxiān!
Lǚ Bù
Styled: Fèngxiān
Go and pick out a good Xīliáng horse!
and give it to Mèngdé.
Yes.
Thank you, Premier!
It's nothing.
Sir, you have shown me great kindness.
This bastard is strong.
I can't underestimate him.
Premier.
I feel a little tired.
Then please rest, sir.
I will watch over you.
Mèngdé, what are you doing?
Your servant Cáo offers you
the Seven Star dagger, sir!
This is a fine blade.
A fine blade indeed.
Fèngxiān,
take it.
Come. Come. Come.
Let's see which horse Fèngxiān chose for you.
This is a good horse.
Indeed, it is a good horse!
I am very grateful for this fine horse.
This horse is quite spirited;
you must be careful.
Yes, I will be.
Father.
Just then, I think Cáo Cāo
was trying to assassinate you.
I had my doubts too.
The Premier is in the pavilion.
You may enter.
Lǐ Rú
Could it be
that when you caught him,
he pretended to present the blade?
Premier,
Cáo Cāo has no family within
the capital and lives alone.
We can send someone to summon him,
and if he shows up,
then he meant to present the blade to you.
If he does not,
then he meant to assassinate you.
Send someone to summon him.
Premier,
Cáo Cāo really wanted to assassinate you.
Cáo Cāo never returned home.
He rode his horse to the east gate,
told the guard there
that he was sent by the
Premier on urgent business,
and rode out of the city.
I valued him,
but he meant to kill me!
Premier,
there might be accomplices to this plot.
Accomplices?
Arrest this traitor. Find his accomplices!
As you wish.
Prime Minister, we should quickly distribute
wanted posters to arrest the traitor Cáo Cāo.
Out of the way!
Get on the horse.
Isn't that nice?
Uncle, what's that?
Sit straight. Don't move.
Uncle, isn't that you?
Arrest him!
Why are you arresting me?
You got the wrong man!
Let me go!
You've got it wrong!
I'm just a merchant passing by!
My surname is Huángfǔ. Let me go!
Chén Gōng
Styled: Gōngtái
Hurry up and let me go!
To hand him over and be rewarded,
or to let him go?
If I hand him over to Dǒng
Zhuó the realm will curse me.
If I release him, my career will be...
You do somewhat
bear a resemblance.
Correct, but there are many
people who resemble each other.
You made a mistake by arresting me, and I don't blame you.
Just hurry and let me go!
For now, imprison him.
You've got the wrong man!
Hurry up and let me go!
Let me go!
You got the wrong man!
Hurry up and let me go!
The wrong man!
Cáo Cāo.
You must be mistaken.
My surname is Huángfǔ.
Why must you hide your identity?
When I went to Luòyáng to seek
a government post in the past,
I happened to meet you, Cáo Cāo.
I heard the Premier treated you very well.
Why did you invite trouble for yourself?
A sparrow cannot understand the aspirations of a swan!
You compare yourself to a swan,
but how can you know the others are sparrows?
Stop blabbering!
Now that you've caught me, hand me over and claim your prize!
How did you know I was going to?
Treasures and a title of a marquis.
Is that not enough?
It's a lot for a small magistrate like me.
Quite a lot, indeed.
Becoming a marquis is something
I never would have dreamed of.
However,
I could have sent you to the capital today and be rewarded for my service.
But then why
did I imprison you for now
and not reveal your identity?
Could it be that you're going to release me?
How can you be sure I will release you?
Then what are you going to do to me!
I was just asking!
The Premier trusted you,
but you attempted to assassinate him.
What is the reason for this?
For generations, my family was favored by the Hàn Empire.
If I turned from my country,
how would I differ from a beast?
That's why I bowed down to Dǒng Zhuó.
It was to find a chance to kill the bastard.
Yet now I would fail and my efforts are for naught.
But alas, perhaps this is the will of Heaven.
Then, where will you go?
I will return to my hometown and issue an edict
calling all the lords of the
realm to march against Dǒng Zhuó!
An expedition?
Against Dǒng Zhuó in support of the Hàn!
Please sit, accept my respects!
Your prisoner does not dare
to accept such a virtue.
Please sit.
I dare not sit first.
Please.
I don't know where your hometown is.
My father and his family are
all live in Dōng commandery.
My wife and children also reside in Dōng commandery!
So you and I are fellow townsmen?
May I ask your name?
My surname is Chén and my
forename is Gōng, styled Gōngtái.
After you return home,
how are you going to rally the lords of the realm?
Now, the realm is in chaos and all the lords are beginning to rise up.
After I return home,
I will use all my family's wealth to conscript an army.
I am good friends with Yuán Shào,
styled Běnchū, of Jìzhōu.
His family has served the
nation for many generations.
He has deep connections
with the nobles of the realm,
so I can cooperate with him to call an expedition against Dǒng Zhuó and save the royal family.
I am sure they will respond.
Good.
Dǒng Zhuó runs amok and is
a calamity for the state and the people;
the whole realm wants to get rid of him.
You're following the will of heaven and the people.
You will surely succeed in your undertaking.
However, at the moment...
Do you think I would have
handed you over for a reward?
I, Chén Gōng, am not just a petty official,
but I've never met a worthy master.
I'm deeply moved by your loyalty
towards the nation and the people.
I will relinquish my duty as county magistrate,
and follow you to help in this great cause.
Gōngtái,
a person named Lǚ Bóshē lives here.
He is my father's sworn brother.
For the night, why don't we stay here?
I can ask about my family's whereabouts.
He won't reject his sworn brother's own son, then!
Let's go.
Who are you looking for?
Is your master in?
Yes.
Master, there's someone here to see you.
Lǚ Bóshē
You are...
Uncle,
I am Āmán.
Note: Āmán is Cáo Cāo's childhood name.
Āmán!
Please come in quickly.
Quickly.
Please. Come in quickly.
Uncle.
Please sit.
Please sit, Gōngtái.
Āmán,
I heard...
Please.
I heard that the Imperial Court was looking everywhere
to arrest you.
Why did you...
Why did you come here?
Your father has already taken refuge at Chénliú.
It's hard to explain.
I failed to assassinate Dǒng Zhuó,
so I fled the capital city in the night.
I ran until I was arrested at Zhōngmóu county.
Were it not for magistrate Chén
sacrificing his post to escape with me,
your nephew would have long been dead.
Were it not for you, the entire Cáo clan would have ended.
Please take a seat and rest here for the night.
Sorry to bother you, uncle.
You two, take a rest. I'll be right back.
Please.
Uncle.
I don't have good wine at my house.
I'll go to the village and purchase some for you.
Thank you, uncle.
I can sleep here in peace tonight.
Gōngtái.
Listen. What is that noise?
Lǚ Bóshē is not a close relative.
He left in a hurry and has yet to come back. It's too suspicious.
Sharpen it.
Listen to that. If we don't act now, we'll be killed.
Murderer!
This...
Your uncle wanted to slaughter a pig to treat us!
They died for nothing!
It's too late for regrets.
We have to flee!
So Uncle really did buy wine.
Gentlemen, why are you leaving?
As a criminal, I would not dare to stay for long.
Gentlemen, please wait! Please wait!
I already told my family to
slaughter a pig for you!
Gentlemen, why not rest at
my humble house for the night?
Please turn around!
Please come back!
Come back!
Nephew, what's that on your body?
Uncle,
look who's behind you.
Last time, you killed by accident. What did you kill him for now!?
If Bóshē came back home, he would have seen his entire family murdered. Would he let that go?
He would lead men to pursue us
and we would be doomed.
Uncle.
He's already dead.
Crying won't make a difference.
Let's go.
You murdered him.
You...
You've gone too far!
Rather I betray the world,
than let the world betray me.
Until now I followed him for the nation.
For that, I can't kill him,
but I can't stand with him.
I will leave now. You may go ahead with your 'great cause'
Cáo Cāo went back to Chénliú afterwards.
He spent all his family's wealth to recruit an army.
He contacted Yuán Shào and sent out declarations to all provinces to march against Dǒng Zhuó.
They were answered all across the realm.