This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 29
Refugees Cross the River
Zhuge Liang set Bowang Slope on fire at the start of his career
and bruised the morale of the Cao army.
Not resigned to failure, Cao Cao ordered Cao Ren to attack Xinye again.
Little did he knew, that he was falling into Zhuge Liang's trap.
Cao Ren was fortunate enough to make a narrow escape in the dark.
Chancellor.
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
That Zhuge peasant! How dare he?!
Prepare my armies, we will exterminate Xinye!
Well...
Liú Yè
Styled: Ziyáng
Chancellor intents to take Jīng-Xiāng for its masses.
So this time, when we enter Xiāngyang,
we must conquer the hearts of the populace.
Liu Bei has already led the people into Fancheng.
Why not summon him to surrender?
If Liu Bei refuses,
then the people may see our 'mercy'...
If he accepts, then the lands of
Jīng-Province are settled without struggle.
This plan can work.
Then, who can be the envoy?
My Chancellor, there is one man among our army very close with Liu Bei.
He can be our advocate.
Who is so close with Liu Bei?
None other than Xu Shu—Xu Yuanzhi.
No, no.
He has not offered a single thought to me.
If we send him away, he will not return!
Chancellor does not need to worry.
Xu Yuanzhi always cared about his reputation. If he doesn't return, he would be ridiculed.
Whether or not he is successful, he will definitely return.
Very well then. Order Xu Yuanzhi to set out at once.
Xu Shu
Styled: Yuanzhi
Lord—
—Yuanzhi to be sent from the heavens, just like the sweet rain after a long drought!
I am delighted from the bottom of my heart!
Mister Shuijing has predicted long ago—
— that if you have the Sleeping Dragon, the world is yours.
I can see that it is indeed true.
Easy for you to say!
Since our last meeting at my hut, you have made me busy day and night!
Tell us, has Cao Cao let you come to persuade my Lord to surrender?
Cao Cao has sent me to persuade you,
so that he can win the people's hearts this time.
Now Cao Cao has his armies traveling along eight routes —
— and intends to enter by damming the Bai-River. I'm afraid Fancheng won't hold.
You must make another plan.
Zhuge Liang
Styled:
Kongming
Yuanzhi is correct.
Retreat is the first choice of the Thirty-Six Stratagems.
Very well, I am able to meet you all today, my wish is fulfilled.
With two armies fighting, it is wrong to overstay. I will take my leave.
Since you have come, you must not return to that damned place again.
Lord, if I don't return, I would be mocked.
My mother has passed, and I will carry the pain until my last breath.
My Lord, even though I am situated in the Cao camp—
—I swore to never in my life form a plan or stratagem for Cao Cao.
You have the Sleeping Dragon's help—
—what fear could you have?
I will leave now.
Liu Bei
Styled: Xuande
Yuanzhi!
Yuanzhi, take care!
Everyone–farewell.
My Lord, you must abandon Fancheng at once
and retreat to Xiangyang for now.
The people of Xinye and Fancheng have been with me so long—
— how can I part with them?
My Lord, if you take them with you, they will only be a burden.
Sun Qian
Styled: Gongyou
Why not let them run for themselves?
All great accomplishers of old —
— regarded the common men as the foundation and to be of utmost importance.
The ruler is worth less than the populace.
My Lord, you can order someone to tell the people—
—that they can choose to follow us,
or to remain here.
It will be as Strategos says.
Attention, all ye people!
The Cao army is coming to attack!
Those who wish to follow Lord Liu  —
- We follow with Lord Liu, let's go!
— must cross the river for refuge in Xiangyang!
Cross the river for refuge in Xiangyang!
Attention, all ye people,
the Cao army is coming to attack!
Those who wish to follow Lord Liu must cross the river for refuge in Xiangyang!
Follow Lord Liu to Xiangyang to avoid bloodshed! Move quickly, you all!
Waves surge on —
Shuǐ tāotāo
— roads go on
lù mànmàn
Carrying the old and young, each step strenuous.
fú lǎo xié yòu bùlǚ jiān
What have people done to deserve this exodus —
Bǎixìng hégù zāo líluàn
—wishing to cross, yet the boats are few.
yù dù chánghé shǎo xíngchuán
Common men have not abandoned me,
I can't rest —
Mín bù qì wǒ wǒ nán shě
— seeing fore and ailing aft with sorrow.
zhānqiángùhòu xīn chuàngrán
For the Cause —
Lì dàyè
— For all men —
mín wéi běn
— for if men are safe, can there be peace.
mín dé píngān tiānxià ān
Wind howls on—
Fēng sàsà
—road goes on —
lù mànmàn
— with my sword I raise my head to ask Above.
fǔ jiàn ángshǒu wèn cāngtiān
Warriors of yore always suffered so—
Gǔlái zhuàngshì duō kǔ è
— yet when can the Kūnpéng soar tall and proud?
kūnpéng hé rì dé gāo xuán
If I who serve cannot a nation build —
Chénzǐ bùnéng jiàn jīyè
—then I can't face my forebears in death.
lǎo qù wú yán duì zǔxiān
With these men —
Mín xiāng suí
— My will steels —
zhì yù jiān
— If I can't turn this fate, my heart shan't rest.
bùzhěng qiánkūn xīn bùgān
Horse treads on —
Mǎ chí chí
— road goes on —
lù mànmàn
— the geese cry against the sunset clouds and yellow grass.
mù yún cānghuáng yàn shēng hán
Emperor Wǔ’s Autumn Wind Poem's spirit lives —
Hàn wǔ qiūfēng cíyì jiàn
— why should heroes lament over prime years past?
yīngxióng héxū tàn huá nián
For its righteousness can I accomplish —
Dédàoduōzhù gōng chéngjiù
— all for people's faces of joy and bliss.
yuàn jiàn shēng mín jìn huānyán
If we part—
Zòng xiāng bié
— wave fare-wells —
huīshǒu qù
— love and humanity shall persist under heavens.
rénài cháng cún tiāndì jiān
If we part —
Zòng xiāng bié
— wave fare-wells —
huīshǒu qù
— Love and humanity shall persist under heavens.
rénài cháng cún tiāndì jiān
Xiangyang
Dear nephew Liu Cong, please open the city gates quickly!
We are only here to save the people, nothing more.
Hurry, open the city gates!
Dear nephew Liu Cong, quickly open the gates!
Liu Cong
What should I do?
The people are too tired and cannot go any further.
Dear nephew Liu Cong, please open the gates quickly!
You only need to keep the people, my troops will leave immediately!
Lies! Those words cannot be trusted!
Cai Mao
Styled: Degui
Liu Bei is sending his army to denounce us!
He's using the commoners as a cover! You mustn't fall for this trap!
Greet him with arrows!
You can't harm the innocent!
Innocent or not, all is uncertain—
—but if we let them in, it'll bring chaos to Xiangyang again. Fire!
Traitorous bastard!
Lord Liu is a man of virtue!
Wèi Yán
Styled: Wéncháng
He has come to save the people,
why are you keeping them from the city?
You–
Let's go!
Imperial Uncle Liu, lead your troops in to kill the wicked traitors!
Wei Yan! How dare you rebel! Do you recognize me as Senior General Wen Pin?
General Wen Pin!?
I wanted to protect the people, but now I'm endangering them.
I can't enter Xiangyang.
My Lord, abandon Xiangyang at once and turn to Jiangling.
Jiangling is an important location in Jing-Province. Why not rest there?
Let's go.
Wen Pin! I will spare your life today— we will meet again!
Wei Yan, don't you flee!
Wen Pin
Styled: Zhongye
Grave of Liu Biao,
Overseer of Jing-Province
I have failed to live up to your trust.
The sin is with me alone,
not with the people.
I pray that your spirit in heaven will rescue the people of Jing-Xiang!
Please stand!
My lord.
Cao Cao's army has occupied Fancheng.
They're preparing boats and rafts and will soon cross the river.
Elder brother.
We are leading tens of thousands of people and can only travel about 10 li per day
With such speed, when can we reach Jiangling?
If the Cao army catches up, how can we resist them?
Why don't we temporarily abandon the people and advance ahead?
No, accomplishers of great deeds must have the people as their priority.
Now that the people have joined me,
how can I abandon them?
My Lord, the army will soon be upon us.
You can send Yunchang and Gongyou —
— towards Jiangxia to ask Liu Qi for help.
Tell him to raise his army and embark to meet us at Jiangling.
Yunchang, follow his orders and hurry to Jiangxia with Gongyou!
Yes.
Xún Yōu
Styled: Gōngdá
How many troops, horses, money, and grain are there in Jing-Province?
Chancellor, there are 50,000 cavalry —
— 150,000 infantry, and 80,000 naval infantry.
Most of the money and grain are at Jiangling.
With the supplies from other places, there are enough —
— to supply Chancellor Cao's victorious army for one year.
How many warships are there? Who was in command?
There are 7000 warships of all sizes.
Zhang Yun and I were the commanders.
Jing-Province has 280,000 troops and cavalry, 7,000 warships—
—and the money and grain altogether are just about enough
to support my army for a year.
With the strength of such resources—
—why did you generals surrender without a fight?
How can the troops of Jing-Province dare to resist Chancellor's mighty army?
Your intellect is unmatched in the world, you use the army like a god—
—you are invincible!
My Chancellor, you are, of this age ...
Very well, I grant you the title of
Marquis-Guardian of the South—
— and Grand Admiral of the naval force.
Zhang Yun is Pacifying-Marquis and Vice-admiral of the naval force.
You must keep the naval force ready, and await for command.
Thank you, Chancellor.
Liu Cong, I have already granted you to be the Overseer of Qīng-Province —
Why are you weeping?
When we surrendered the city, you promised my son will be the Lord of Jing-Province.
Lady Cai
Why are you sending us, mother and son, off to Qīng-Province?
The battles in Jing-Province are far from over, Liu Bei and Liu Qi refuse to surrender.
If I appointed Liu Cong as the lord of Jing-Province,
how could he keep his lands under his control?
If this is so, I do not wish to become an official!
I wish to guard my parents' native lands.
Please allow me to become a commoner!
Qīng-Province is near the capital. You can become an official under the imperial court.
You avoid being harmed in Jing-Xiang.
I did this with you both in mind. Set out at once.
Chancellor!
Yu Jin!
Yes!
Lead fifty soldiers to Lady Cai, Liu Cong, and his party before they reach Qīng-Province —
Kill them all.
Yes sir!
Chancellor, Cai Mao and Zhang Yun are lesser men who can only flatter and slander.
They are of reprobate nature.
Why were they granted such high ranks and entrusted with the naval force?
Do you think I could not tell?
It's because we men of the north are inexperienced with naval warfare —
— so I must use those two.
After they have fulfill their purpose,
I have other ways to deal with them.
Yes!
My respects, Chancellor.
All the officers of Xiangyang are here already—
—what made you alone take such time?
As an official, I failed to protect my Lord's territory.
My heart is ashamed. What face do I have to see anyone?
You are an official of integrity, rarely seen in Jing-Xiang.
Shame that you haven't met a worthy master!
General Wen Pin, I appoint you Marquis of the Inner Pass, and Administrator of Jiangxia.
Thank you, Chancellor.
Report!
Chancellor, Liu Bei's party is traveling only 10 li a day heading towards Jiangling.
Chancellor, Jiangling a place of import in Jing-Xiang. It is rich in money and grain.
If Liu Bei guards Jiangling, it would be very hard to dislodge him.
General Wen Pin!
Yes!
Lead your troops towards Jiangling and open up a way for our army.
Xu Chu, Zhang He!    - Yes!
Zhang Liao, Li Dian! Yue Jin!     - Yes!
Choose 5,000 cavalry to advance day and night to catch up to Liu Bei!      - Yes!
Xiahou En!
Yes!
I order you as the sword-bearer to carry the Blue Pommel and follow me.
We are traveling too slowly, what if the Cao army pursues us? How can we resist?
Yunchang and Gongyou departed for Jiangxia.
We have received no news, I wonder what happened.
Could it be that Liu Qi...
It seems that I will need to trouble you to go there.
You saved Liu Qi's life once. If he sees you, things will be settled.
I would go there, but what of things here, Lord?
Don't worry about it, with Yide and Zilong, nothing will happen to me.
Liu Feng!
Yes.
Lead 500 troops to escort the Strategos.
Yes!
I hope Xianhe and Zizhong will protect my Lord here well.
Please rest assured, Strategos.
Take care, my Lord.
Let's go!
What is this place before us?
It's the border with Dangyang county, and that hill is Jingshan.
Pass on the orders, we'll station on Jingshan.
Yes!
My Lord, we should not station here!
Cao Cao now has Xiangyang and will definitely send troops after us!
We are moving so slowly!
If we stop, I fear that Cao Cao's troops will catch up before daylight!
The people and soldiers are tired. How can we keep going?
If we go on like this and the Cao army comes—
—we will not only fail to protect the people from them, but you will also be in danger!
What is your idea?
My Lord should leave the people and ride quickly to Jiangling!
Otherwise, when the Cao army comes, disaster will fall!
The people have followed me all the way here from Xinye—
—and have gone through many hardships
How can I abandon them without regard?
Although the situation now is pressing—
—I have sworn to share life and death with my people.
We will live and perish together!
Don't try to persuade me. Pass on my orders again.
We will station on Jingshan.
Let the people get a night's worth of rest. We'll be on our way in the morning.
Zilong will protect my family
and Yide will be our rearguard!
Let's go, quickly!
Quick!
Sister, let me carry him for a while
The Cao army is coming! Run for your lives!
Elder brother, elder brother, quick!
The Cao army is coming from the northwest, run to the east at once!
Go quickly!
Hurry! Hurry and follow!
Lord Liu! Don't you run away!
Wen Pin! How has Brother Jingsheng ever mistreated you?
You dare betray your own lord for glory?
Submitting to Cao Cao, now killing your late master's brother?
Where is your conscience? Have you no shame?!
Treacherous villain, Zhang Yide from Yan is here!
Elder brother, follow me!
Don't move. Try not to move.
Elder brother!
The common people, old and young—
—Zilong, Mi Zizhong, Mi Zifang, and Jian Xianhe—
—where are they all?
My Lord, the Cao army had encircled all the commoners —
— and massacred more than half.
We don't know where the others have gone.
A hundred thousand living souls all suffered because of me...
Now the whereabouts of the people, of families, or the officers is unknown.
Even if one has a heart of stone and mind of iron, how can one not grieve?
Elder brother!
My Lord!
If you were to die, what reason do we have to live?
My Lord, General Mi is here!
My Lord, emergency!
Mi Fang
Zhao Zilong has defected to Cao Cao!
Speak no nonsense!
Zilong is an old friend, how could he leave me for Cao Cao?
He must have seen how weak our forces were,
so he followed Cao Cao for the riches and honors
No.
Zilong joined me when I was in misfortune.
His heart is of iron and stone,
no riches and honors can move him.
I saw him ride towards the northwest with my own eyes!
I will seek him later. If I run into him, I shall kill him under my spear!
Third brother, don't be rash!
Follow me!
Third brother! Third brother!
Dangyang
Bridge
Elder brother could not be seen—
—even in such short distance!
Why don't I raise the dust as a tactic to deceive the enemy?
Soldiers!
Go cut down branches
and tie them to your horse's tails!
Divide into two! One group run west to east!
The other run east to west!
This will raise the dust and look like an ambush!
Yes!
General Zhang, where is the Lord now?
My Lord is now hiding in the woods over there!
Do you have any news about Zilong?
Jian Yong
Styled: Xianhe
If not for General Zhao, I would have met a violent death.
General Zhao has gone back to look for the two Ladies and the young Lord.
Please inform the Lord immediately.
You must go yourself.
I will, I will.
Zilong!
Older brother!
Older brother, where is our Lord?
In the woods before us.
Sister-in-law, you must be startled!
Third brother...
Lady, now that you are with General Zhang—
I will look for Lady Mi and Adou again.
Return the sword, that's the Chancellor's Blue Pommel Sword!
Return me the legendary sword!
General Zhao, please save us!
Have any of you seen Lady Mi and the young Lord?
Lady has the infant, but can't walk because she is wounded in her leg!
She is sitting by the broken wall over there!
Head for the east, General Zhang is waiting at the bridge.
Thank you General Zhao! Thank you for rescuing us!
Lady!
General!
Lady, I have come late—
—and let you suffer.
Since you are here, Adou will live!
Have pity that his father has wandered half his life with only him as his flesh and blood.
I hope that you can protect Adou.
If he can see his father again, I can die without regrets.
It's Zhao Yun's sin to allow my Lady to suffer.
Please take my horse, my Lady.
I shall fight on foot beside you and ensure that we make it out alive!
That cannot happen, how can you go without a horse?
I will entrust Adou completely under your care.
I...I am already heavily injured, there would be no regrets if I die.
I hope you can take him ahead! I don't want to drag you down!
Lady Mi, if I have found you but cannot protect you—
—how can I look at my Lord in the face again?
Quick, quick! Go over there!
Lady Mi, please, the troops are near! Please mount the horse!
No, I really cannot move and should not be a burden to both of you!
My Lady, please mount the horse now!
Adou will be left in your care, General
Quick, quick! Go that way, quick!
My Lady, please mount the horse!
Hurry!
General, there is someone here! Quick, over here!
My Lady.
Lady, my Lady!
Lady!