This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 30
Debate Against Southern Scholars
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Xiàhóu Jié
Chancellor, this man has slain over fifty of our warriors!
Who is that man?
I will go and find out!
Cáo Hóng
Styled: Zǐlián
You, warrior! What is your name?!
Zhào Yún
Styled: Zǐlóng
I am Zhào Zǐlóng of Changshan!
A true tiger-like warrior.
Capture him alive!
Chancellor has ordered!
Zhào Zǐlóng must be captured alive! No shooting!
Chancellor's orders!
Zhāng Hé
Attack!
Though we are not brothers sworn by oath —
— Our meeting must be as fate ordained!
Brave and loyal to the Hàn you remain —
— Spirit alike to Peach Garden's names!
A lone rider of one spear breaking shields —
— With valor that sends all foes to yield!
Stained is that white gown with deep scarlet!
At Dangyang your glory shines, starlit!
Zǐlóng, Zǐlóng,
rivaled by none!
Legend of the Five Tiger Generals!
Though we are not brothers sworn by oath —
— Our meeting must be as fate ordained!
Brave and loyal to the Hàn you remain —
— Spirit of the Peach Garden you attain!
A lone rider of one spear breaking shields —
— With valor that sends all foes to yield!
Stained is that white gown with deep scarlet!
At Dangyang your glory shines starlit!
Zǐlóng, Zǐlóng,
rivaled by none!
Legend of the Five Tiger Generals!
Zǐlóng, Zǐlóng,
rivaled by none!
Legend of the Five Tiger Generals!
Dangyang
Bridge
Yide, aid us!
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Zilong, hurry! I will stop the pursuers!
Madam Gān
General Zilong!
General Zilong has returned!
My liege!
General Zilong!
Sir Zhao!
- My liege!
My liege!
Sir Zhao!
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Zilong.
My liege!
Zilong!
My guilt can't be redeemed even
by ten thousand deaths.
Lady Mi was severely wounded
but she refused to mount my horse.
She threw herself down a well!
I buried Lady Mi in the well
by pushing down the wall—
Mi Fang
—I broke out of the encirclement, with the young lord by my bosom.
Zilong, rise!
We managed to escape,
thanks to the lord's grand luck.
The young lord cried just a moment ago—
—but now he isn't moving, so I'm afraid I lost him!
My liege!
My dear child!
Your son was unharmed!
For this baby, I very nearly lost a great general.
Even if my organs are spread onto the ground,
your kindness cannot ever be repaid!
Wén Pìng
Styled: Zhòngyè
Cáo Rén
Styled: Zǐxiào
I fear this may be an ambush by Zhuge Liang.
Report to the Chancellor immediately.
-Yes sir!
I am Zhang Yide of Yan!
Who dares come and fight me to the death!
Guan Yunchang had mentioned Zhang Yide.
He can go through an army to take the head of a warrior-general as if reaching into a pocket.
Now here is that man in front us,
we must not underestimate him.
I am right here!
Who dares come and fight me to the death!
Chancellor, there may be an ambush across the bridge.
Fight or don't fight! Run or don't run! Which is it?
Retreat!
In the 13th year of the Jian'an era, 208 C.E.
Under Cao Cao's coercion —
Liu Biao of Jing Province's son, Liu Cong,
surrendered his cities to him.
Liu Bei abandoned Fancheng and fled with the people over the river to Han Ford.
Jiangxia
He turned to Liu Qi for refuge in Jiangxia.
Now Cao Cao gathered with his victorious 830,000 troops at the north bank of Yangtze River —
— casting his greedy eyes at the six commanderies of Jiangdong.
...best to ask East Wu's Sūn Quán for aid.
Zhūgě Liàng
Styled: Kǒngmíng
We can support each other—
—then the north and south will stand facing each other, which can benefit us.
Jiangdong has many able, talented figures, who must have ambitions of their own. Could he accept us?
My lord!
My lord, Wú's Sūn Quán has sent Lǔ Sù to offer his condolences, and his boat has landed!
When Sun Ce died, did Xiangyang send someone to express sorrow?
Jiangdong should despise us over the death of Sun Quan's father —
Liu Qi
—why would they come here to spare their pity?
It may seem Lu Su came here in the pretext of mourning to investigate our strength.
That Cao Cao leads a million men.
He has taken Jianghan and now threatens Jiangdong.
Sun Quan wants to preserve his family's legacy —
—  thus he sent someone to explore our position,
and to ask us to join forces.
As Heaven favors it, the envoy is Lu Su.
I say we make use of the wind and sail to Jiangdong.
With my incorrupt tongue —
— I will persuade the north and south to battle each other.
If the South wins, we will press on Cao Cao and retake Jing Province.
If the North wins, the chaos will present us a chance to take control of Jiangnan.
That is a strong argument!
Mister Kongming, we're approaching Chaisang.
For the good of our common cause
I've a request to make.
When you meet my lord —
— do not tell the truth about the magnitude of Cao Cao's army.
Lǔ Sù Styled: Zǐjìng
You need not remind me!
I will know how to reply.
Please, please!
My lord!
Report!
My lord, Lu Su has returned from Jiangxia
and is waiting for an audience.
Let him in.
Aye! Master Lu is wanted!
My respects, sire!
Your arrival is welcome!
Cao Mengde has sent an envoy today.
We're discussing about it.
Sit.
When I received the imperial order
to crusade against the guilty —
— with my banners pointed south, Liu Cong submitted to me.
People of Jing-Xiang
foresaw the coming tide and submitted.
With an army of million men and many veteran generals under my command  —
— I hope we can join our great hunts at Jiangxia and together defeat Liu Bei.
Upon our victory, his land will be shared between us for amity's sake.
Sir must not be a bystander, for I need your quick reply. - Mengde
What have you decided upon, my lord?
Sūn Quán
Styled: Zhòngmóu
No decisions yet. It is still under our fellow gentlemen's discussion.
Zhāng Zhāo
Styled: Zǐbù
My lord, my lord!
Cao Cao has an armada of a million on his side —
— pacifying lands by the imperial authority.
If we are to resist —
— our most important bulwark
is no more than the Yangtze River.
But since Cao Cao has taken Jing-Province —
— we now share that same barrier.
We can't stop his momentum.
The only way to tranquility, in my opinion, is submission. It is the only way to ensure peace.
My lord, my lord!
Zibu's words accord with the wishes of Heaven.
Do not hesitate, sire.
Submission means safety for the people of Eastern Wú —
—  and tranquility for
the six commanderies of Jiangdong!
Indeed, my lord!
Who knew the autumn night of Jiangnan could make people shiver so.
Submission is self-protection!
Cao Cao has a million troops!
Sir, what is your position?
What they have said will lead
Your Lordship to make a grave mistake.
A common man might submit to Cao, but you, sire, cannot.
Why?
If someone such as I submits to Cao Cao, we may keep our position like before.
— but if sire submits, you will be made at the most a Marquis —
— with no chariots save one, no more horses than
a geldling, and retinue left only a few.
You will be but a fleeting shadow in the eyes of the South.
The gentry are covetous, every man is for himself, and not to be listened to.
You best decide soon how to make your legacy last.
What our ministers have said disappoints me greatly.
Only your words, Zijing, match my grand strategy.
It is like Heaven has gifted you to me!
Still, Cao Cao has attained the former armies of Yuan Shao —
— and annexed the soldiers of Jing-Province  —
I fear he is too powerful to be withstood.
I have brought here Zhuge Liang,
brother of Zhuge Jin, from Jiangxia.
You could inquire him the true situation of Cao Cao's army.
The 'Sleeping Dragon' is here?
He's at the guest-house right now.
It is quite late. Tomorrow, gather
all officials and officers civil and military.
I will invite him to meet the gentry of Jiangdong and thereupon debate.
My lord.
I take my leave.
When you meet with sire, say nothing of the magnitude of Cao Cao's army.
You reminded me many times on the boat yesterday.
Mister Kongming, please.
Gentlemen, he's here! He's arrived.
Sir Kongming, you cannot by any means frighten the nobles!
Don't worry, Zijing. I will act in what's most fit without err.
Please.
Gentlemen—this is Mister Zhuge Kongming.
Gentlemen, I am lucky to meet you all!
This is the Commissioner-General of the Household, Zhang Zhao, or Zhang Zibu.
Greetings.
Here is Gu Yong, Gu Yuantan!
Here is Yu Fan, Yu Zhongxiang.
Yú Fān
Styled: Zhòngxiáng
Bù Zhì
Styled: Zǐshān
Here is Bu Zhi, Bu Zishan.
Xue Zong
Styled: Jingwen
Here is Xue Zong, Xue Jingwen.
Lu Ji
Styled: Gongji
Here is Lu Ji, Gongji.
Yan Jun
Styled: Mancai
Here is Yan Jun, Yan Mancai.
Cheng Bing
Styled: Deshu.
Here is Cheng Bing, Cheng Deshu
I am honored to meet you all.
Please.
Sir Kongming.
Sir Zibu, what plans do you have?
I'm the most insignificant of our officials.
People say you have once compared yourself with Guan Zhong and Yue Yi. Is this true?
Indeed, but it is only a trifling comparison I had made.
I heard that Liu Bei solicited you three times at that thatched hut —
— and considered himself fortunate to get you—
'a fish finding water' was how he put it —
— then he expected to possess the lands of Jing-Xiang.
Yet now, the province belongs to Cao Cao.
We would like to hear sir's account for that.
Yes, how do you explain that!
I think that retaking lands of Jing-Xiang is as easy as turning over one's palm.
My master, Lord Liu of Yu-Province is both humane and honorable —
— thus he did not stoop to filching his kinsman's estate.
But Liu Zong, too adolescent, listened to insidious counsel —
— thus surrendered to Cao Cao's ferocity.
My master, with forces stationed at Jiangxia —
— has promising prospects of his own,not to be lightly dismissed.
Be it so, but your words and your deeds do not agree.
Sir claims comparison with Guan and Yue —
Well, Guan Zhong led his master Duke Huan of Qi to become a hegemon over all lords.
Yue Yi helped the feeble state of Yan subdue the seventy cities of the mighty state of Qi.
These two were men of most
commanding and conspicuous talent.
-Indeed, indeed!
But before Lord Liu of Yu-Province, obtained your services —
— he was a force to be reckoned, seizing cities wherever he went.
Why, then, after you had committed yourself to Lord Liu —
— did your soldiers throw aside their arms, and armors and flee like rats?
Abandoning Xinye, fleeing to Fancheng, defeated at Dangyang —
— and holed up in Xiakou,
barely a place to take refuge.
-Yes, yes!
It seems that Lord Liu was better off before you came, sir.
Could it be...
This is the capability of Guan Zhong and Yue Yi?
I trust you do not mind my blunt words.
How can the common fowls understand
the long flight of cranes?
WhileI was a farmer in Longzhong —
Whenever I met someone who was gravely ill —
— The physician would tell his family
to first feed him sick simple gruel  —
— then administer mild tonics until his viscera is balanced and recovering.
Then the sick may be given meats and powerful drugs to cure him —
— thus is the root of the disease eradicated and health restored
If before the sick man's breath and pulse were in harmony —
— volatile drugs were instead administered early, it will be difficult to restore the patient.
When Imperial Uncle Liu suffered defeat at Runan, and went to Liu Biao —
— he had less than a thousand men and only
Sir Guan, Sir Zhang, and Sir Zhao Yun as officers.
That was indeed like a man wasted by disease.
Xinye, a mere small county, with few people, scant grain and weak foundation —
— Such insufficient forces, weak walls, with untrained men and lacking supplies —
— yet still, the fire of Bowang-slope, the flooding of Bai-River —
— put Cao's leading generals, Xiahou Dun
and Cao Ren, in a state of panic and disarray.
I wonder whether Guan Zhong and Yue Yi would have surpassed us in warfare.
As for Dangyang, we had hundred thousand common people, with children and elderly, following us.—
Imperial Uncle Liu was too humane to abandon them, and never thought once of taking Jiangling —
But willing to suffer with his people —
— for that is what humanity
and sense of honor means!
The few cannot oppose the many,
victory and defeat are common in all campaigns.
The High Forefather of the Han Dynasty suffered many defeats —
— but had his decisive victory at Gaixia!
Was not it for the strategy of Han Xin?
Indeed, for the grand strategy of a nation,
the restoration of its spirit —
—— all must depend on true statesmanship!
Not those decadent rhetoricians of vapid discourses —
— nor those with empty reputations who fraud common men.
Those who sit in complacency and grandstand above all else —
— but fail to have even a single idea out of a hundred to confront any crisis.
Truly a farce for all the world!
Chancellor Cao gathers an army of million, glaring like a predator at Jiangxia!
I would ask Mister Kongming
what is your outlook on this uncertain future?
Cao Cao has but annexed surrendered rebels and mobs of low-morale from Yuan Shao and Liu Biao.
A million they may be, but they are not to be feared.
You were defeated at Dangyang
and in desperation fled to Xiakou.
Your retreats frantic,
and could hardly find a place to rest.
Now you have crossed the river to ask for our help —
— yet maintain there is nothing to be feared?
What a jest!
Are you not Yu Fan, Yu Zhongxiang?
You laugh too soon!
Was Imperial Uncle to hold off with a few thousand honorable troops —
— against a million murderous brutes?
Yet our army are united as one, determined to resist —
— regardless of defeat,
we will still fight to the last blood!
The elite army of Jiangdong are good with ample supplies, and Yangtze as its bastion.
Yet there are men advising
their lord to kneel and surrender —
— and care not of being derided worldwide!
In contrast, Lord Liu of Yù-Province is someone
proud to be fearless before that despot Cao!
Not long ago, you were under the tent of Adminstrator Wang Lang of Kuaiji.
You persuaded him into surrendering to Sun Ce.
Surely you're not trying to make your lord surrender once again, this time to Cao Cao?
Seems like some habits will not die!
Kongming, is that not going too far?!
Ah, brother Zishan. My apologies.
Are you trying to model after Sū Qín and Zhāng Yí,
by agitating us to help using your sharp tongue?
Note: Sū Qín and Zhāng Yí were rival political strategists of the Warring States period.
Su Qin led the Vertical Alliance of Six States against Qin, while Zhang Yi led Qin to dissolve it.
Do you regard Su Qin and Zhang Yi as simple lobbyists?
Do you not recognize them as real heroes of their time!
Su Qin held the Chancellor's seals of six states.
Zhang Yi was twice the Chancellor of the state of Qin.
Both were talents who brought about the reformation of their nations.
Not like those who cower before the strong and victimize the weak.
You gentlemen never seen a single soldier of Cao's, yet urge surrender with craven dispatch.
Are you the ones to ridicule Su Qin and Zhang Yi?
May I ask, sir Kongming,
what is your view on Cao Cao?
A tyrant and traitor to the Hàn Empire. What else is there?
Sir is mistaken.
The time of the House of Hàn under Heaven is near its end.
Today, Cao Cao has in his hands two-thirds of the empire, and people are submitting to him.
Liu Xuande refuses to recognize the season of history. He is throwing eggs at rocks.
His failure is certain.
Xue Jingwen, do you mean to deny both lord and father?!
You!
Between Heaven and Earth, loyalty and filiality is a foundation of being!
Cao Cao's ancestors served the Hàn Empire, enjoying its prosperity —
— yet their progeny think not of gratitude, but of usurpation!
What is he then if not a traitor?!
For traitors such as these, only assault
and execution by the entire realm is most fit!
Yet you sir, as an official of the Hàn, wish to whitewash this despot!
Is that not to deny loyalty and filiality!?
You...!
You are not worthy of discourse!
Unfit to speak with any further!
Cao Cao may be overruling the court through coercion of the Emperor —
Note: Cáo Shēn was one of the early chancellors
of the Han Dynasty, who aided Liu Bang in it's founding.
— but he is still Premier Cáo Shēn's descendant.
Liu Xuande claims to be Prince Jing of Zhongshan's descendant, yet no evidence is known.
Those in the world only know that he is a weaver of mats and seller of shoes!
How is he worthy to challenge Cao Cao?
Master Lu —
— isn't that gentleman Young Lu, or Lu Gongji,
that stole Yuan Shu's oranges whilst among guests?
Please sit down, and heed just a word from me.
Cao Cao is a descendant of Premier Cao,
ergo he is to be a consul of the Hàn Empire!
Yet now, Cao Cao consolidates power for himself and abuses all and his sovereign.
Not only shaming the Emperor,
but shaming his forebearers!
Not only is he a rebel consul of the Hàn, he is also an insurgent of his clan!
Imperial Uncle Liu is an imperial scion of dignity.
The Son of Heaven has inspected the clan registry
to confer nobility, naming him 'Imperial Uncle'.
How can you say 'no evidence is known'?
Our Forefather was a lowly corporal,
but came to unite the world under Hàn.
So what shame is there
in weaving mats and selling shoes?
Sir, your puerile views are most unfit for an eminent gentleman!
You!
Kongming, all of what you've said is just bombast.
None within reason.
Gentlemen, you needn't argue with him.
May I ask you, Kongming,
what canon classics have you studied?
I am no pedant student of reaping passages and picking phrases for bluster.
Those are for foolish, debauch dryasdusts who worm books.
It has no use for governance and state affairs.
The age old statesmen of transcendent ability weren't subservient the classic texts.
First King Tāng of Shāng's consul Yin Yi was but a slave-farmer.
Zhōu Dynasty's grand-aide
Jiang Zhiya was a fisherman
Zhang Liang and Chen Ping of later ages, were all men of transcendent ability.
Note: Chen Ping was another early chancellor of
the Hàn dynasty, who was a key advisor for Liu Bang.
Yet, I've never heard of what canons they mastered.
Unfortunately the gentry of today know only to quote classic texts and repeat old proverbs.
Wasting their days on the pen and inkstone.
I think these men can only bicker over petty matters behind the back flourishing words and wasting ink!
You, sir, are certainly given to exaggeration.
But it's doubtful if there is real learning behind it.
I'm afraid your words can only be ridiculed by all scholars.
If we are to speak of scholars —
— Then you must know the scholars' discernment of noble and lesser men?
A noble scholar is loyal to the nation,
compassionate and just, standing against evil.
He commits fully to the present —
— and is appraised in the future.
But not same with lesser men!
Slaving over paper and ink, knowing no skill but that of petty tricks and fraud.
Writing odes in callow youth,
by old age still devoted to canon.
Thousands of words flow from his pen, but not one thought in his bosom.
Look at Yang Xiong! He glorified the age with his writing, his thoughts and poetry —
Note: Yang Xiong (53 BCE–18 CE) was a poet and philosopher of the late Western Han Dynasty
— and yet shamelessly stoop to serve Wang Mang who usurped the throne.
Note: Wang Mang was a minister-turned-usurper of the Western Han Dynasty. A Confucian traditionalist whose reactionary reforms devastated the nation.
And thus ended up throwing himself out of a window!
Those are the lesser men, pedants who can write ten-thousand words —
— but none with value to speak of!
You..!
I know sir Deshu are a great scholar of Runan.
I have as well read your great 'Selections from the Book of Changes'.
Note: 'Selections from the Book of Changes' (周易摘) is a real book written by Cheng Bing in history, along with two other major works
I wish you would be a noble scholar, with loyalty and honor to the nation.
Not to imitate lesser men like Yang Xiong —
— leaving your name in infamy for the days to come.
-Kongming, how dare you...!
Cease this infernal squabble!
Mister Kongming is a genius of our generation —
— but rather than show respect to our invited guest, you besmirch him!
Huáng Gài
Styled: Gōngfù
Our foe is at our borders, yet instead of planning our defense —
— you sit here like children, whining!
Sir.
General Huang.
Talking may yield profit,
but there is more from silence.
What will you gain by debating these people?
It's better to have your advice spoken to my lord.
The pressing issue is how we two could be united to defeat Cao Cao.
Senior general, you said it quite well.
These folks all rose to ask, so it was my obligation to answer, that is all.
Please follow me to meet my lord!
Good.
Let's go.
Gentlemen, so sorry.
That Zhuge Kongming dares to talk down at us!
- If we let him meet with our lord —
—  he will ruin us and our state of Wú!
-Yes!
The blade's light and sword's shadow fade,
Àndànliao dāoguāngjiànyǐng
Far away is the drum and horn's serenade;
yuǎn qùliao gǔjiǎo zhēng míng
Before my eyes appear, one by one,
Yǎnqián fēiyángzhe yīgè gè
Such vibrant visages.
xiān huó de miànróng
The old paths are buried now—
yānmòliao huáng chén gǔdào
—by a fire burning through every town.
huāngwúliao fēnghuǒ biānchéng
But time, you cannot take away that string—
Suìyuè a nǐ dài bù zǒu, nà yī chuàn chuàn
—of still familiar names.
shúxī di xìngmíng
What man will determine victory or death?
Xīngwáng shéi rén dìng a
Prosperity and decline have no cause, indeed!
shèngshuāi qǐ wú píng a
A single breeze scatters the clouds—
yī yè fēngyún sàn nà
—and the world as we knew it vansih with them.
biànhuànliao shíkōng
Meetings and partings happen for their reasons—
Jù sàn jiē shì yuán a
—but these comings and going still rouse our feelings!
líhé zǒng guān qíng a
We carry the weight of our pasts—
dāndāng shēngqián shì a
—and account little for the opinions left behind.
hé jì shēnhòu píng
The Long River turns to tears—
Chángjiāng yǒuyì huà zuò lèi
—its waters rise in a song;
Chángjiāng yǒuqíng qǐ gēshēng
In the skies of history there yet shines a few stars—
lìshǐ di tiānkōng shǎnshuò jǐ kē xīng
—as in the world of man dwells a spirit of heroism, ever galloping forward.
rénjiān yī gǔ yīngxióng qì zài chíchěng zònghéng