This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 20
Sūn Cè's death
Sūn Cè dominated Jiāngdōng, seizing Lújiāng, gaining momentum to his cause.
Once finished, Zhāng Hóng was sent to Xǔchāng to announce their victory.
But his request to become Grand Marshal Cáo Cāo and so it was refused
Sūn Cè become concerned for this,
and began planning a counterattack to Xǔchāng.
Thus, the Administrator of Wú Commandery,
Xǔ Gòng, contacted Xǔchāng in secret,
Xǔ Gòng
informing Cáo Cāo of the operation.
Go by the river,
deliver this to the Chancellor Cáo.
Make sure no one else sees this.
Yes!
Wait!
This is extremely classified. Be careful.
Yes!
Halt! Who is crossing the river?
Administrator of Wú Commandery, Xǔ Gòng!
We are returning back to
the offices after Sūn Cè army drills!
Sire, our army is now prepared.
If you can suppress
Huáng Zǔ and cut down Liú Biǎo,
we can rely on the Yangtze River as our bulwark for Jiāngdōng, and bring peace to our land.
Zǐbù, the land you speak of is different from mine.
Right now, Cáo Cāo commands all in the Emperor's name.
Yuán Shào has the Héběi region,
a tiger among men.
Note: Héběi is one of the names for Jì-Province,
How could I be satisfied with only the Jiāngdōng region?
Sire has overseen vigorous
training for our men yesterday,
and now we are here to oversee the building of our ships.
Is it possible... is it possible that...
Report!
Report! An envoy of Xǔ Gòng was crossing the river, and was detained by our patrols!
"Sūn Cè is valiant and indomitable, akin to Xiàng Jí.
Note: Xiàng Jí, styled Xiàng Yǔ, was the Hegemon-King of Chǔ,
a fierce warlord who advanced the fall of Qín dynasty.
The court ought to reward him, then summon him back to the capital.
You must not let him dominate Jiāngdōng..."
...'Or he will become a menace'.
The realm is in anarchy, the lords scramble for power.
Those without ambition, can only serve others.
Zǐbù, now you understand the land that I dream of...
Right?
Sūn Cè
Styled: Bófú
General Sūn Cè has sent a message!
General Sūn is hosting a banquet for the envoys of Jīng-Province.
and has asked for you, sir, to come with us.
Let me prepare my chariot, I'll come after.
There is no need, Mr. Xǔ!
General Sūn has prepared one, just for you!
Look, sir.
You see that?
Yes.
Sir, is this...
What is happening?
Who is that man?
Sire, that is-
Sir! Sir!
That is an Immortal! A god among men!
Scram! Scram!
What Immortal!?
Go ask who he is!
Sir, the exalted Immortal will punish us if we don't kneel!
Sire! Get down now! Now!
Zǐbù, don't tell me you believe in this nonsense too?!
Now!
Sire! If you don't kneel,
then you better get out of here!
You can't stay here, sire!
I am Sūn Cè of Jiāngdōng!
They should be kneeling to me! Damn peons!!
Zhòngmóu, task General Chéng Pǔ
to locate those three shady men.
I understand.
Stop.
Those men are of no importance.
Tell General Chéng to capture that foul sorcerer!
Yes, sir.
Sire, peasants praying for that
Immortal is only a trifle matter.
Zhāng Zhāo
Styled: Zǐbù
There's no need for anger.
How can I not be angry?
I am the lord of this region!
Why should I prostrate myself to some heretic magician!
I will find out who that revolting sorcerer is.
Stop his bewitching of the citizens of this city!
Sire.
Ma'am.
Your son pays his respects to you.
Rise.
My son, what is troubling you?
Mother, why have you come here?
I've been inside too long.
I heard recently there's an Immortal in the city.
They say he can work miracles, curing the sick, and seeing the future.
I have nothing else to do,
so I want to see him for myself.
Mother, the markets are messy, why go there?
Besides, there are no such thing as Immortals.
I seldom go out to a walk,
I just want to expel the boredom.
Rumors may not always be false.
The world can hold many surprises unimaginable.
Come out! All of you, come out!
Who is it? Who told of that
heretic street magician to my mother!?
Sire, we can take care of this.
No need to upset your family.
What are you still kneeling for? Help our lord to rest!
With that foul sorcerer here, I will not rest!
How can I rest?!
I am going hunting in Dāntú Mountain.
No more of this!
Back then, on the Shéntíng Ridge,
I ascended to the temple there,
there I swore an oath,
facing the idols of our illustrious heroes,
If I can revive my late father's foundations in Jiāngdōng,
I would rebuild that temple,
venerate it at every snake's hours.
Note: 9-11 A.M. based on the Earthly Branches.
Today, Jiāngdōng is in prosperity.
It is time to honor that oath.
If at this mountain peak I could build another temple,
one which can let the people
stand tall and see the distance,
and revere our pioneers, wouldn't that be better?
Hurry, hurry!
Hurry!
Sire!
Sire? Sire?
Sire! Sire!
Sire,
I was too careless!
I was too late!
Zǐbù,
I want to build a temple for Guāngwǔ, so that the people can see...
Note: Emperor Guāngwǔ Liú Xiù was an imperial scion who lived as a farmer, but would later restore the Han Dynasty in 25 AD
... So that people never forget...
The greatness men can achieve...
What do you think?
Good.
How severe is his condition?
The arrow was poisoned.
I'm afraid it has already entered his body.
He must rest for a hundred days and do nothing.
My son has suffered this disaster,
all because of his volatility and arrogance.
Hang it there.
To the right.
Sire, you can get up!
Sire!
A blessing from the Heavens!
Mother,
Husband.
What blessings from Heaven?
I am destined to be a hero, not to die.
How could Xǔ Gòng's servants be able to kill me?
Please don't strain yourself, my son.
For two months, I've kept my hope for you.
You are still injured.
You must go back and rest.
What are these?
You were in peril, so your mother and I, and all the servants,
prayed on your behalf to
the Immortal deities for a swift recovery.
O spirits, please forgive him,
my son is young and passionate.
Let all disaster befall on to me in his stead.
This whole mansion has fallen into devil worship.
How could I, Sūn Cè, be aided by some mystical deities?
I detest witchcraft, and those
heretic prophets who mislead men's hearts.
Take them off! Don't let me see them again!
Yes.
Who dares!
Without the Immortals' help,
would you be here today?
Sūn Cè's wound had started to recover slightly.
Zhāng Hóng, who went to Xǔchāng to report Sūn Cè's victories,
had an envoy return in his stead, now a visitor to the mansion.
Sir, how many days have you been here?
The Envoy
It has been six days.
When will you return to Xǔchāng?
I will go back to Xǔchāng tomorrow.
General, can you inform Zhāng Hóng of this?
I would, only that Zǐbù won't let me speak.
Sire, your wound hasn't healed yet
and you've been playing weiqi for too long.
I believe that's enough for today.
Stop.
Since the envoy will return to Xǔchāng tomorrow,
I will only ask one thing.
Please allow me this one, Zǐbù.
I just want to ask this gentleman
Does Cáo Cāo really fear me?
It's true.
You lie!
It is not a lie.
Cáo Cāo does fear Your Lordship.
His advisors too all respect your Lordship. Only...
Only what?
His Lordship said, he only asks one question.
Yes yes yes!
I have spoken too much, I must take my leave.
Allow me one last sentence.
I hope my Lord will get well soon with vim and vigor!
What vim and vigor?
You mean to anger me?
Speak.
Speak!
Who would disregard me, Sūn Cè?
Only Guō Jiā disregards.
Guō Jiā?
What did he say?
My lord, please,
I can't repeat Guō Jiā's words!
I take my leave!
Halt, sir.
Sir, you've already started,
why not finish your words before leaving?
Would you make our lord angrier?
No matter what the words are, please finish before leaving.
Guō Jiā had told Lord Cáo,
that there's nothing to be afraid of.
Go on.
He said that Your Lordship is a bloated
and arrogant cretin. A barbaric imbecile.
What more?
Yes...
Say it!
Yes!
He said... Your Lordship will die like a lout!
Sire, Guō Jiā is just a base-born. He deserves death.
Sire, please calm.
The nerve of that cur!
I will crush Xǔchāng!
Zǐbù.
Here.
It's been many days since
Yuán Shào sent his envoy, Chén Zhèn.
Why didn't you report?
That...
You. Inform master Chén Zhèn...
I will ally with Yuán Shào against Cáo Cāo.
But... Well...
Tomorrow, summon our generals to the city top.
And tell mister Chén Zhèn to come as well.
We will discuss our strike against Cáo.
The doctor warned sire to rest for a hundred days.
How can you sacrifice your well-being like this?
Gentlemen, do rise.
Do rise.
Mister Chén Zhèn is Yuán Shào's envoy and shall be the guest of honor.
Please?
Please.
Every gentlemen present,
whether be the veteran ministers,
or all the fierce generals who founded
Jiāngdōng and followed me in conquests,
or like Zǐyì.
All great champions, heroes of the battlefield,
for me to have Jiāngdōng as part of my legacy,
it is thanks to all of you, that we could be here today.
Please accept all my gratitude, my noble men!
May Your Lordship recover and lead Jiāngdōng to greatness!
Everyone, the men of Jiāngdōng are fed.
The commoners live in peace and prosper.
These developments are indeed gratifying.
However,
To protect Jiāngdōng,
one has to hold great ambition.
Those without ambitions will only be subject to others.
We can join with Yuán Shào and resist Cáo Cāo.
This is now our goal.
If we want peace, we must prepare for war.
Build a great navy and fortify our position.
then we can march north and besiege Xǔchāng.
Why look out?
Immortal Yú is passing by down there.
We generals wish to pay our respects.
It's that heretic again! Throw him out!
I...
Superstitious hogwash!
For even officers to be fooled by these lies,
if this continues, how can I conquer the realm?
Sire!
Sire, he is called Yú Jí.
He travels everywhere to administer medicines.
He has healed many, no disease has ever stumped him.
They call him an Immortal.
Sire, this isn't to be taken lightly!
Scram!
Get that foul sorcerer and off with his head!
Anyone against me, shall follow with him!
Sire, you can't do this!
Sire
Master Yú has never done anything wrong in all his years in Jiāngdōng.
Sire, you mustn't kill him!
Sorcerer swines must be slaughtered.
General, can't you see the people below revere Yú Jí?
Sire!
Please sir, this isn't the time or place.
You are all men of reason,
why be unreasonable now?
I must vanquish this evil at all costs, for the good of men!
General, please spare him, for our sake!
You wish to rebel, for Yú Jí?!
You dare bewitch the people?
I only speak on behalf of heaven to save people.
I would never take anything from them.
How could that be bewitching them?
If you take nothing, then where did you get your clothes? What do you eat?!
Don't play coy!
If I let you go, all will fall into chaos!
Son, cease this!
Son, you know killing Immortals without reason bears ill!
What? How could you not trust me?!
Mother, you know who I am!
The empire is still in turmoil. My task is not over!
This sorcerer brings disaster, lulling
the officials and generals into subservience
People bend their knees to him!
At this rate, how will I realize my father's dream?
How could I not know?
Yet because you disrespected
the deities did you invoke calamity.
I- I'm scared!
The assassins of the mountain
were Xǔ Gòng's retainers.
I was careless.
But how could you be so foolish,
bringing trouble to your own son!
Quiet!
My son...
Your father was also short-tempered and rash.
He did not heed others,
and died in those mountains.
Do you not understand?
If you are an 'Immortal', why kneel?
How is he?
Why aren't you speaking?
How is it?
You need to tell the Grand Lady and Mrs.
It's not my place to speak on such matters.
Speak.
You can tell me everything.
I  wouldn't dare lie, but our Lord... he is dying.
His Lordship's venom within hasn't healed.
And because of his outburst,
the poison has spread to his body.
It infected his heart and lungs.
This ailment is already too late to heal.
This lowly servant has been well treated by his Lordship.
I regret my inability to heal him.
Mother...
So, it is over...
Thus, summon my brother.
Zhòngmóu...
Sūn Quán
Styled: Zhòngmóu
Zhòngmóu...
The realm is in chaos. But with men of Wúyuè,
Note: Wúyuè is one of the historical names of the Jiāngnán/Jiāngdōng region
and the strength of Three Rivers, you will have a future.
Zǐbù.
Here.
Yes.
In gathering the men of Jiāngdōng, in leading legions through fire,
in challenging the world,
my brother does not compare to me.
Yet in recognizing talent,
in sacrificing one's own being to defend Jiāngdōng,
I do not compare to my brother.
My brother, the hardship father
and I went through to achieve all this...
You must understand.
You!
Now is not the time to cry.
It is up to you now to uphold our family's legacy!
Come!
Come.
Mother, I know my years from Heaven are over
and I can no longer serve you.
Now I shall entrust my cause to my younger brother,
and I hope you will train him day and night.
My father and I will fade into the past.
Be cautious he doesn't become too idle.
Your brother is still young,
he cannot handle state matters.
Wrong.
In internal matters, inquire Zhāng Zhāo.
In external matters, inquire Zhōu Yú.
The only pity is that Zhōu Yú isn't here himself.
I cannot tell him face-to-face!
We have fought together for so many years
Take care of our mother after I'm gone.
Tell Xiaoqiao to inform Zhōu the Youth,
may him aid my brother as he did to me..
Please do not betray me and the love we share!