This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 17
Hanging the seal and locking the gold.
After Cao Cao accepted Guan Yu's three conditions,
Guan Yu missed Liu Bei on one side
and took care of Ladies Gan and Mi on the other
whilst following Cao Cao to Xudu.
Liu Bei lost Xiaopei, Xu Province, Xiapi in rapid succession
and had no choice but to join Yuan Shao.
Zhang Fei broke out of a heavy siege and left towards Mount Mangdang.
Sisters-in-law, you must be exhausted.
However, we still need to travel tomorrow so please rest.
Brother-in-law, you must be exhausted as well, so please return and rest.
General, please rest. We will take our leave.
Lead me to the living quarters.
Why aren't you leading me to the living quarters?
General, some soldiers are sleeping in the streets.
It would be hard for you to escort the two ladies.
I received the Chancellor's order.
This room is just for the general and
the two ladies, especially arranged for you.
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
What? Just this room? For both us and the two ladies?
General, I do not know.
The Chancellor really did personally arrange these living quarters.
How rude!
Does he want to ruin my name
and break the bond between lord and vassal?
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Chancellor.
I watched the night at thy orders,
however, General Guan has been standing outside since this night.
I don't know why he won't leave.
You must serve the ladies well!
Yes.
Chancellor Cao!
I noticed your war cloak is well-worn.
Let this fine silk be your new one, made just for your size.
The distance to Xudu is significant.
For all that could trouble you on the road, I hope you will forgive me.
That...
Everyone, come and take a good look.
It fits well, eh?
Yunchang, why are you so modest?
I am not modest, it's that the old cloak was gifted to me by Imperial Uncle Liu.
Wearing it is like seeing my brother,
and how could I wear it over with your cloak
and forget my elder brother's kindness?
That is why it is on the outside.
Sir, you really are righteous.
Thanks, Chancellor!
Wait!
Yunchang, why is your mount so thin?
My body is heavy and the
horse cannot bear it, thus it is thin.
Yunchang, do you recognize this horse?
That can't possibly be Lü Bu's mount, Red Hare?
Sir, why not ride it for me to see?
This isn't good!
If Guan Yu gets this horse, he might escape and leave forever!
Yunchang would not be so dishonorable.
Besides, Liu Bei's two wives are still in the city.
Chancellor, look!
Get aside!
Get off me!
Chancellor.
Many thanks, Chancellor!
I gave you a silk cloak, yet you wouldn't kneel.
Yet I give you a horse,
and now you kneel in reverence!
Why do you value beasts over men?
Chancellor, this horse can travel
thousands of li in a day, and you gave it to me!
Once I know where my elder brother is,
I can be with him in one day.
You receive this much generosity, yet you still ponder leaving?
Chancellor, I'm very grateful for your kindness!
It's just that though my body is here,
my heart yearns for Imperial
Uncle Liu, and I am unable to forget him!
Brother, you speak poorly!
A man should weigh the value of all matters.
Lord Xuande's grace hardly can compare to the Chancellor's.
Sir, why must you only have the will to leave?
I do know the Chancellor has given me much.
but I also received the imperial
uncle's love. We swore to die together!
I will not betray that oath!
Chancellor, I cannot remain here forever!
I will repay you, sire, then will I depart!
If Xuande has left the world, where would you return?
To the underworld.
This man never forgot his roots.
Yunchang is a righteous man in this world!
Generals, we shall march to Xudu!
Move away!
Return Yunchang home.
Sire, after you.
After you, Xuande.
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Yuán Shào
Styled: Běnchū
Xuande, your face tells me something is amiss.
Xuande,
I don't understand why you are always aggrieved.
I have no news of my two brothers and my family are in the hands of that traitor!
Above, I cannot repay my nation;
below, I cannot repay my family.
How could anyone stay still and not be emotional?
I have always wanted to capture Xudu.
Now we have a growing army to do so.
Cao Cao has treacherously deceived his lord.
My lord, you must punish him!
This will win over and unite the heroes all across the realm!
My lord,
when Cao Cao attacked Xu Province, Xudu
was open, but Your Lordship did not advance!
Now Xu Province has been conquered!
We must not underestimate the enemy!
It would be better to maintain our position and wait for a chance to strike.
My lord, Cao Cao is most treacherous.
If we don't act now, you could
lose your prestige among the people.
Xuande's words are very brilliant!
My lord, Liu Bei's words cannot be trusted!
You!
You belittle our strength with your tongue! Do you deem me to fail?
My lord! To ignore my loyal advice is to doom our men!
Tián Fēng
Styled: Yuánhào
The gall!
Guards, drag him down! Behead him!
Yes!
My lord, if you ignore loyal advice,
it will be too late for regrets!
My lord!
My lord, while Tian Yuanhao has affronted your honor, it being quite contemptible,
to kill your own before mobilizing any troops
would only harm the men's morale.
My lord, please consider this.
Imprison Tian Feng. He will remain there until after I finish this war.
My lord, my lord, if you ignore loyal advice,
it will be too late for regrets!
My lord! My lord!
I hereby assign Yan Liang as the vanguard and to attack Baima!
The main army shall accompany me as scheduled towards Liyang!
As you wish!
Song Xian!
Here!
I've long heard you were a
fierce general under Lü Bu.
Would you honor us by taking on Yan Liang?
Chancellor, watch me seize Yan Liang's head!
See my strength!
Yán Liáng
What a strong general!
Chancellor, Yan Liang killed my friend!
I will risk my life to avenge him! Go!
Yan Liang, I will send you to hell!
Who dare challenge him?
I will!
Xú Huǎng
Styled: Gōngmíng
My lord! My lord!
Stop!
Sound the bells!
Chancellor, I know one man able to match Yan Liang.
Who is it?
Only Guan Yunchang.
But he stated he wouldn't leave until he repays me.
If he repayed me, he would leave.
That's why I didn't let him join the fray.
If Liu Bei was here, he would ally with Yuan Shao.
Thus, if you send Yunchang to defeat Yuan Shào's army,
Yuan Shao would suspect Liu Bei and kill him!
If Liu Bei dies, then who will
Yunchang have to follow?
Good, send someone to Xudu and get Yunchang immediately!
The troops of Hebei are known to be strong.
As I see them, they are nothing
but a pack of puny hounds.
That man under the commander's banner is well dressed,
wielding a blade and
riding a horse. That is Yan Liang.
As I see him, it is nothing short of easily taking his head.
Don't be too arrogant.
I may lack talent, but I can charge in,
seize his head, and present it to you, sire!
There is no joking in warfare!
Yunchang, don't be reckless!
Beat the drums!
Cao Cao killed Yan Liang with Guan Yu,
and valued him more.
He had Emperor Xian of Han enfeoff
Guan Yu as the Precinct-Marquis of Hanshou,
Enfeoffs, or the granting of land in exchange for loyalty,
was a popular tactic for warlords at the time.
forging a seal for him as well.
My lord, my lord, our vanguard, Yan Liang, has been beheaded!
What!
Who killed Yan Liang?
One with a red face and a long beard! He wielded a glaive!
His horse just burst through like no other!
He beheaded Yan Liang, resulting in a major defeat!
Who is this man?
Liu Xuande's younger brother, Guan Yunchang.
My lord-
He killed my favorite general!
You must be colluding with Cao Cao!
Guards!
Here!
Wait! My lord, don't let one-sided words end our alliance!
Because of our 'alliance',
I'll allow you speak for yourself.
Since my defeat at Xu Province, I haven't heard of my brother's survival.
There are many in the world who look similar,
so how could that man with
such traits happen to be Guan Yu?
My lord, let's verify this, then decide.
Did you see the man who killed Yan Liang?
No.
I almost killed a decent man because of you!
My lord, me and General Yan were oathsworn!
Now I must avenge him!
Please let me meet with the enemy!
Only General Wen can avenge this!
I'll give you 100,000 men. Cross the Yellow River and hunt down that fiend!
My lord, you must not!
Jǔ Shòu
We should remain at Yan ford and send a regiment towards Guandu afterwards.
If the situation goes awry when we
cross the river, it will be too late to return!
You burden the army with your talk.
Anymore from you will delay us!
Dispatch the men. We will leave immediately!
Yes!
Wen Chou is a famed
general of Hebei. Who'll take him?
I'll go!
En garde, Wen Chou!
Don't you dare fire!
En garde, knave!
General Guan is a true hero!
Zhāng Liáo
Styled: Wényuǎn
Second Brother!
Did you hear someone call me?
No.
Was someone calling to me?
Liu Bei, what is your excuse this time!?
What did I do wrong?
You?
You had your brother kill a great general!
How is that without crime?
Take him out and behead him!
Wait! Let me have my final word!
My lord. Gentlemen.
Cao Cao has gone after me with restlessness.
Now he's learned of me residing by thy side, fearing our alliance.
Thus he had Yunchang kill the two generals,
aimed to enrage you, sire.
This is to have me be blamed by the nobles of Hebei,
and thus twist thy hand to kill me.
Nobles of Hebei,
will not one of you implore for me to His Excellency?
Why have I been so forsaken?
Xuande! Wait!
Xuande's words are correct.
You almost harmed my virtuous reputation!
I have no way of repaying
Your Lordship's magnanimity!
I will send a trusted messenger to meet with Yunchang in secrecy
so he'll have news of me; he'll rush through the night to join us.
We'll assist you, sire, to execute that traitor,
avenging Yan Liang and Wen Chou! What do you think?
If I can get Yunchang, he'll be worth more than
ten Yan Liangs and Wen Chous combined!
Wait.
Let us fetch brush and ink, and
write this down in front of everyone.
General Guan!
Who is it?
One of your old acquaintances.
Let him in.
Yes!
General Guan!
Sir, who are you, and
why do you claim to be an acquaintance?
Chén Zhèn
Styled: Xiàoqǐ
I am Yuan Shao's subordinate,
Chen Zhen of Nanyang.
This here is Liu Bei's personal letter.
General Guan, please read.
"We made an oath in the Peach Garden,"
"swearing we would die together."
"So why are we alive yet divided,
and with our bond and goal abandoned?"
"If you really covet glory and wealth,"
"I will offer my head for you to achieve it."
"I have not said everything.
I anxiously await your reply."
Elder Brother!
"It's not that I don't want to find you,"
"but that I do not know where you are!"
"Younger brother, how could you betray
our oath for wealth and glory?"
Xuande hopes to see you again.
If you do not want to betray your oath,
then you should go see him now.
Men born within this world.
without being consistent deserve no respect.
I came here openly and I must leave in the same way.
I will write a letter and burden you to give the reply back.
That once I leave Cao Cao,
me and his two sister-in-laws will see him.
But if Cao Cao won't let you leave, what then?
I would rather accept death.
How could I remain here?
Sir, you should write a reply to reassure Lord Liu.
Men who are righteous will not betray;
men who are loyal do not fear death.
When I was young, I studied such, and have a broad understanding of it.
Whenever I see the example of Yang Jueai and Zuo Botao,
I have always sighed and wept.
When I defended Xiapi, it did not have enough resources inside
or soldiers outside. I would have accepted death.
However, knowing your love of your two wives,
I did not kill myself, or that would betray our trust.
And so I allowed myself to be captured, planning to escape.
And now knowing of your location,
I will bid farewell to Cao Cao and leave with your two wives.
Should I ever have evil thoughts, may the gods punish me.
For all our friendship, ink and paper hold every word.
I hope to see you in person. This is with all due respect.
I know my brother's heart and its unsaid questions.
If there are complaints, I am willing to bear them.
Wenyuan, what is the matter?
I have heard you received news
of Xuande and came to congratulate you.
Although my lord is here, I can't see him.
Why congratulate?
The relationship between you and Xuande...
how does it compare to ours?
You and I are good friends.
Xuande and I are both friends, and brothers most of all.
We are also lord and subject.
How could you compare the two?
Now Xuande is at Hebei.
Sir, are you going there or not?
How could I betray my promise?
Wenyuan, you must see the Chancellor
to convey my will on my behalf.
Yunchang has decided?
A just man's words are to the point;
every sentence flies true.
I should have never agreed to his terms.
Chancellor, if not for your promise, how could Yunchang follow us?
If so...
Letting him go is really a pity,
but if you force Yunchang to stay, he will resist.
And that is my dilemma!
Wenyuan, you may leave.
Chancellor?
I have a plan to keep him here.
Yes!
I suppose Wenyuan told him my intentions,
for the Chancellor avoids me.
Inform General Zhang that I have urgent matters to discuss!
General Zhang is resting and will not receive any visitors.
I ask you, sir, to please tell the general that I want to see him.
I know, but I am under specific orders from General Zhang.
General Guan, you are no exception.
What?!
Sir, calm down.
Wenyuan, am I not a guest?
How could you use sleep
as an excuse to reject my visit?
If you won't see me, I will
go see the Chancellor again!
Sir, sorry for the bother.
Why won't the Chancellor see guests?
I'm only a servant within the house.
I know nothing of the Chancellor's affairs.
You know nothing?
Indeed I don't.
My wish to leave is set. How could I stay?
General.
Have you checked carefully?
By your orders, I wouldn't dare make a mistake.
That's good.
Then please tell me the Chancellor's gifts
have all been left here,
and that they must not be touched.
Yes.
Only...
General.
This seal was granted to you by the court.
General, I think you should keep it.
This seal is the Chancellor's doing. Leave it.
General!
"I have learned that my former master is with Yuan Shao."
"With our previous oath, how could I ever betray it?"
"Despite your generosity, my master's cause is more important."
"I have left a special message,
written with the most respect."
"I still have not yet fully paid your kindness, and I hope to do so one day."
Reporting to the Chancellor!
Guan Yu has locked away all the gifted gold and silver,
the ten beauties are housed in a separate room,
the noble seal of Hanshou has been hung up at the hall,
and the men you assigned have all been left behind.
He only took his own followers and luggage, and left from the North Gate.
Chancellor!
I can take 3,000 cavalry to go capture
Guan Yu and deliver him to you, Chancellor!
Chancellor, why not give the order?
Never forgetting his roots, coming and
leaving so cleanly. What a true man!
You all should follow his example.
Are you really letting him go?!
Everybody, back down!
Do not speak of this again!
You have treated Guan Yu extraordinarily well,
yet he left without even a word.
This was an act to humiliate you and it should be avenged.
Now if you let him join Yuan Shao,
it is no different than adding wings to a tiger!
If you don't hunt him down, he'll cause trouble later!
Absolutely not.
I made a promise with him, so I cannot break it!
As your lord, do not chase him!
Wenyuan.
Here.
Yunchang has abandoned his seal and the gold.
Riches could not sway his loyalty;
titles could not stir his ambitions.
Such men have my utmost respect!
He won't have gone far. I will do him one last favor.
Wenyuan, have Yunchang wait for a moment to await my escort.
Gift him a warrior's cloak and passage for the journey.
Let this be our parting memory.