This is a Gentlemen of the Hàn free fansub.
Episode 8
Thrice Offering of Xú Province
Be careful on the road!
Táo Qiān
Styled: "Gōngzǔ"
Yes. Please rest assured, sir.
Táo Qiān's men have murdered my father!
Cáo Cāo
Styled: "Mèngdé"
He will be avenged!
Xiàhóu Dūn will lead the vanguard.
If anyone dares to aid the Xú-province...
Show no mercy!
Yes!
After Cáo Cāo failed to defeat Dǒng Zhuó,
he garrisoned his forces at Shāndōng
and ordered his men to
leave for Lángyá Commandery
to pick up his father and his household and bring them back to Shāndōng.
Along the way in Xú-Province, Táo Qiān,
seeking to become allies with Cáo Cāo,
sent his subordinate, Zhāng Kǎi,
to escort his father along the way.
But Zhāng Kǎi wanted to seize his wealth
and so, en route, he murdered his entire household.
Cáo Cāo, furious from this,
led his soldiers to annihilate the Xú-Province.
Chén Gōng
Styled: "Gōngtái"
If I could save the people of Xú-Province,
I would hand over it's provincial seal to Cáo Cāo,
and let him execute me!
My Lord, you can't do it!
Sir, please don't do it.
My Lord, you have long governed the Xú-Province! The people love you!
Mí Zhú
Styled: "Zizhòng"
But Cáo's army is mighty!
We can't beat them!
But he hasn't breached the walls of the Xú-Province's capital.
You and the people need to unite!
Let me exit the city! I will ask
Kǒng Róng for reinforcements!
But if they don't arrive soon,
the city will have been breached!
'Father of Lord Cáo, Sōng.'
My Lord, there's someone called Chén Gōng who wishes to see you.
No, I won't see anyone!
Yes.
Wait.
Who is it?
He's Chén Gōng.
Which Chén Gōng?
The magistrate who released you in Zhōngmu county,
That Chén Gōng.
Call him in!
Yes.
My Lord.
Gōngtái, have you been well?
I am doing fine, thank you.
I wonder now, Gōngtái, where have you been since we last met?
I am stationed in Dōng Commandery.
That's a good post you have!
My Lord, you jest.
I always knew you and
that Táo Qiān were good friends.
Have you come to beg for him?
That's exactly the reason why I have come.
My Lord, to avenge your esteemed father, you sent an army to siege Xú-Province,
but Táo Qiān is a benevolent lord and not one to abandon justice.
Your father's death was due to Zhāng Kǎi, not Táo Qiān's.
My Lord, what animosity do you have with the people?
Yet wherever you march...
What you're doing is a massacre!
Chén Gōng, back then you abandoned me.
What right do you have to talk to me?!
Táo Qiān murdered my entire family.
I vowed to rip out his gall
and cut out his heart for vengeance!
But sire!
Kǒng Róng
Styled: "Wénjǔ"
Táo Gōngzǔ can relax.
You have a plan to repel the enemy?
I want to introduce you to someone.
Who is it?
Please!
Yes.
Please call over Lord Liú!
Liú Bèi
Styled: "Xuándé"
Master Mí, I've long known about the situation in the Xú-Province.
Táo Gōngzǔ is a benevolent lord.
He should not suffer for other's guilt.
Sir, during the Eighteen Lord's expedition against Dǒng Zhuó,
have you heard of Sir Liú, Guān, and Zhāng, who fought Lǚ Bù at the Hǔláo Pass?
Guān Yǔ
Styled: "Yúnchǎng"
Sir Liú is a true champion of our time.
If he can come aid
the Xú-Province, he can lift the siege.
Sir, I've long known about
your righteousness,
and your ability to save those in need.
Now the Xú-Province stands alone,
their people in peril.
Please save us from this peril.
Lord Xuándé, you are a scion of the Imperial House,
Now Cáo Cāo attacks and subjugates the people.
Why not come to their rescue?
I wouldn't dare refuse,
but I lack the troops to take drastic actions.
Sir, I want to save Táo Gōngzǔ
not just for our friendship,
but also for justice.
Sir, how could you not uphold justice?
Administrator Kǒng.
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: "Yìdé"
In that case, please give us troops
and let me go to Gōngsūn Zàn to borrow 35,000 troops. I will be back afterwards.
Good!
I'm lucky to have met a hero like yourself!
Good! Tomorrow, I will provide you with the troops.
I hope you won't go back on your words.
Sir, who do you think I am?
The sages have said,
"Without trust cannot a man stand."
Whether I bring back soldiers or not,
I will come back to you.
Good!
You were right, Liú Xuándé truly is a hero!
With Lord Xuándé here, the Xú-Province is saved!
Hurry! Hurry!
Open the city gates!
Open the gates for him!
Hurry!
Lord Liú arrives!
My Lord.
My Lord, I was afraid that you had no provisions left
and wouldn't hold out for long,
so I forced my way in
to strategize a way to make the enemy retreat.
To have you come to our rescue,
Truly, it's a sign for mercy
for the people of the Xú-Province!
Mí Zhú.
Yes, sir.
Get the Seal of the Xú-Province.
Yes.
Sir, what is this for?
The nation is in great disorder, and the imperium lost,
Sir, you are a scion of the Hàn,
able to support the nation.
I'm but an old man now, too feeble.
I would gladly gift you the Xú-Province!
My Lord!
The words you thus spoke have humbled me greatly.
Though I am of the Hàn dynasty,
I'm of only humble merits and virtue.
I only hold a lowly office at Píngyuán.
I am here only for the common good.
Sir, the words you spoke...
Does sire suspect me to desire annexing the Xú-Province?
If I harbored such thoughts,
may heavens abandon me!
My words are sincere!
I will submit a memorial to the
imperial court of my will.
Please, sir, please accept this!
I can't do it!
My Lord, right now our foes are besieging our gates.
Our priority should be to repel them.
My Lord, what Lord Liú spoke is true.
Good!
Good! I will write to Cáo Cāo
to urge his retreat.
If he refuses, then we will strike!
Good, good!
Who does Liú Bèi think he is,
asking me to retreat?
Mocking me between the lines.
Come!
Yes, sir!
Kill the messenger.
My Lord, Liú Bèi has come afar,
yet negotiates before using force.
Guō Jiā
Styled: "Fèngxiào"
My Lord should reply with courtesy, lower his guard,
then assault the city walls! The city will fall!
Sir! An urgent report for you!
Pass it!
Report! Lǚ Bù followed Chén Gōng's plan
and captured Shāndōng!
Give me the reports!
Cáo Rén has reported,
"Recently, Chén Gōng of Dōng County
joined Zhāng Miǎo
"and advised Lǚ Bù to seize Shāndōng and advance into Púyáng."
"We only have Juànchéng, Dōng'ā, and Fàn County left, thanks to Xún Yù and others' last ditch effort."
"The rest were taken by Lǚ Bù!"
Cáo Rén couldn't win them back,
so he requested aid.
After that, Lǚ Bù was forced by Lǐ Jué and Guō Sì to leave Cháng'ān.
He joined Yuán Shù,
and then joined Yuán Shào.
He left him and then Zhāng Yáng
to join Zhāng Miǎo like a cur!
Lǚ Bù is a reckless fool.
Who would've thought, that trivial
Chén Gōng could be able to do this,
just for my refusal over the Xú-Province.
My Lord, Shāndōng is lost.
We have no home to return to.
The only way back is to retake our lost lands.
What the General has spoke is true.
The vengeance against Xú-Province must be delayed.
It's better to do Liú Bèi a favor
and withdraw to retake Shāndōng.
We withdraw.
Lord Liú arrives!
My Lord.
Lord Liú, your letter saved us all!
My Lord, you are wrong.
It was only a small favor.
Please! Please!
Good!
Everyone, I have prepared light wine.
A banquet for all you loyal and righteous heroes.
Please?
Please.
Everyone, I have something to say.
I ask you gentlemen to heed it well.
I am old and ill.
My two sons are incapable of administering the province.
Lord Xuándé is of the imperial clan.
With his virtue and talent, he can lead the Xú-Province.
I am willing to retire and heal.
No! No!
Kǒng Wénjǔ wanted me to save the Xú-Province.
It was a just act. I'm not here to seize the Xú-Province,
lest I be known as corrupt and disloyal.
My Lord.
The Hàn Empire is declining and the realm is in anarchy.
Now is the time to rebuild.
the Xú-Province is rich,
with tens of thousands households.
Lord Liú, you are fit to lead us.
This is the place where you can lead by example.
Sir, you mustn't refuse.
I wouldn't dare accept.
Chén Dēng
Styled: "Yuánlóng"
Lord Táo is constantly ill
and mustn't manage affairs.
Sir, you have to accept.
Sire, Yuán Gōnglù's clan has long served as the Three Excellencies.
Those within the four seas look up to him.
And he resides at Shòuchūn, near here.
Why not let him have the Xú-Province?
Yuán Shù is but a a corpse in a tomb!
Why bother with him?
Lord Xuándé, this is a chance sent by the heavens.
If you refuse it,
then you will regret it.
No! I can't accept!
Lord Xuándé, if you refuse me,
I will not rest in peace!
Elder Brother, you should accept Lord Táo's offer.
Furthermore, you are fit to lead the Xú-Province.
Right! It's not like we are forcing him!
He wants to resign,
so refuse?
Do you want to entice me to treachery?!
My Lord, I dare not accept your offer of Xú-Province!
Lord Xuándé, if you are unwilling to do so,
there is a small city near here, called Xiǎopèi.
You may garrison there.
Sir, would you please garrison there
for some time to protect the Xú-Province?
Can you do that?
This...
Sir Xuándé has no need to decline, surely?
Then we can all rest assured.
Thank you, My Lord!
Lǚ Bù
Styled: "Fèngxiān"
Lǚ Bù!
We had no quarrel between us!
Why do you steal my territory?!
Everyone has a share of the Empire's land.
Why can you seize the Xú-Province,
yet I cannot take Shāndōng?
Wretched Lǚ Bu!
Who is willing to take down Lǚ Bu?! Kill that arrogance!
Chén Gōng! A baseborn magistrate like you!
Now you dare work with a tiger
and encourage his troops!
You will die for this!
Cáo Cāo rushed back to
Shāndōng to fight with Lǚ Bù.
Chén Gōng kept on presenting plans to make Cáo Cāo lose one after another.
Where is Cáo Cāo?
That man riding a yellow horse!
That's him!
Go!
My Lord, go! My Lord, go! Go!
In the Battle of Púyáng,
Cáo Cāo almost lost his life,
the same year that locusts started to swarm.
Cáo Cāo, with his provisions empty due to this,
had to retreat to Ju'àn-City.
Lǚ Bù also retreated and fortified inside Púyáng.
And thus, the conflict ceased.
Cáo's army has left...
It must be due to Lǚ Bù's attack on Shāndōng...
They may have retreated,
but they will return by spring.
I can't help but to recall...
...the massacre Cáo's army did in the Xú-Province...
My Lord, you must not worry about it.
Chén Dēng already went to Xiǎopèi
to summon Lord Liú here a long time ago.
The Xú-Province... Do you think...?
My Lord, you tried to resign twice to Xuándé.
Back then, you were still healthy enough,
so Lord Xuándé wouldn't accept it.
Now that you are ill,
he must not be able to refuse.
I hope so...
My Lord.
My Lord, how has your condition gotten to this?
Rise... Rise... Bring seating...
My Lord, you must rest assured. Don't-
I know... Once Cáo Cāo takes revenge on Lǚ Bù...
...He will come for us too...
... The Xú-Province... Is at crisis!
Please sir... Take pity on the poor people!
Preserve this city for Hàn Empire's sake!
My Lord.
My Lord, you have two sons.
Why not let them inherit this duty?
Neither of my sons have the skill...
After I die... I hope you will tutor them...
But never let them into political affairs...
How could I be prepared
for this great responsibility?
Let me recommend one person... That can assist you...
He is called Sūn Qián, of Běihǎi.
Zizhòng.
Here.
Lord Liú is a champion of the times...
I hope... you will serve him well...
My Lord?
My Lord!
Order all in Xú-Province to attend the mourning.
Yes!
What? That bastard Táo Qiān has died?
That Liú Bèi took over Xú-Province with no effort?
He's pushing his luck!
I will kill Liú Bèi first,
then dig out and flay that Táo Qiān's corpse, and avenge my father!
My Lord, what is your order?
Wait.
Xún Yù
Styled: "Wénruò"
Sire, do not send an army to the Xú-Province this time.
Why?
Of old, Hàn Gāozǔ guarded Guānzhōng, and Hàn Guāngwǔ occupied Hénèi.
Both of them were deep-rooted and had firm foundations.
It was enough for them to advance and to retreat whilst having a strong base.
That was how they realized their great undertaking.
If you take the Xú-Province today with
too many soldiers left, it will be hard to maintain;
too few soldiers left, then Lǚ Bù will take advantage and seize it.
If you lose Shāndōng
and fail to take the Xú-Province,
then where would sire retreat?
Even if I let go of my grudge,
I will still obtain the Xú-Province.
Cáo Rén and Xiàhóu Dūn!
Sir!
You two guard Ju'ànchéng!
Yes sir!
Eliminate Lǚ Bù first, remove all potential obstacles.
Yes!
Rally the remnants of our army!
I will end that bastard Cáo!
General, Cáo's army is powerful.
You cannot compete with him.
We need to find shelter first,
and then can we take revenge.
But when you told me to take Shāndōng, you said,
"Cáo Cāo is nothing to be afraid of!"
Gōngtái, if I ally with Yuán Shào again.
How does that sound?
You've left Yuán Shào before.
General, your arrogance cost us nearly all our soldiers.
If you attempt to join him again,
I fear there is no room.
We can first send scouts to the Jì-Province,
if Yuán Shào won't tolerate us, then...
Perhaps joining with Liú Bèi.
What?!
I was going to save the Xú-Province
but now...
Lǚ Bù is a beast! He mustn't be taken in!
He will bring harm!
If it weren't for Lǚ Bù's attack at Shāndōng,
we wouldn't have rescued Xú-Province.
Today, he came to me in need.
How could I let him down?
Brother, you are too kind. Even so, be vigilant.
Yide, you will come with me.
Bring my horse!
Yes!
After I plotted with the Minister over the Masses,
Wáng, to kill Dǒng Zhuō,
we were attacked by Lǐ Jué and Guō Sì, so I wandered east.
Many of the warlords didn't give me shelter.
Today, I came here to join you.
We'll achieve great things together.
How does that sound?
When Cáo Cāo came to attack the Xú-Province,
thanks to your capturing of Shāndōng,
helped lift the siege on the Xú-Province.
Now with Lord Táo's passing, and no one left to govern the Xú-Province,
I stepped up to manage the provincial affairs.
Fortunately,with your presence, I can step down.
I am only a warrior,
How could I administer a province?
General, please accept.
As is it said,
"a strong guest does not oppress the owner."
Please don't doubt us.
If so...
See, when I captured Shāndōng,
I hoped to establish a base to achieve my cause
but fell to that treacherous Cáo's trap.
My army suffered, losing most of its power.
Now that you have taken me in,
in the midst of grim circumstances,
I am grateful and indebted
to sire's righteousness and compassion.
Come! Bring them out to pay respects to Our Lord!
My family now has a place to live,
thanks to Lord Liú's generosity.
You must bow down to him.
No, no! Absolutely not!
Brother, there is no need to be humble.
My Elder Brother is kin of the Hàn!
Who do you think you are!?
Dare claim him as your brother?!
Get over here! Let me have at him!
Even my Elder Brother
refused to accept the seal many times!
Yet why should a cur like you deserve the Xú-Province!?
My younger brother is just raving. Please don't blame him.
I thank you for receiving me over refusal.
But if since your younger brother
won't tolerate me...
I... I will seek refuge elsewhere!
General!
If you go, then it's my great mistake.
My younger brother was just raving,
I'll make him apologize to you another day.
Better I just go!
There is a place called Xiǎopèi, where you can stock up on soldiers and provisions.
General, if you don't mind,
you may garrison your men there.
Good military supplies should
make up for this offense.
General, if...
If so...
I thank you!
When the Son of Heaven
moved the capital to Luòyáng,
news of him hounded by Lǐ and Guō
passed to Shāndōng,
shocking Cáo Cāo and all officers, who had only been planning an assault on Xú-Province.
Sir.
Though Liú Bèi took in Lǚ Bù, I think plans for the Xú-Province ought to be delayed
now that the Emperor has moved to Luòyáng,
This is a matter of great
importance that we need to consider.
Of old, Duke Wén of Jìn reinstated King Xiāng of Zhōu,
Note: When King Xiāng of Zhōu was deposed by his brother.
Duke Wén of Jìn used his power to reinstate the deposed King.
all the warlords accepted that.
When Emperor Gāozǔ of Hàn mourned over Emperor Yì,
Note: Yì was the Emperor of Chǔ, formerly King Huai II.
He was murdered by Xiàng Yǔ, Gāozǔ's rival.
the whole world swore allegiance to him.
Now the Son of Heaven has lost his power and fled.
My sir, if you were to call upon under a righteous cause,
to receive the Emperor and the people's will,
would be to re-establish the heavenly order.
If you don't act now, then others will act first!
The Emperor loses his power
if called upon under a righteous cause
to receive the Emperor and the people's will.
It would be to re-establish the heavenly order.
If I don't act now, then others will act first!
The Son of Heaven thus orders Cáo Cāo to enter the imperial court and assist the royal family!
Cáo Cāo, accept this order!
Your minister, Cáo Cāo, accepts!
Burn it all?
All of it.
General, spare me!
Please spare me for this offense!
I received the nation's grace, of which I shall repay!
Under orders I shall escort the Emperor to the palace,
for the spirit of the nation!
I call upon righteous soldiers against all adversity!
We shall march as legion invincible!
Save the Emperor! Onward to Luòyáng! March!