This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 23
Fall of Yuán Shào
In the seventh year of the Jiàn'ān era,
202 A.D.
Screenwriter:
Zhu Yaoping
Director:
Shen Haofang
Cáo Cāo invaded Yuán Shào, who, in his stress, died.
Before his death, he disinherited his eldest son, Yuán Tán, for his youngest son, Yuán Shàng.
Thus he provoked the struggle between Yuan Tan and Yuan Shang.
Yuan Shang besieged Yuan Tan, compelling him to send Xīn Pí to negotiate his surrender with Cáo Cāo.
Zuǒzhì, I'm thinking of returning to aid you,
but I'm not sure if Yuan Tan's surrender is sincere.
It is not sincere.
Oh? Then it is deceit?
It is no deceit.
My lord, you needn't ask his sincerity.
You only need to ponder their state.
Yuan Shao has been losing for years.
His military is exhausted,
and his advisers executed.
His sons quarrel, his state now divided in two.
Meanwhile famine and disasters plague the people.
Both the wise and simple know this is
Heaven itself calling to end the Yuán clan.
Now Your Excellency is attacking Jì-Province.
If Yuan Shang does not reinforce Jì-Province, then he would lose his base.
But if he does reinforce it,
then Yuan Tan would pursue him.
With your esteemed might, you should strike his fatigued troops
like a wind sweeping through autumn leaves.
The realm's greatest bane is in Hebei.
Pacify Hebei to extend your dominance.
And if you please sir... A gift of wine?
I regret not meeting you sooner!
"The realm's greatest bane is in Hebei."
"Pacify Hebei to extend my dominance."
Good.
With you as his envoy,
even if his surrender is deceit, he will surrender.
Xīn Pí
Styled: Zuǒzhì
Yuán Tán
Styled: Xiǎnsī
This subject, Yuan Tan,
pays his respects to the Chancellor!
Who are the two generals behind you?
Lǚ Kuàng and Lǚ Xiáng pay their respects!
Do you two consider each other blood brothers?
Yes, sir.
I am aware you two were
Yuan Shang's subordinates.
Why are you surrendering now?
Chancellor,
Yuan Shang knows you came to rescue me,
and has fled to Jì-Province.
He ordered those two generals to engage me
but I had told them on the battlefield,
"When my father was alive,
I never treated you with disrespect."
"Now why follow my brother and seek my defeat?"
When they heard reason, they submitted.
I again told them,
"Surrender not to me, but to Chancellor Cao."
Thus these two have come
and await your orders.
When your father was still alive,
despite all the humiliations,
he never once bowed to me!
Though you two pity the Yuan clan,
you cannot stand their brothers' conflict.
Now I will name you as marquises!
You will accompany my army!
Thank you, Chancellor!
Rise!
Chancellor!
I dare ask another question. When do we attack Jì-Province and Yuan Shang?
Our supplies are exhausted
and shipment is treacherous.
You can stay at Píngyuán while I set camp at Lìyáng.
After we clear the supply lines, we will advance.
You two are now his lackeys.
Why are you still doing here!?
Leave!
Report!
Yuan Shang had Yǐn Kǎi guard Máo-fort to maintain supply lines from Shăngdăng!
The vanguard has already set up camp!
Report!
Yuan Shang had Jǔ Kù hold Hándān-city,
leaving Shěn Pèi and Chén Lín to guard Ji-Province!
Troops assaulted Pingyuan overnight!
It seems Yuan Shang is really determined to defeat Yuan Tan and I.
Report!
Yuan Shang's army is pressing
down on Pingyuan! Yuan Tan pleads great danger!
He came so fast!
Gentlemen?
Report!
Sir Xu You has come back from Xuchang!
Chancellor, Yuan Shang has already sent troops to attack Yuan Tan,
yet you still await here.
Are you expecting for lightning to smite the two Yuans?
This is all within my plan.
Cao Hong?
Here!
You'll advance your forces to attack Ji Province.
I'll lead an attack to Mao-fort, then Handan.
We'll meet before the walls of Jì-Province!
Yes, sir!
Generals, heed my orders!
Here!
Prepare at third watch, we move out at daybreak.
Ji-Province will be ours!
Yes sir!
So there is a lightning...
Cáo Cāo marched his army and crushed Yuan Shang,
who had to send the Overseer of Yù-Province, Yin Kui,
to the Cáo Cāo's side to negotiate surrender.
Chancellor?
Yuan Shang's army is decimated, they've ran 50 li away.
Now the Overseer of Yù-Province, Yin Kui is here, under Yuan Shang's orders.
He has come in Yuan Shang's stead to surrender.
First, the elder brother sent someone to surrender
And now, the little brother sends someone to surrender.
Surrender accepted.
Zhāng Liáo. Xú Huǎng.
Sir!
Yuan Shang knows I've granted his surrender, he'll be unprepared.
You two will raid their base at night.
Leave them not a moment of respite
Yes sir!
Whether Yuan Shang is dead or alive,
At dawn, I will receive his surrender.
Roger!
"Surreder"?
Chancellor, we attacked their camp as you wished.
Yuan Shang abandoned all his belongings and fled to Zhōngshān.
Let him go.
Officers!
Sir!
We will assault the Jì-Province!
Shěn Pèi
Styled: Zhēngnán
Shěn Pèi!
Your lord Yuan Shang has fled to Zhōngshān in defeat!
Jì-Province is outmatched, your end is near!
Why not surrender now?
Do you await for the waters
of Zhang River to flush out your city?
Uncle, you've been standing here for two days now.
You should take rest in the tower.
Your subject, Yuán Tán, pays
his respects to the Chancellor!
When our former lord reigned,
Hebei was a force to be reckoned with.
Now, our lord has passed,
and Yuan Tan surrendered
Yuan Shang was going to save our city.
Yet now he's fleeing to Zhōngshān,
before even stepping a foot inside the city.
Sir, we have seized all eighty of
Xīn Pí's kinsmen, young and old!
Bring them here.
Roger.
Bring them up!
Move!
Ji Province is about to fall! It's only a matter of time, so why not surrender now?
Please spare us!
If everyone in the city remains loyal to Shen Pei, then you will all die!
If any of you kills Shen Pei and delivers the city,
you'll be a hero for your people, rewarded as such!
After entering the city,
Chancellor Cao will award you!
Uncle!
Please spare us!
Please spare us, sire!
If any of you that kills Shen Pei and delivers the city,
you'll be a hero for your people, rewarded as such!
After entering the city,
Chancellor Cao will award you!
Stop shouting!
Father! Father!
Father!
Mother!
When we enter Jì Province, do not harm any members of the Yuán clan.
Anyone who surrenders,
soldier or civilian, shall be spared.
Mother!
Grandfather!
Uncle!
Uncle, if you don't trust me,
I can ask Mister Chén to relieve you.
You can't possibly keep going on like this!
It's been three days!
Uncle!
Everybody, back!
Chancellor, look! General Xú has captured Shěn Pèi!
Guō Jiā
Styled: Fèngxiào)
They're coming now.
General Xú, please wait!
You pathetic, murdering mongrel! Look where you are now!
Bastard!
Murderer!
Mongrel!
Pull him up, bring him to see the Chancellor.
Look where you are now!
Shen Pei.
Do you know who opened your gates?
It was your nephew, Shěn Róng!
My nephew swore to live and die with the city. Thus, when the city fell,
he was already a step
ahead of me and died for his nation.
I arrived here yesterday.
Why were there so many archers on the walls?
I only regret it was too few!
I know you are loyal to the Yuan clan. You only did what you had to.
Will you surrender now?
No!
Chancellor!
My entire family was murdered by this bastard!
Even if I've flogged him 800 times,
it'd never be enough to quell my hatred! Chancellor!
In life, I serve as Yuán clan's vassal.
In death, I will serve as Yuan clan's ghost!
I'm not like you lot, hypocrites full of treason and fraud!
Come, kill me now!
Fine. I'll respect your wishes. Anything else?
My lord is in the north, and I do not wish to die facing the south!
Then I'll bury you north of the city.
Much obliged!
When your elder brother, Xīn Píng, received news that you surrendered,
he died in shame!
He wished on his deathbed, for on the day the city fell,
I would have all eighty of your kin executed!
Now they're with Xīn Píng, just as he wanted!
There are so many loyal men in Hebei.
A pity the Yuan clan could not use them to their fullest.
Had they done so, how could I dare eye this place?
Generals, follow me.
Isn't that Chén Lín? Chén Kǒngzhāng?
When Yuan Shao was preparing his armies to attack me,
you had composed an Denunciation Essay,
calling for an expedition against me.
In it, you had listed my crimes,
but why insult even my father and grandfather!?
The arrow was on the bowstring, I had to shoot it.
Chancellor! Execute him! Execute him!
"An arrow that had to be shot", eh?
Bring me your essay tomorrow.
You will follow me to Yuan Shao’s tomb, to pay tribute to Běnchū.
Forward!
Who dares to enter Yuan Mansion
without my knowledge?
News, Chancellor.
Your son is inside.
Insolent whelp, why aren't you coming down?
Cáo Pī
Styled: Zǐhuán)
Father.
You know of my orders?
I knew them.
Then why did you defy them?
Your son knows its wrong,
but I ask my father to meet someone.
Meet with whom?
Who is this?
This is Yuán Xī's wife, Lady Zhēn.
Lady Zhēn
Take good care, do not harm them.
Yes!
Chancellor
Outsiders cannot protect the our house.
We are willing to offer Lady Zhen as a wife for your son.
An outsider cannot protect?
Yes.
Who do you think you are, to speak thusly?
Lady Liu
Why do you dress like this?
Well...
Since this is Yuan Běnchū's wife,
fine silks and grain will be bestowed
Chancellor.
What is it?
I have something to ask.
Go on.
Please bestow to me... the mercy of death.
Truly, a most fitting wife for my son.
General Xǔ, you so worked hard!
Do you think any of you'd gotten in the city without me?
Xŭ Chŭ
Styled: Zhòngkāng
We put our lives at risk
innumerable times to capture this city!
Yet you dare to boast!
Baseborn ignoramuses,
what do you have to yap for?
Chancellor, Xǔ Yōu was too impudent, so I had to kill him.
Ziyuan and I were old friends, and
he humored me often. Why kill him?
General Xǔ.
Please bury Ziyuan with full honors.
Yes sir.
Long ago, Běnchū and I commanded armies together.
Běnchū once asked me:
If matters go awry, where would you go?
I asked him, 'Friend, what are you saying?'
Běnchū said,
To my south cuts a river,
to the north blocks lands of Yān and Dài,
Note: Yān and Dài are ancient names for lands situated in modern-day Hebei and Liaoning.
along with the tribes of the steppes.
If I marched south to conquer, would I succeed?
I replied:
I entrust the wisdom and power of all beneath the heavens,
With virtue on our side, nothing could stop us.
That, I did say before.
Yet now, Běnchū is gone,
and my lament cannot cease!
The people of Hebei have faced fire and steel. Hence, this year their burden of tax will be cut.
Xu Chu?
Here!
Have the headstones of Ju Shou, Shen Pei,
Xīn Píng, and other gentlemen from Hebei prepared.
Yes sir!
Yuan Tan, Yuan Shang,
and Yuan Xi only cared of killing each other.
They are sons most unfilial!
They may still live, but only barely.
Their end will come.
Cáo Hóng, place headstones for them as well.
They shall be with their father.
Yes!
Chen Lin?
I am here.
Take out that Denunciation Essay you wrote back then.
Chén Lín
Styled: Kǒngzhāng
Read it!
The Ducal Minister of Works, Cáo Cāo,
his grandfather Cáo Teng,
with the eunuchs, violated the state with depravity.
His father, Cáo Song, the eunuch-adopted groveler,
with his venal false-name, now a briber of the powerful.
[Cáo] Cāo is heir to the ugly, his obscenity inherent.
Wicked and vile, loves only to carnage...
You...!
Chancellor, please make him stop!
Chancellor!
Read it! Why stop it now?
When this essay was spread to Xǔdū,
I suffered migranes and laid ill in bed.
Reading this text, my senses were opened, my hairs stood on end,
In a cold sweat, my migranes were gone.
Hence could I lead a grand army
to conquer Liyang, to repel Yuan Shao,
and fight him to the last man!
Truly, an essay written like an arrow...
With this arrow loosened,
it made corpses of so many able men on the field,
their souls now in heaven's bosom.
If I, Cáo Cāo, cannot receive this arrow,
How could those able men sleep in the earth
and rest beneath the meadows,
Like stars shining, these words are radiant.
If this text wont be read,
how shall I return this debt of blood to the heavens!?
A war council setup against tyranny (Dong Zhuo),
with drawn swords and beating drums, an order sent out to the East,
to gather all heroes, and absolve their past sins.
Thus would there be unity with Cáo Cāo,
and ally with his ranks.
With his skills like hunting-hounds,
would tooth and nail be used.
Yet [Cáo] Cāo domineers in arrogance.
Abusing men and their nation,
poisoning people and their souls.
Look through all the annals,
of all the consuls most corrupt,
most glutton and hateful,
there stands [Cáo] Cāo worst of all.
Those who bring Cáo Cāo's head,
will be given lands of five thousand households, and a reward of fifty million!
Announcing to all in under heaven, let all men know
of the calamity that befell our holy dynasty.
Thus saith the law.
After Cáo Cāo conquered Jì-Province,
the Yuan brothers continued to war with each other,
causing Yuan Shang to flee to Yōu-Province to join with Yuan Xi.
Yuan Tan had surrendered,
yet still wished to retake Jì-Province.
Cáo Cāo was furious and began war against Yuan Tan.
Yuan Tan attempted to surrender to Cáo Cāo again, but was refused,
and was finally killed by Cao Hong in battle.
Soon, Cáo Cāo sent his troops north to capture Yōu- and Bìng-Provinces,
then battled the Wuhuan-tribes in the west, in pursuit of Yuan Shang and Yuan Xi
and fought the final battle to pacify the north.
- Fèngxiào!
- Chancellor!
You had to go through so much just so we could pacify the desert, and now carry on with illness.
How I can I forgive myself.
Chancellor... Your grace...
... My life can't repay even a fraction of your grace.
Fengxiao, in these harsh lands,
if I wanted to return home, how does that sound?
Armies live on swift action.
We travel thousand miles to attack,
but we're lacking in speed due to our heavy supplies.
We should send light troops to move out and cover ground.
Fengxiao, your words are pertinent.
Then, I will lead veteran troops to advance through the back-road
Let most of the army to return for further orders.
Fengxiao.
You should return with them to recover.
Chancellor!
We will meet again soon.
Chancellor.
The desert is hard to pass through. You need a guide.
After Cáo Cāo confronted Yuan Shang and Yuan Xi in Bailang Mountain,
Chief Tàdùn of Wuhuan lead his horsemen on the unwitting enemy force.
In the ensuing onslaught, Tàdùn was killed.
Yuan Shang and Yuan Xi had to retreat with their few remaining cavalry to Liáodōng.
When Cáo Cāo returned to his lands,
Guo Jia had already passed away, at the age of 38.
His service lasted for eleven years.
Chancellor.
Chancellor has mourned for so long here.
We worry for you, sir.
Yuan Shang and Yuan Xi have ceded to Liáodōng. It will be hard to reach them.
Chancellor, why not return to the capital of Xǔ[chāng]?
If we stay too long, there's a risk Liú Biǎo in Jīng-Province might grow unruly.
Gentlemen, a moment please. This won't take long.
We can return once the Yuan brothers' heads have been delivered
Chancellor.
Gōngsūn Kāng of Liaodong has sent the heads of Yuan Shang and Yuan Xi.
What? How...
Just as Fengxiao predicted.
A letter.
"Yuan Xi and Yuan Shang will flee to Liaodong."
"Sire should not send troops to follow."
Gōngsūn Kāng has feared the unity of the Yuan clan, thus will be suspicious of them.
Were you to use force and haste, they will match it in unity.
But if you stalled,  Gongsun Kang and the Yuans...
They will conspire against one another, as this is their nature.
Indeed.
When I returned, Fengxiao's aide gave this letter to me and said:
“If Chancellor were to follow the letter..."
"The matter of Liaodong will be solved."
We are all veterans with many years behind us.
But Fengxiao was youngest of us.
He was to be my confidant.
Yet he was taken so soon, I cannot but grieve.
Fengxiao is dead.
O Death, have you seized too soon!
East of Jieshi, I gaze at the blue sea.
"Gazing at Dark-Blue Sea" (观沧海) by Cáo Cāo
The water dances gently,
The mountain island towers.
The trees grow thick,
While the grass still lush.
Cold autumn winds blow,
Great waves surge forth.
The path of sun and moon,
like cometh from within.
Brilliant band of stars,
Bursting from its depths.
Oh, to have such luck!
I sing, I shout my ambition.