This is a Gentlemen of the Han free fansub.
Episode 28
The Inferno at Bowang Slope
Third Brother, we'll meet with
Elder Brother soon. How are you feeling?
Second Brother, Cao Cao's army is coming.
It's up to us to do something!
Our bond is unbreakable by now!
Elder Brother.
The Strategos has arrived.
Zhāng Fēi
Styled: Yìdé
Elder brother just keep saying how he's 'like a fish getting water'!
Why not use this 'water' to fight?
My lord —
Zhūgě Liàng
Styled: Kǒngmíng
— when we fight the enemy, please listen to me.
Good brothers, you mustn't shirk responsibilities.
You two should count our troops and
prepare supplies and weapons for when we march.
Guān Yǔ
Styled: Yúncháng
Yes.
Elder Brother, rest assured.
Strategos, please.
You called for me?
Liú Bèi
Styled: Xuándé
Xiahou Dun is leading 100,000 soldiers
towards Bowang Slope.
This is an emergency for us.
Strategos, what do you think?
My lord, what do you think?
When there is an emergency, I look at your face.
You're not afraid of Cao's troops —
— but you fear our strategies don't align.
That's why I asked you to advise me.
How exactly should I handle it?
My lord, the bolder you are, the more plans I will have.
Bring me my sword and seal!
Aye!
These are my personal seal and sword.
I entrust you to lead the three armies.
My lord, your trust... really humbles me.
Xiahou Dun is less than 40 li away from Bowang Slope!
When he comes, we won't be ready!
Agreed!
Second Brother, all of our officers are anxious!
Elder Brother hasn't even said anything!
You and me will charge into the enemy!
You're that eager to die!
Brothers! Brothers!
Zilong, why aren't you at Fancheng and instead here at Xinye?
Zhào Yún
Styled: Zǐlóng
I've come under Strategos's orders.
Outpost-commander.
Here!
Report on the situation!
Aye! Scouts reported that Xiahou Dun's 100,000 army is already 30 li away from Bowang Slope!
Officers, heed me!
Officers, you shall act by these orders.
Each regiment shall coordinate with each other.
Should one of you disobey them...
We shall obey your orders!
Outlook?
Here!
Have men scout on every single movement of the Cao army and report it back!
Yes, sir!
Provisioner.
Here!
You will maintain the supplies in the warehouses and check their distribution.
Report the amount of grain each day! No mistakes!
Be prepared to transport when called!
Yes, sir!
Sentry of Xinye!
Here!
Fortify the city walls and gates.
There shall be no mistakes!
Here!
That's all he has!
Now Xiahou Dun's leading
100,000 soldiers to take Xinye.
He'll have to go just outside Bowang first.
In that engagement, we'll defeat them there.
Guan Yu.
Here.
To the left of Bowang Slope is a mountain called Yu.
To the right is a forest called 'An.'
General Guan?
Have you heard my word?
You said that Bowang Slope is flanked by mountains and forests.
Guide.
Here!
May your explain Bowang Slope's geography?
I specialize in surveying the landscape to guide the armies.
Then tell General Guan about Bowang's geography.
To the left of Bowang is a mountain called Yu.
To the right is a forest called 'An'.
Strategos, what you have said is correct!
I will listen to your orders.
General Guan, lead one thousand troops to ambush at the base of Mount Yu.
If you see the front of the Cao army, do not engage —
— for their supplies will be at their rear.
Once you see the fire signal from the south, you will attack.
Set fire to their supplies, and then pursue them in their confusion!
Yes.
Zhang Fei.
Zhang Fei?
I'm here!
General Zhang —
— set up a thousand soldiers behind
the An-Forest's valleys for an ambush.
When you see the fire signal from the south, attack.
You will set fire to Bowang City's supplies.
I know that.
Fine!
Guan Ping and Liu Feng.
Here!
The two of you will lead five hundred men to make enough fuses for fire.
Wait south of Bowang Slope and as soon as the Cao army arrives, release the flames.
Guān Píng
Liú Fēng
Aye!
Zhao Yun.
Here!
Officer Zilong, you will lead your troops
and be the vanguard.
Prepare to engage at the northern village from Bowang Slope.
When you engage, make sure to lose, and not win.
Why?
As to entice the enemy into going deep within the valley of Bowang.
Yes, sir!
My lord, you can lead another army to reinforce Zilong if necessary.
Yes!
Aim for defeat, not victory.
Understood.
Make sure to lure the enemy in!
Don't worry, Strategos!
All of you shall act as ordered without fail!
Yes, sir!
We're all going out to repel the enemy,
but what are you going to do?
I'll be guarding the county seat.
We go out to fight, while you just sit here and wait!
Third Brother!
Must be very comfortable!
The sword and seal are here if someone disobeys...
Don't you know plans made in camp
can lead to victories thousands of li away?
No more grumbles, my brothers!
Third Brother —
— let us see if his plan really works.
It won't be too late to confront him after.
Sun Qian and Jian Yong.
Here!
Prepare our victory feast,
and to distribute awards according to merit.
Aye.
Disperse.
Yes, sir!
My lord, are you still doubtful?
Not anymore.
Xiàhóu Dūn
Styled: Yuánràng
Where are we?
General Xiahou, we are approaching Xinye.
Ahead of this road is Bowang Slope.
Behind us is the Luochuankou.
Front, into formation!
Yu Jin and Li Dian, suppress their advance!
Yes, sir!
Xu Yuanzhi praised Zhuge Liang in front of the Chancellor.
Claimed he has the talent to sew Heaven and Earth together, with an unpredictable wit.
But now look at this plan!
Using such paltry men as the vanguard against me,
isn't as if using livestock against beasts?
I even boasted to the Chancellor that I will
capture both Liu Bei and Kongming alive!
Today I will fulfill that promise!
You follow Liu Bei like dying men for a corpse!
Witness my spear!
See my spear!
Retreat!
General, don't pursue them!
I fear an ambush!
Liu Xuande, I will capture you!
Get him alive! We will not retreat if we do not catch Liu Bei!
My lord, they are in pursuit of us!
Good. My brothers, let us retreat! Now, now!
Lǐ Diǎn
Styled: Mànchéng
This is bad.
The roads are narrow and the trees are packed.
The enemy might attack us with fire!
Rear troops, halt!
Loose!
We fell to their trap! Retreat!
Retreat!
Retreat! It's an ambush!
Loose!
Retreat now!
Elder brother! Strategos!
You two, please rise.
My liege. Three generals.
Xiahou Dun is routing from defeat.
Cao Cao will lead his main forces here himself soon!
We mustn't show any carelessness!
We obey your command!
Withdraw.
Aye!
Please.
Strategos, I am going to see Liu Biao.
How shall I respond?
First, thank him for the matter of Xiāngyáng.
Should he intend to give Jīng-Xiāng to you,
you must not decline!
Should he ask you to conquer Jiangdong, you must not agree.
Just say you want to go to Xinye to train your troops.
Good.
Liú Biǎo
Styled: Jǐngshēng
Now that the Jiāngxià is lost and Huang Zu was killed,
Jīng-Xiāng is in danger.
Therefore, I invited you, brother, to discuss ways to take revenge.
Huang Zu was too belligerent
and didn't listen to his advisors.
Thus, he was killed. It is truly a pity.
If we leave to go and are take Xiakou, what should we do if Cao Cao attacked Jīng-Province?
So what you're saying is that
we cannot avenge our affront?
Please be patient and calculate our moves.
I am old and sick.
I cannot handle state affairs anymore.
I also asked you to come here for help—
— for after my death, you will be 'the Lord of the Jīng-Province'.
Brother, how can you say that?
How dare I take this responsibility, I—
Brother, please be of sound mind and rest.
I need to think over this matter.
Liu Jingsheng was going to give you Jīng-Province!
My lord, why refuse?
It really is a pity if we miss this chance.
Strategos, say no more!
Jingsheng has treated me with the utmost kindness.
How can I bear exploiting his plight for some land?
My lord, you really are too pure-hearted!
My lord, have you ever considered that if Cao Cao were to attack,
would tiny Xinye be able to hold out long enough?
Furthermore, Jīng-Province is a versatile and strong place.
My lord, if you do not take it, other men will.
My lord, noble son, Liú Qí, has arrived.
Uncle!
Noble son, get up! What's wrong?
Uncle, please save me!
Liú Qí
Uncle!
Noble son, please don't cry. Tell me what's wrong.
Uncle, my stepmother can't tolerate my prescence!
Now she wants Liu Cong to succeed as Governor! She always tries to harm me!
I'll only live for today!
Nephew, this is your personal matter.
Strategos, surely you can help out the noble son.
This is the noble son's own business. How can I involve myself?
Then my life ends here!
Noble son!
If you come to me like this, whatever can we do?
Tommorow, I will just say I am ill.
I'll have the Strategos advise you instead of me.
You can do everything else, noble son.
Sir, please.
Please.
My stepmother can't tolerate me!
I'm in imminent danger!
I beg of you to help me!
I wouldn't dare involve myself in this.
Farewell.
Sir, it is fine! Don't be so hasty!
I have an ancient book that I invite you to read.
Sir?
Fine.
Sir, please.
Sir.
Where is the book?
Sir, my stepmother wants to
kill me and my life is at stake!
How can you have the heart to not help out?
You tricked me with a 'book', so here we are.
As I have said earlier, this is your family affair.
I cannot say more.
Farewell.
Sir!
I need one of your plans to save me, yet you are afraid this will reveal your secrets!
What happens today won't reach heaven nor earth, and what you say is only for my own ears!
Haven't you ever heard "acquaintances shouldn't tangle like relatives?"
How would I dare conceive plans for you, noble son?
Sir, because you refuse to help,
I'll kill myself right before you!
Sir, don't be like that!
I already thought of a good plan.
Please, enlighten me!
Does the young sire know about Shēnshēng  and Chóng'ěr of the Spring and Autumn Period?
Shēnshēng stayed home yet bound to die,
while Chóng'ěr left yet survived.
Note: Shēnshēng (申生) was Crown Prince of Jìn, son of Duke Xiàn of Jìn.
Chóng'ěr would later become Duke Wén of Jìn, one of the Five Hegemons of Spring and Autumn.
Now that Huang Zu has died and Jiāngxià is ungaurded —
—why not, young sire, send word requesting to go station troops and guard Jiāngxià?
Do so, and you can avoid disaster.
Thanks, sir!
Please rise.
My son, (Liu) Qi, petitioned yesterday he would defend Jiāngxià.
I'm afraid it will be difficult for him to hold that. Virtuous brother, what do you think?
Jiāngxià is too strategic.
Someone must always defend it,
but there is no one who can.
I think it is advisable for him to do so.
If you say so,
I hereby order Qi to lead 3,000 to garrison Jiāngxià.
The defense of our south-east can be undertaken by your older son.
Regarding the north-west,
I will try my hardest to defend it.
Good.
I have heard that Cao Cao was at Zaiye,
training his navy at Xuanwu Lake.
He must be going after the south-east.
We cannot let it be undefended.
Brother, do not worry.
I will return to defend Xinye.
Just as Zhuge Liang expected —
Cáo Cāo
Styled: Mèngdé
Cao Cao mustered an army of 500,000 in the 7th month of the same year.
He had his army go south in five different routes.
Jīng-Province was thus in great danger.
Cao Cao's grand army is coming here.
How can we oppose him?
Xinye is so small, we cannot stay there.
I just heard Liu Jingsheng is about to die.
Let's seize this chance to take Jīng-Province
in order to oppose Cao Cao.
Jingsheng has never treated me unfairly, so how can I betray him?
We met face to face, and he asked me to be the Potentate of Jīng-Province, but I declined his offer.
I declined his offer.
If you don't accept it, it will be too late for regrets.
I'll never do anything like that.
Stop!
My father is sickly! I came to see him!
Please let me in!
Cài Mào
Styled: Déguī
Our lord has spoken! You are to fortify Jiāngxià!
Don't worry about internal affairs!
My father is dying! I have to do something about it!
By our lord's orders, no one is to enter!
You abandoned your duties!
If Eastern Wu soldiers arrived at Jiāngxià,
what could you do then?
Go back to Jiāngxià and guard it!
Father!
My father has passed, my brother is at Jiāngxià, and Uncle Liu is at Xinye.
You named me successor. But if brother or uncle ask for help waging war,
how should I proceed?
Good question, young sire.
You should send a letter to Lord Liu Qi of your mourning —
— asking him to hurry back to Jīng-Province to help handle things.
Also to ask for Lord Xuande's help to fight Cao Cao in the north —
— and Sun Quan in the south.
An all-encompassing strategy!
Lǐ Guī! You dare open your mouth!?
You traitor!
You're conspiring to claim the last will, forsaking the elder for the younger!
Soon the nine commanceries of Jīng-Xiāng will be destroyed in the hands of the Cai-clan!
To see you act as such is reason enough to curse your name to hell and back!
Guards, seize him, and behead him!
Filthy traitor, the nine commanderies of Jīng-Xiāng will fall by your hands!
My lord,
Kuǎi Yuè
Styled: Yìdù
Cao Cao's grand army of 500,000 has easily passed our borders.
Now that the elder prince is at Jiāngxià and Xuande at Xinye,
I come to express my condolences.
Jīng-Xiāng is in danger if we raise our troops.
I have a single plan to make the people of Jīng-Xiāng as safe as Mount Tai.
It will also maintain your status as a noble.
If it's a good plan, speak then.
Better to give the nine commanderies to Cao Cao.
Cao Cao will treat you very generously.
Why are you saying that?
I have just inherited my father's lands
but have not even grasped it yet.
How can I abandon it?
My lord—
Disperse.
My lord, how do you compare to Lord Cao?
I cannot compare to him.
Lord Cao has a strong army with many capable generals and advisers.
He captured Lü Bu, destroyed Yuan Shao, and chased Liu Bei. None could best him.
Now he is coming to subjugate the south,
in the name of the court.
If you opposed it, you would be insubordinate.
Just hearing this news of Cao's army approaching has made the people's blood has run cold.
Can you really fight him?
Song Zhong?
Here.
I want you to take this secret letter and present it to the Cao army.
You must not spread any word of this!
Yes.
Elder Brother, Cai Mao sent Song Zhong to the Cao camp with a letter—
—but Second Brother caught him.
When my brother, Jingsheng, has died, Lady Cai did not tell me!
Now the nine commanderies of Jīng-Xiāng are given to Cao Cao!
If my brother's spirit is in heaven—
— why didn't you execute those traitors!
What's happened has happened, so don't dwell on it.
First, we'll kill this dog, then we'll get our troops to cross the river and take Xiāngyáng!
We'll kill Lady Cai and Liu Cong, then fight Cao Cao!
Just leave me be!
Let's go.
My lord,
I come from Jiāngxià.
Upon Liu Jingsheng's death, Lady Cai has illegitimately made Liu Cong as lord.
The elder son begs you to join his forces and go to Xiāngyáng to condemn what is unfolding.
Yī Jí
Styled: Jībó
Where did this come from?
Song Zhong, when was returning from Cao Cao,
and was captured by Yunchang.
If this is the case —
you should go to Xiāngyáng under the pretense of mourning.
Afterwards, invite Liu Cong and Lady Cai over and capture them!
Jīng-Province will be yours!
My liege, with Yi Ji's words, perhaps we can salvage our situation.
Liu Biao trusted me as he was dying!
Now if I seize his son's lands —
— how could I face him when we meet again in the underworld?
If you do not do this —
— when Cao already has Wancheng, what chance do we stand?
I'd rather go to Fancheng to avoid this issue!
The enemy is at Bowang!
How can we oppose them?
Remember, we incinerated the majority of Xiahou Dun's army.
The Cao army is coming now.
My lord, just relax.
I have another trick they'll fall for again.
If you do it, please move the people of Xinye into Fancheng for now.
That...
Good.
My lord, as I expected, the wind is strong.
Tonight, there will be flames in Xinye.
Report! Cao Ren has occupied Xinye!
Generals Guan, Zhang, and Zhao are all ready according to plan!
Good!
Cáo Rén
Styled: Zǐxiào
Enter the city! Enter the city now!
Set up camp and prepare the rations!
Yes!
General, there's a fire in the city!
General! The city's east is in flames!
Hurry! Escape through the East Gate!
Cao Ren, halt!
Hurry! Capture Cao Ren!
Capture Cao Ren!
Release the water!
Cao Ren, you lout!
I've been waiting here for too long!
Run away!